<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A golden trumpet, to rowse vp a drowsie magistrate: or, A patterne for a governors practise drawne from Christs comming to, beholding of, and weeping ouer Hierusalem. As it was founded at Pauls Crosse the 1. of Aprill, 1624. By Iohn Lawrence preacher of the word of God in the citie of London.</title>
            <author>Lawrence, John, preacher of the word of God in London.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 234 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05191</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15325</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104883</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840613</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840613</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5137</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05191)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5137)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 892:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A golden trumpet, to rowse vp a drowsie magistrate: or, A patterne for a governors practise drawne from Christs comming to, beholding of, and weeping ouer Hierusalem. As it was founded at Pauls Crosse the 1. of Aprill, 1624. By Iohn Lawrence preacher of the word of God in the citie of London.</title>
                  <author>Lawrence, John, preacher of the word of God in London.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 104 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Haviland,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A sermon.</note>
                  <note>Print show-through; some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5137:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5137:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A GOLDEN TRVMPET, TO ROWSE VP A DROW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie MAGISTRATE: OR, A PATTERNE FOR A GOVERNORS Practiſe, drawne from CHRISTS comming to, beholding of, and weeping ouer Hieruſalem.</p>
            <p>As it was ſounded at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe the 11. of <hi>Aprill,</hi> 1624.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> IOHN LAWRENCE <hi>Preacher of the Word</hi> of God in the Citie of LONDON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ESA. 53.1. ROM. 10.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Lord, who hath beleeued our report?</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ESA. 58.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Cry aloud, ſpare not: lift vp thy voice like a Trumpet, and ſhew my people their tranſgreſſion, and the houſe of Iacob their ſinnes.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Either reade all or leaue all,</l>
               <l>Let not the Epiſtles be paſt ouer,</l>
               <l>Left idle Readers you diſcouer.</l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by IOHN HAVILAND, 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5137:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5137:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE SIR MARTIN LVMLEY, <hi>Knight,</hi> Lord Maior of the Honourable Citie of <hi>London, and to the Right Worſhipfull (his Brethren) the Aldermen and Sheriffes of the ſame.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">AS ALSO TO THE RIGHT Worſhipfull Knights, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ALLEN APSLEY, his MAIESTIES Lieutenant of the Tower, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> RICHARD MORISON, Lieutenant of his MAIE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIES Ordnance, and S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> BENIAMIN RIDDIARD one of <hi>his Maieſties Officers in the Court of Wards,</hi> IOHN LAWRENCE <hi>wiſheth increaſe of Grace in this life, and Eternall happineſſe in the life to come.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable, Right Worſhipfull:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ithence one profeſſion of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards God, and Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Iuſtice towards man hath combined you together; let me not ſeuer you in this my Dedication:
<pb facs="tcp:5137:3"/>
for my deſire is to manifeſt my dutifull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of you all; therefore I craue your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable conſtruction and acceptance of this my bold enterpriſe. Your <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Worſhips</hi> (by the prouidence of our good God) are the <hi>Generall Captaines</hi> and <hi>Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants</hi> of this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Citie,</hi> and chiefe <hi>Caſtle</hi> of this <hi>Renowned Kingdome,</hi> vnder whoſe gouernment we the Inhabitants of the ſame enioy great peace and tranquillitie; God might gouerne the whole <hi>Vniuerſe</hi> (if it pleaſed him) immediatly by himſelfe, but out of his heauenly wiſdome (for cauſes beſt knowne to himſelfe) hath committed the guiding thereof to <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and <hi>Rulers,</hi> whom with an high ſtile he hath honored, calling them <hi>Gods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47.9.</note> and the <hi>Shields of the earth</hi> to defend from wrongfull euils the children of men; approue your ſelues there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, according to your titles and places. Let the ſound of this <hi>Trumpet</hi> enter not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the eares, but alſo into the heart, that you may the more bee incouraged to draw out the ſword of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and with bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to ranſacke the <hi>irrilegious</hi> corners of
<pb facs="tcp:5137:3"/>
this <hi>Citie.</hi> Follow the counſell of <hi>Cambyſes,</hi> which he gaue to all <hi>Citizens</hi> that deſire the ſafetie of their <hi>Citie;</hi> namely to be moſt <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant when the eies moſt require reſt, that the hurtfull people may feare, as well in darkneſſe as light, night as day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Common-wealth</hi> is compared to a <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall Inſtrument, the ſtrings whereof are the people, &amp; you are the Muſitioners;</hi> therefore as the <hi>Muſitian</hi> cannot abide the ſtrings to iar, nor his <hi>Inſtrument</hi> to be out of tune, no more ſhould you ſuffer the people to be without <hi>manners,</hi> nor the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> without <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> Shew your ſelues carefull in this one thing, that the world may ſee, the longer the tree growes, the better: Offer vnto the Lord <hi>Primitias cordis, &amp; oris tui,</hi> the firſt fruits of your heart and mouth vpon this Altar. Doubtleſſe, it will be an acceptable <hi>Sacrifice</hi> vnto him, <hi>more pleaſing then a Bullocke that hath hornes and hoofes.</hi> I feare I detaine your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> and <hi>Worſhips</hi> too long: therefore I conclude, deſiring Almightie God ſo to bleſſe your gouernment in this Citie, that ſinne may bee puniſhed, wickedneſſe ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed,
<pb facs="tcp:5137:4"/>
the naked cloathed, the hungry re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed, the feeble cheriſhed, Gods word maintained, his Miniſters rewarded, and all the enemies of the truth ſuppreſſed; which God of his mercy giue you hearts to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme for his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus his ſake. AMEN.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours and Worſhips to command to the further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of his power, I. L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5137:4"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE AND TRVLY Religious Knight, Sir ROBERT CARR, Gentleman of his Highneſſe Bed-chamber, <hi>and Keeper of the Princes priuie Purſe:</hi> IOHN LAVVRENCE wiſheth all <hi>health and happineſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orthy Sir, when I call to minde the great fauours which you ſhewed to my father in his life time, I cannot but reprehend my ſelfe of ingratitude, in not performing that dutie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto (for his ſake) I am ſo farre ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged: but ſtudying how I might beſt teſtifie my grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full affection, haue here preſumed to preſent you with the firſt fruits of my poore ſtudies. I could finde no better flowers than thoſe that ſpring from faithfull loue, bound with the bond of dutie, to make my labours gracious in your thoughts: If I preſume too farre, pardon mee, for this my loue is ſprung from the root of your bountifull kindneſſe towards my father, which if euer I forget, I will not ſay with <hi>Dauid, Let my right hand forget her cunning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.5.</note> (for that is nothing) but let <hi>God</hi> himſelfe forget to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent me with any grace, or to follow mee with any bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: Accept therefore (moſt <hi>worthy Sir</hi>) theſe <hi>mites, graines, drops, teares, cries,</hi> as it was by me <hi>ſounded</hi> forth in place of publike meeting; I muſt confeſſe it hath loſt what it then had, for a dead letter cannot be ſo patheticall as a liuing voice; neither can the pen ſo ſet it forth in writing, as the tongue in ſpeaking. <hi>Papias</hi> who was a
<pb facs="tcp:5137:5"/>
companion of <hi>Policarpus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſch. Eccleſ. Hiſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> thought that hee did not ſo much profit by the writings and bookes of the Apoſtles followers, as by the authoritie of the perſons, and the liuely voice of the ſpeakers: Whereupon <hi>Aeſchines,</hi> when hee had read the Oration which <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> had made againſt him, and withall perceiued how the people wondred at the force and excellencie of it, anſwered them thus:<note place="margin">Hier. Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>What would you haue thought, if you had heard him pronounce it with his owne mouth: q.d.</hi> If you are thus rauiſhed with hearing it read, how would you haue beene rauiſhed if you had heard him ſpeake and pronounce it? Howſoeuer, I hope you will looke more vpon my minde and honeſt purpoſe, then vpon the worthineſſe of the worke: I durſt not preſume to ſhroud theſe <hi>vnpoliſhed</hi> ſprigs vnder ſo <hi>vertuous a patronage,</hi> if I did not hope, that as <hi>Dauid</hi> loued <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> for his good father <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathans</hi> ſake; ſo you this lame worke of mine. I humbly intreat you therefore, that as <hi>Vliſſes</hi> was defended vnder the ſhield of <hi>Aiax;</hi> ſo theſe my vnworthy lines may by your fauour, be <hi>patronized</hi> from the enuie of malicious detractors. Our tribe oweth much to you, both for lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and rewarding their labours, for which cauſe I know many ioine with me, to wiſh your whole man, ſoule and body, true perfect ioy in this life, and full accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of glory in the next, for the which I doe and euer will pray,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Whileſt I remaine</hi> IOHN LAVVRENCE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5137:5"/>
            <head>TO ALL MY LOVING Friends and well-willers, both in and without the Liberties of this City of LONDON, Grace and Peace bee multiplied.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian friends, ſome known, all deſired in the Lord; I cannot more fitly ſalute you, then in the phraſe of that diuine Apoſtle:<note place="margin">2 Ep. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. v.</note> 
               <hi>Grace be with you, mercy and peace from God the Father, and from the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Beloued, I wiſh aboue all things that your ſoules may proſper as your bodies doe, for I haue <hi>no greater ioy then to heare that my children walke in the truth:</hi> as I haue laboured to doe you good,<note place="margin">3 Ep. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. v.</note> doe not you requite me with euill; cenſure me not too raſhly for this my forwardneſſe to the Preſſe, nor for my ſlender iudgement in proſecution of my matter. I muſt confeſſe, that in regard of the ſmall number of my yeeres, I may iuſtly incurre the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of preſumption, in that I ſhould bee ſo forward; firſt to preach in ſuch an honourable Aſſembly, next to ſend my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to the worlds view; had I not to the former beene en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned by authority, and to the latter preſſed by importunity, the place of birth had beene the place of buriall, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories of many the graues where I would haue left it, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo earneſtly preſſed thereunto, with the perſwading how much good might come thereby, not onely to the City in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, but to euery mans houſe and family in particular; at laſt condeſcended, not for <hi>affection</hi> or <hi>oſtentation,</hi> but for the glory of my God, and the good of Church and City: It was plaine in preaching, but more plaine in printing, to the end it might not be obſcure to any: if any thing be amiſſe, as ſure it
<pb facs="tcp:5137:6"/>
cannot be perfect, let me requeſt you to mend the fault with a good conceit, and to cure my failing with my good meaning; remember it is an eaſier thing to plucke downe a houſe then to build one: If my ſtile be too homely, then thinke wiſe men deſire rather a carefull then an eloquent <hi>Phyſician;</hi> if wee might not make bookes, wherefore were letters firſt inuented? ſhall the <hi>Epicure</hi> be tolerated to write diſhoneſt things, and ſhall not a Miniſter much more good and needfull things? O yes: accept therefore of this ſmall mite, which at this time I haue caſt into <hi>Gods Treaſury.</hi> Scorne not to reade it becauſe I am young, for the leaſt <hi>ſtarre</hi> hath his light and influence, and there may be ſome vſe of <hi>Goats-haire</hi> to the finiſhing of the <hi>Tabernacle:</hi> I haue many friends to remember in this my iourney, but if I call at euery mans doore, I ſhall be lated, therefore I craue leaue to paſſe by moſt, not for want of any affection (for I loue you all in Ieſus Chriſt) but that in due time I may arriue at my hoped hauen, entring my lodging at a lawfull houre.</p>
            <p>The firſt friend which dwelleth in the way I trauell, is the <hi>Minories</hi> which in times paſt vſed me very kindly, for ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained me when I was deſtitute of outward comfort, affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding both me and mine meat, drinke, and lodging, almoſt two yeeres together, and ſtill would, had not the principall corne beene <hi>blaſted</hi> with the <hi>Eaſterly wind of vaine reports,</hi> and the <hi>mil-dew of euill imaginations;</hi> yet for the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe once receiued, I cannot forget them, for hauing lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them, I cannot chuſe but ſtill loue them: Can the mother forget that Childe which indangered her life moſt? if ſhe could, yet cannot I forget you, I ſpeake it not for any vaine glory, but the more to ſtirre mee vp to returne praiſe to him to whom all praiſe belongeth, that gaue me ſuch an heart to ſeeke the good of your ſoules: my God (and you, if you will but ſpeake the truth) can teſtifie with me, how that I thought not my life deare for your ſakes. This is my comfort, ſo long as I was with you, I omitted no time, wherein I might doe good to your ſoules, but <hi>in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon,</hi> morning, euening, publike, priuate, in Gods
<pb facs="tcp:5137:6"/>
houſe, in my houſe, or in your houſes, was I neuer backward to afford you the <hi>milke of the word,</hi> if I were deſired there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: when you were aſleepe, I was awake; when you were a bed, I was at ſtudy; when you little thought of me, many times was I praying for you, that the Lord would make my Miniſtery <hi>the ſauour of life vnto life, and not the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of death vnto death</hi> to any one of you. But alas, my paines were not noted, but my failings ſtrictly obſerued, and pried into, nay blazed abroad <hi>to the wounding of my ſoule.</hi> It was not you, but <hi>Satan,</hi> who ſought to ſow <hi>tares</hi> where God ſowed <hi>wheat,</hi> and the Lord brought this thing to paſſe for my greater humiliation, yea I know it ſhall worke for my good if the fault be not in my ſelfe: but I ceaſe, deſiring you to eſteeme of me as I of you, my hoped, louing and faithfull friends, ſaluting the worſhipfull Maſter <hi>Mulis,</hi> Maſter <hi>Tice,</hi> Maſter <hi>Vphill,</hi> Maſter <hi>Hauercampe,</hi> with their wiues and families, and all the reſt of that pariſh, wiſhing health and happineſſe to attend you in this life, and eternall glory to be conferd vpon you in the life to come, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I had quite taken leaue of the <hi>Minories</hi> (for I was preuented of that intended curteſie) through the mercy of the Lord my God, I met with another harbor, namely Saint <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garets Fiſh-ſtreet,</hi> where I was louingly receiued, kindly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained and friendly welcommed, but a ruffe Sea of a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging diſcontented minde ſoone wrought my departure from my faithfull friends, for ſuch is the nature of enuy, that both eies ſhall be ventured to extinguiſh one of the parties not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, and <hi>Viper</hi>-like will not ſticke to teare the belly where once it was cheriſhed, but I remember my promiſe was vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to forget, and abſolutely to forgiue in my farewell: ſince my continuance was ſo ſhort, my diſcourſe cannot bee long, therefore I kindly take my leaue of all my louing friends there remaining, euer reſting your poore <hi>Orator</hi> at the throne of grace for your ioy in this life, and euerlaſting happineſſe in the life to come.</p>
            <p>At this time I was like the diſtreſſed traueller, remaining in the wild fields, in the midſt of a tempeſtuous ſtorme, farre
<pb facs="tcp:5137:7"/>
from company, deſtitute of mony, beaten with raine, terrified with thunder, ſtiffe with cold, yet not brought to deſpaire for all theſe miſeries, but ſtill truſted in God who was able to helpe me. Neither was I deceiued in whom I relied, for hee that is called <hi>faithfull,</hi> ſhewed himſelfe moſt <hi>mercifull,</hi> tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his countenance angry to his wonted clemency, giuing me entrance after ſeuen daies abſence, into his Sanctuary at Saint <hi>Margaret Pattens,</hi> alias <hi>Rood-Church,</hi> where recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a moſt free <hi>Election,</hi> I comfortably ſpent my labours al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt two yeeres, reaping the profit of my ſtudies with much ioy; I hope the conuerſion of many ſoules vnto God: but <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> that ſubtill enemy of mankinde, who euer ſought my ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion and ouerthrow, would not ſuffer my foot long to reſt in any place, but by his malicious minde I was ſoone diſpoſſeſſed of my harbour, where had I not found one faithfull friend,<note n="*" place="margin">Saint <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolphs.</hi>
               </note> my habitation had beene like <hi>Dauids</hi> in the <hi>Wilderneſſe;</hi> farre be it from me I ſhould lay any thing <hi>to the charge of Gods choſen,</hi> my ſinnes deſerued my puniſhments had they beene greater, and I pray with Saint <hi>Auguſtine, Hic vre, hic ſeca, vt in aeternum parcas Domine,</hi> id eſt, <hi>Here burne mee, here ſlay me, to ſpare me hereafter,</hi> q.d. Lord doe what thou wilt with my body, ſo that thou wilt but ſaue my ſoule. Nay further, I pray with Saint <hi>Ierome, Vtinam ob Domini mei nomen, atque iuſtitiam, cuncta gentilium turba me perſequatur &amp; tribulet: vtinam in opprobrium meum, ſtolidus hic mundus exurgat, tantum vt ego mercedem Ieſu conſequar;</hi> id eſt, <hi>I would to God that the whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Gentiles, Pagans, and Infidels, would for the name of my God, and for the glory of his Goſpell, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute me and trouble me: I would to God this mad and fooliſh world would riſe vp againſt me for the profeſſion of Gods bleſſed truth, only that I may obtaine Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus for my reward.</hi> For the loue I found generally amongst you all, I haue nothing wherewith to requite it, therefore I onely praiſe my God, and heartily thanke you, amongst which Louers I cannot chuſe but particularize ſome of the beſt, for where moſt kindneſſe hath beene receiued, moſt thankefulneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:5137:7"/>
ſhould be returned; and though I am not able worthily or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently to returne thankes vnto you, yet I hope you will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of what I am able, receiuing theſe few lines as a teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of further ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, I ſalute the worſhipfull Miſtris <hi>Moore,</hi> with whom though my acquaintance be but ſmall, yet for the good I haue both heard and ſeene, cannot chuſe but mention as one of my friends, if my iudgement faile not: they are to be counted the beſt friends that prouoke a man to cleane clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt to God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.5.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren out of enuy ſold him to bee a bond-ſlaue, but God that ſits aboue turned the wheele ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, that enuy brought glory; debaſement, aduancement; for this the Lord ſuffered them to doe for his and their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation. Miſtake me not, I doe not tax you with any iniury, but thanke you for your courteſie, for this be farre from me to grieue any of the Saints, of which I am perſwaded you are one, for the world hath crowned you for <hi>religion, piety</hi> and <hi>bounty,</hi> for <hi>wiſdome, honeſty</hi> and <hi>ciuility,</hi> for <hi>kindneſſe, courteſie</hi> and <hi>modeſty,</hi> and which is moſt of all, for a tender conſcience, ready to releeue the poore members of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, affording ſuccour to his Miniſters, which are deſtitute of outward comfort. <hi>Helen</hi> Queene of <hi>Adiabene,</hi> when ſhee left her owne Country and came to dwell at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> ſhee filled the bellies of the poore with the Cornes of <hi>Aegypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſ. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi> Ioſeph. antiquet. lib. <hi>20.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and the Fruits of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> ſparing for no coſt to doe good to the Saints that were at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> by which your ſelfe hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a very famous report, and I hope the Lord will ſtill make you a beneficiall inſtrument, both to <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> The rarer this vertue is, the more I reuerence it, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending you and your houſhold to <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 20.32.</note> 
               <hi>and to the word of his grace, which is able to build further, and to giue you an inheritance among all them which are ſanctified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maſter Freeman,</hi> you I muſt not forget, vnleſſe I forget my ſelfe, and though I ſhould forget my ſelfe, yet can I not chuſe but remember you, the affection of your heart I haue found by the act of your hand, and your willingneſſe to doe me good hath beene ſeene by your forwardneſſe to ſpeake and
<pb facs="tcp:5137:8"/>
write in my behalfe, vpon any occaſion that hath beene offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto you; a requitall I cannot make, vnleſſe it pleaſe you to accept of my heartieſt prayers, which I ceaſe not to poure out at the throne of grace for you, your wife and family, and for my vnknowne friend, who deſiring them, hath not forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten me.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Goodwin,</hi> my loue is great to your ſoule, though my familiarity be ſmall with your bodily preſence and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourly aſſociation. I wiſh (if it might not be offenſiue) to liue to requite ſome part of your courteſies, for beyond my deſert I haue found you forward to ſubſcribe to any good motion for my good, for which I ſhall euer reſt at your command for any ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Miſtris <hi>Glouer,</hi> much wrong I ſhould doe you, if I neglect to number you amongst my friends, you were the tree that yeelded me the firſt fruit in this City; though it was but ſmall, yet it was comfortable, by reaſon of my neceſſity, ſince you haue watered my ſtudies with your beneficence, that euen my barrenneſſe hath (through your drops) yeelded ſome fruit, I truſt to the comfort of many, your loue to Gods Saints and zeale to the Word doth crowne you; for as women delight not onely to ſee faire Iewels, and curious needle-workes, but to take them out and we are them, ſo I dare boldly ſay, that your care is not onely to know, but to expreſſe and weare the good things you know in your conuerſation. I beſeech God to increaſe his fatherly bleſſings vpon you, and vpon your ſonne, Maſter <hi>Richard Glouer,</hi> and vpon all the reſt of your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and family, to his owne glorie and your endleſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Alkin,</hi> you are the fauour of my heart, and the Father of my being in ſome kinde, if euer I was obliged to any, in a double and treble manner to you. Your care both for me and ouer me, hath beene more fatherlike then friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and not onely to me, but to many more of my Brethren, which if pride doe not too much puffe vp their minds, cannot chuſe but acknowledge: forwith <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodome,</hi> you haue receiued the <hi>Angels and Meſſengers of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.2, 3.</note> with <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:5137:8"/>
you haue courteouſly entertained the ſeruants of <hi>Abraham;</hi> with beleeuing <hi>Rahab,</hi> receiued the <hi>Spies;</hi> nay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.25. <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 2.1.</note> with <hi>Publius in the Ile of Malta,</hi> you haue receiued <hi>Paul;</hi> and with <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Marie</hi> you haue receiued, if not Christ himſelfe, yet Chriſt in his members: nay, with <hi>Lydia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 28.7. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.38.</note> you haue conſtrained the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to ſtaie in your houſe; and with <hi>Tabitha</hi> you are full of <hi>good works</hi> and <hi>almes deeds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 16.15.</note> according to your abilitie. This I know, therefore cannot chuſe but ſpeake, not to the end you ſhould bee puft vp with vaine glorie, but to encourage you in this godly courſe, that at the latter end of your daies, you may with comfort ſay: <hi>I haue fought a good fight, I haue finiſhed my courſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>I haue kept the faith, from henceforth is laid vp for me a crowne of righteouſneſſe, which the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> I ſeale vp my loue with my heartieſt praiers; for you, your Wife, and all the reſt of your Family, euer reſting your true friend.</p>
            <p>Time calls away, the euening requires haſte, I dare not call to any more friends, leſt darkneſſe ouertake me, and preuent me of my hoped hauen: Generally therefore, I ſalute <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Camden, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Parker, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Whitbread, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Milſop, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Smith,</hi> with the reſt of my friends in <hi>Rood Pariſh;</hi> wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all happineſſe to attend you in this life, and eternall glory to be conferred vpon you in the life to come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To Maſter</hi> Gifford, <hi>and all his louing Pariſhioners now dwelling in</hi> Saint Buttolphs Billingſgate, <hi>Iohn Lawrence</hi> wiſheth health and happineſſe.</p>
            <p>Louing friends, yet not more louing then beloued, though you are the laſt in this action, yet not the leaſt in my affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: If I owe a thankefull acknowledgment to any, much more to you; for aboue many you haue comforted my bowels both in word and deed. In health you were ioyfull to receiue me, in ſickneſſe you often came to viſit me: my riſing was your deſire, my falling you did not require. This, and more then this I haue found, which enforceth my pen (becauſe my tongue cannot) to ſet forth the thankefulneſſe of my heart to you for it. I was your Preacher two yeares together, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which time I trauelled in paine, that <hi>Chriſt Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:5137:9"/>
might be formed in you.</hi> All my deſire was your good, not your goods: your ſaluation was the end of my ſtudie, and by ſubmitting to the word, though meanly deliuered by me, you did much encourage my holy entended labours. My de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire was ſtill to haue beene amongst you, but ſithence it might not, my praier was, and ſtill is, that the Lord would giue you a <hi>Paſtor according to his owne heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 3.14.</note> whereby you may be <hi>fed with knowledge and vnderſtanding.</hi> And further, I pray that euery good Miniſter may finde as much comfort from his people as I haue found by you. I know you take no pleaſure to haue your goodneſſe publiſhed, becauſe you account vertues faireſt Theater to be a good conſcience, yet it becomes an ingenious minde to profeſſe by whom he proficeth. I would that euery Pariſh in London vnderſtood your godly diſpoſition and Chriſtian cariage, both in publike and priuate, that they might be prouoked by your vertuous example. I will not dull your eares with too large a diſcourſe: therefore to conclude. I commend this Treatiſe to your diligent reading, and not onely to yours, but to all theirs that loue the truth, and my ſelfe to your Chriſtian praiers, and all of vs to the good grace of God. Thus crauing your pardon, and the continuance of your fauour to him who acknowledgeth himſelfe</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Bound vnto you in all dutie, IOHN LAVVRENCE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Page 88. line 16. for <hi>like time,</hi> reade <hi>life time.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5137:9"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:yhwh">יהוה</g>
                  </p>
               </figure> A GOLDEN TRVMPET, TO ROWSE VP A DROW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie MAGISTRATE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>TEXT, LVKE 19.41.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Et vt appropinquauit, viſa vrbe, fleuit ſuper ea.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as he drew neere, he beheld the Citie, and wept ouer it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, Right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and welbeloued friends, I am here preſented by the hand of the Lord vpon this eminent place, or place of eminency; in perſon to your eies, in voice to your eares, in matter to your iudgements, in nothing to your cenſures, but in all to your benefit; yet not for any wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe in mee, being <hi>Minimus Apoſtolorum,</hi> but for the ſakes of you that loue his truth, for whoſe ſakes he continues the preaching of his truth, with all thoſe bleſſings that attend thereupon. Though I cannot ſo truly complaine with <hi>Moſes,</hi> that I am
<pb facs="tcp:5137:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5137:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:5137:11"/>
ſlow of ſpeech, yet I may fitly complaine with <hi>Eſay,</hi> that <hi>I am a man of polluted lips;</hi> yea, confeſſe with <hi>Ieremy, That I am but a childe,</hi> not onely in yeares, but alſo in vnderſtanding. For my tongue is not fluent, my ſtile is not refined, my phraſe is not eloquent, my matter is but roughly caſt, or caſt roughly ouer, receiuing his forme in a courſe mould, therefore wants that gloſſe or decency that perhaps curious braines, or deepe diuing iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments could ſet vpon it, and all becauſe I want the vigilancy of <hi>Gregorie,</hi> the heauenly gifts of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius,</hi> the diuine ſpirit of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> the golden mouth of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> the ſweet veine of <hi>Lactanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and the ſhining ſtile of <hi>Fulgentius:</hi> yea what not? For I haue <hi>nothing of my ſelfe, my ſufficiency is of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 11.6.</note> therefore that God that bids me <hi>ſow my ſeed,</hi> and <hi>in the euening, not to ſuffer my hand to reſt;</hi> the ſame God (I truſt) will make my words profitable, though not pleaſurable, able to refreſh, though not ſufficient to fill; for though my cookerie cannot prouide <hi>Quailes</hi> and <hi>Manna, Angels food;</hi> yet my induſtry ſhall ſet before you ſufficient to keep hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from the doore, though the courſeſt of the wheat.</p>
            <p>Theſe words (Right Honourable) which are read this day in your eares, is part of the relation of Chriſts progreſſe to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> or as I may tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tearme it, a milde, meeke, gentle, louing, and merciful viſitation, which he came to hold in <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Iewes:</hi> for Chriſt being <hi>a Prieſt for euer, after the order of Melchiſedecke,</hi> had an Epiſcopall dignitie conferred vpon him by God
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5137:11"/>
the Father, ſo that (not without deſert) he became the <hi>great Biſhop of our ſoules</hi> from the beginning, and the primate Metropolitan of all the world; therefore his labours did not onely conſiſt in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, (which is the dutie of euery one that beares the title of <hi>Presbyter</hi>) but alſo in executing all other things that onely remaine to a Biſhop, and ought not to be performed by any, but by ſuch as haue an Epiſcopall dignitie conferred vpon them, of which this is one, <hi>viz.</hi> Once or twice a yeare to hold a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation within the limited Dioceſſe, whereby the abuſes in the Miniſtery might be reformed, Church orders better obſerued and performed. This was the intent of Chriſt by his Viſitation, as may be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the words following; and ſhould bee the intent of euery Biſhop by their Viſitation to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>Of theſe words I will not ſticke to ſay, as <hi>Iacob</hi> ſometimes did of his pretended Veniſon; <hi>The Lord hath brought it to my hand, ſit vp therefore and eat, that thy ſoule may bleſſe me.</hi> Euen ſo, this Text the Lord hath brought vnto mee, <hi>Sit vp therefore and ſeed,</hi> that at the concluſion, <hi>your ſoules may bleſſe me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This root ſends forth three branches,<note place="margin">The text bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched into three parts, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Peters</hi> three Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles.</note> or this fountaine three ſtreames: The firſt, Chriſts appropinquation; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>and as he drew neere:</hi> The ſecond, his deepe contemplation, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he beheld the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:</hi> The third, his great compaſsion, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>and he wept ouer it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THeſe three may fitly bee compared to <hi>Peters</hi> three Tabernacles, which he would haue built
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5137:12"/>
at the <hi>Transfiguration of Chriſt,</hi> and each is full of comfort, yea, fuller of comfort, than <hi>Peters</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles would or could haue beene; for though <hi>Peters</hi> Tabernacles ſhould haue had glorified ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in them all, yet Chriſt but in one, whereas the Tabernacles of my Text haue not glory, but Chriſt in them all. In the firſt, he draweth neere to <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> in the ſecond, he viewes and <hi>beholds Hieruſalem;</hi> in the third, hee laments for <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Or to a 1. Chariot.</note>The firſt is made in the forme of a <hi>Chariot,</hi> wherein we haue Chriſt riding to <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>as he drew neere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Watch-tower.</note>The ſecond is made in the forme of a <hi>Watch-tower,</hi> wherein we haue Chriſt viewing <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he beheld the Citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. Solitary Cloſet.</note>The third is made in the forme of a <hi>Solitarie clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet,</hi> hung round with mourning; wherein we haue Chriſt lamenting for <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>and he wept ouer it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Or to Natures twins.</note>Further, they may bee compared to Natures twinnes: Twinnes being borne together; Natures twins, becauſe they produce each other; his <hi>weeping</hi> is produced by his <hi>beholding;</hi> his <hi>beholding</hi> is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by his <hi>comming.</hi> For had he not <hi>drawne neere,</hi> he neither could haue <hi>beheld</hi> nor <hi>wept</hi> as man, but <hi>drawing neere,</hi> he doth both: For his <hi>comming</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets a <hi>beholding,</hi> and his <hi>beholding</hi> their miſerable faſhion inforceth abundant teares of compaſſion, to diſtill from his heauenly eies: therefore as <hi>Pilate</hi> ſaid in another caſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 19.5.</note> 
               <hi>Ecce homo, behold the man,</hi> ſo I in this place vſe the ſame words, <hi>Ecce homo, behold
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5137:12"/>
the man.</hi> A man, nay more then a man; For, for an Obiect at this time, <hi>behold</hi> the true, naturall, deare, and eternall Sonne of God, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the nature of man; and <hi>behold</hi> him in his three-fold Tabernacle. Firſt, <hi>behold</hi> him in his <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propinquation:</hi> Secondly, <hi>behold</hi> him in his deepe <hi>Contemplation:</hi> Thirdly, <hi>behold</hi> him in his great <hi>Compaſsion:</hi> which three may inforce attention with your eares, Meditation in your hearts. It hath beene an ancient ſaying, or the ſaying of the Ancients, that there are three things which will moue atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to wit, the Author, if he be famous; the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if it be of conſequence; the manner, if it bee compendious; all which three doe meet and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre in this my Text. For the firſt, the Author of theſe words is more famous than all men, being as he is indeed, the very Sonne of God: ſecondly, for the matter, it is of great, yea, exceeding great conſequence; for it ſets out to vs the feruent loue the Lord beares to miſerable men: thirdly, for the manner, it is very compendious, for in ten words the fountaine of Mercy is deſcribed in mourning for the loſſe of preſeruation, and the gulfe of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is vnfolded by way of Implication. Therefore as <hi>Ieſus</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Iewes</hi> concerning <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 11.7.</note> 
               <hi>What went yee out into the wilderneſſe to ſee? A reed ſhaken with the wind?</hi> As if he had ſaid, Surely you would neuer haue taken ſuch paines, or aduentured your ſelues into ſuch a deſart, but in hope to haue ſeene ſome ſtrange ſight, great wonder, or rare matter: So I ſay to you, What came you hither to ſee? or rather to heare? why haue you left your owne houſes, to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5137:13"/>
preſent your ſelues in this publique place of mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but onely in hope to heare ſome rare thing, new matter, or ſtrange newes? Then lend me your attention: if any thing be worthy your hearing, then this is; for here you haue <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> the Sonne of God, making his laſt iourney to <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> his firſt progreſſe, and his firſt progreſſe his laſt Viſitation: not ſubſtituting others, but performing it himſelfe, whileſt he was able in his owne perſon: and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into this his Viſitation, is with great ſorrow; For when <hi>hee drew neere, he beheld the Citie and wept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let vs proceed, according as our Text is branched out vnto vs in our diuiſion, and in the handling thereof, let mee intreat you not to runne before me in your quicke conceits, nor to wrong your ſelues in your earneſt expectations; for if you looke for ſtrange things from theſe words, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentable matter from this Text, you may bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued as <hi>Iacob</hi> was, who whileſt he dreamt of beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull <hi>Rachel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.10.</note> found nothing but a <hi>bleare eied Leah. If I ſtudy to pleaſe man, I am not the ſeruant of Chriſt.</hi> Cenſure mee not for what I ſay; yet if you doe, I weigh it not: for as I deſire not to bee applauded by men, I leſſe deeme to <hi>be iudged</hi> of men: yet to purge the minde from ſecret cenſures, and the heart from miſconceiuing thoughts, let mee requeſt you to goe faire and eaſily along with me, till we arriue at our hoped hauen; I meane the end of our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe at this time: then if any thing bee ſo happy as to fill the ſoule with comfort, aſcribe the honor to God who hath inabled me. If any thing bee ſo
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5137:13"/>
vnhappy, as to diſtaſte the ſpirituall, pardon mee, and thinke my time of preparation but ſmall, to prouide my ſelfe fitting with ſuch ſhort warning, for ſo iudicious an Auditory. Thus then as God ſhall aſſiſt me, time and ſtrength permit me, and your Chriſtian patience ſuffer me, I doe begin: and firſt of his <hi>Appropinquation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>And as he drew neere:</hi>
               <note place="margin">In the firſt part or Tabernacle Chriſts Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquation, where 1. <hi>Abſentia.</hi> 2. <hi>Praeſentia.</hi> 3. <hi>Diligentia.</hi>
               </note> This firſt Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle hath three roomes, or the firſt body that proceeds from our root, hath three branches; <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia, Praeſentia, &amp; Diligentia.</hi> Abſence is implied, preſence is deſired, diligence deſcribed. Firſt, his <hi>Appropinquation</hi> implies his <hi>abſence;</hi> for how can it be ſaid, <hi>he drew neere the Citie,</hi> vnleſſe he were firſt <hi>abſent</hi> from the Citie? but he was (at this time) <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> from the <hi>Citie;</hi> therefore it is ſaid, <hi>he drew neere vnto the Citie:</hi> from which implication wee note, That <hi>the greateſt, gloriouſeſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Doctrine.</note> 
               <hi>and famouſeſt place in the world, may be deſtitute of the preſence of Chriſt.</hi> All this was <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> yet Chriſt is abſent from it: Firſt, it was great, in regard of the large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſituation and popularitie of people: ſecondly, it was glorious, in regard of the ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous buildings and great riches: thirdly, it was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, in regard of the ancient monuments, and many victories which the Lord bleſſed them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all aboue any other Nation; yet was not Chriſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with them. I need not inſtance for example an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Rome,</hi> beautifull <hi>Paris,</hi> famous <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> with the reſidue of the great Cities in the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I will iudge of none, yet this I am ſure of, how that the greateſt places may be deſtitute of Chriſts
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5137:14"/>
preſence, for the preſence of Chriſt is not tied to any place for the greatneſſe of it, but for the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it; he cannot <hi>partake</hi> with <hi>Iniquitie,</hi> neither ſhall the <hi>euill doer</hi> enioy his preſence. For as light and darkneſſe, life and death, fire and water, cannot agree together, no more can the preſence of Chriſt with a wicked generation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> God is <hi>omni</hi>-preſent in all places, at all times, with all perſons, therefore no place nor perſon can be deſtitute of the preſence of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Reſp.</note>It is true, the <hi>Lord filleth heauen and earth,</hi> and the Propheticall <hi>Dauid</hi> doth acknowledge as much,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 1.23, 24. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.7.</note> how <hi>that a man can flie into no place where the Lord is not preſent:</hi> But for the cleering of the point, we muſt diſtinguiſh. The preſence of the Lord is two-fold, either <hi>Corporall</hi> or <hi>Spirituall:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Lords pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence corporall or ſpirituall.</note> his <hi>Corporall</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, is his being with any people in his humane Nature; but of this preſence, both we and all other people are deſtitute: his humane Nature onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in heauen, <hi>Sitting at the right hand of God in the glory of the Father,</hi> and there ſhall ſit till his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond comming in the Clouds to iudgement.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His preſence Spirituall is either generall or ſpeciall. <hi>Praeſentia.</hi> 1. <hi>Abſoluta.</hi> 2. <hi>Specialis &amp; Approbationis. Act.</hi> 17.28. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.14. <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.</note>Secondly, his <hi>ſpirituall</hi> preſence is two-fold, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and more ſpeciall: his <hi>generall</hi> preſence is as the Schoole-men call it, his abſolute preſence, which is his eſſentiall being in any place, &amp; ſo he is preſent with all the world, as well with the Reprobates as the godly, the vnreaſonable creatures as the reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable: by this preſence we <hi>all liue, moue, and haue our being:</hi> By this preſence, he is with <hi>Cain</hi> to affright him, with <hi>Iudas</hi> to confound him, with <hi>Saul</hi> to vex him, with <hi>Balſhazer</hi> to amaze him, with all the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5137:14"/>
wicked to terrifie and ouerthrow them for euer.</p>
            <p>The ſecond <hi>ſpirituall</hi> preſence is <hi>ſpeciall</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,<note place="margin">Speciall ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall preſence what.</note> called in Scripture, the <hi>loue of God,</hi> or the <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God,</hi> and thus he is preſent with his Elect and none elſe. When <hi>Abraham</hi> made a requeſt for <hi>Iſmael,</hi> it was onely that the Lord would ſuffer him to <hi>liue in his preſence,</hi> that is, in his fauour and loue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.18.</note> but this preſence, none that are wicked can attaine vnto. As for that preſence which Ieruſalem wanted was his <hi>corporall</hi> preſence, and if I miſtake not, his <hi>ſpirituall</hi> alſo; for theſe Iewes did reiect him, both in his owne perſon, and in the perſon of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, continually refuſing thoſe <hi>which were ſent vnto them</hi> for their owne good,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37.</note> therefore it was iuſt with God to leaue them deſtitute of his <hi>ſpeciall</hi> preſence, as ſoone after wofully came to paſſe.</p>
            <p>Whereſoeuer the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of God is,<note place="margin">Ob.</note> there is alſo his <hi>ſpeciall</hi> preſence: but theſe Iewes had the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God, therefore his ſpeciall preſence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ordinances of God doe not tie Chriſt alwaies to be preſent:<note place="margin">Reſp.</note> Then ſhould his ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall preſence remaine amongſt many Reprobates,<note place="margin">Gods ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces may bee where hee is not preſent in a ſpeciall manner.</note> for thoſe which haue not the feare of God before their eies, can many times get his ordinances, and that into their houſes, yea into their hands, yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a whit the neerer is the ſpeciall preſence of Chriſt, becauſe they want them in their ſoules. It is not <hi>Michahs</hi> getting a Prophet into his houſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 17.13.</note> can inforce the Lord euer a whit the more to be preſent, for the <hi>Arke</hi> may bee in the middeſt of Iſraels army,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.10, 11.</note> yet they put to flight by their enemies, becauſe their ſinnes had baniſhed the ſpeciall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5137:15"/>
of the Lord from their ſoules. But let this be granted, though it neuer can be prooued, yet was the <hi>ſpeciall</hi> preſence of Chriſt now fled or flying from theſe Iewes, and all by reaſon they wanted his ordinances: It is true, they were offered, but reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; for if Chriſt walke but towards the <hi>Gada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens,</hi> this ſalutation ſhall meet him as a hedge to preuent him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. v. vlt.</note> I pray thee <hi>depart out of our Coaſts:</hi> thus they made the preſence of Chriſt a burthen to their ſoules;<note place="margin">and 11.30.</note> his <hi>yoake (though light)</hi> too heauy for them to beare, and neuer could haue inward peace, till they baniſhed his preſence from their Country: I cannot deny, but that they had the Law, and the Sacraments of the law, yet not the ſpeciall preſence of Chriſt in them, for theſe things were now aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, new things ſubſtituted and ſet vp in their roome: Needs therfore muſt the ſhadow giue place when the ſubſtance approacheth. If it haue turned vs ouer to a better Tutor, it ſelfe hath no more to doe with vs, being only but a <hi>Schoole-maſter,</hi> to ſend vs <hi>to Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 19.42.</note> but as for that Law which Chriſt brought, the Iewes wanted, for it was hid <hi>from</hi> their <hi>eyes,</hi> therefore they needs muſt bee deſtitute of the ſpeciall preſence of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>If Ieruſalem that famous City which God lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d aboue all the Cities in the world; If that place, I ſay, was or could be deſtitute of the ſpeciall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt, then let not Rome boaſt too much of her holineſſe and outward flouriſhing eſtate, let her neuer ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ap.</hi> 18.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>I am a Queene and ſhall ſee no mourning,</hi> for ſince the <hi>bloud of all the Prophets</hi> are onely <hi>found in her, her fall ſhall come ſuddenly:</hi> But what haue
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5137:15"/>
we to doe with <hi>Rome?</hi> and concerning her Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, God grant wee neuer may. Let vs therefore turne vnto our ſelues, looking more neere home, for here wee ſhall finde imployments ſufficient a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelues:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>If iudgement beginne at the houſe of God, where ſhall the wicked and vngodly appeare?</hi> if God deale thus with a <hi>greene tree,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k.</hi> 23.31.</note> 
               <hi>what ſhall become of the dry?</hi> If the Iewes ſo ſmart, Gods eldeſt ſons, what ſhall the Gentiles looke for, his youngeſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants? Surely, ſinne cannot goe long vnpuniſhed, for Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his Booke of 50. Homilies,<note place="margin">Aug. lib. <hi>50.</hi> Hom. Hom. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> Homily 21. ſaith that <hi>Iuſtitia eſt, vt puniat peccatum,</hi> It is a part of Gods Iuſtice to puniſh ſinne, yea,<note place="margin">No greater pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to a City, than to be deſtitute of Chriſts ſpeciall preſence.</note> a part of his actiue iuſtice. But how he will puniſh it in vs we doe not know, worſe he cannot puniſh it in any nation, than to depriue the ſinner of his ſpeciall preſence, and that firſt becauſe his preſence is a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>protection:</hi> For if <hi>the Lord keepe not the City,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>the watchman wake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h but in vaine;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. It is a Cities protection. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.4, 5, 6, 7. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.18. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.25. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16.3. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 3.12.</note> It is not <hi>Goliahs</hi> great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nor <hi>Azas</hi> ſwiftneſſe, nor <hi>Abſolons</hi> beauty, nor <hi>Achitophels</hi> policy, <hi>Sampſons</hi> ſtrength, <hi>Salomons</hi> wiſdome, <hi>Croeſus</hi> purſe, nor any thing vnder the Sunne, that can be the ſafety of a City, but only the preſence of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Secondly, his preſence is a Cities <hi>direction:</hi> For as the wiſe men were led from the Eaſt to <hi>Bethelem</hi> by a <hi>Starre;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Direct. Mat.</hi> 2.9.</note> ſo are thoſe people where Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, led from nature to grace, from ſinne to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, from bad to good, from good to better; for Chriſt is that <hi>bright morning ſtar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.16.</note> who will not ſuffer any to lodge long in ſin, if they direct but their courſe to that hauen whereunto Chriſt will guide them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:5137:16"/>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>Inſtruct.</hi>
               </note>Thirdly, his preſence is a Cities <hi>Inſtruction:</hi> For as the Sunne diſcouers all darke places, ſo wil Chriſt who is that <hi>Sunne of righteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 4.1.</note> or righteous ſunne, by his preſence, vnmaske the face, take off the vaile, and chaſe away the foggy miſts of ſinne and ſuperſtition from the heart,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7. <hi>&amp; Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>Prou.</hi> 1.4.</note> filling the ignorant with knowledge, the ſimple with vnderſtanding, and all with grace.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. <hi>Conſol.</hi>
               </note>Fourthly, his preſence is a Cities <hi>comfort</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation,</hi> and that becauſe he is all things beneficiall, and the end of our hopes; hee is <hi>a Sword, Water, Milke, Wine, a Treaſure, a Salue, a Garment, a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, a Bridegroome, a Crowne, a Pearle, a King, and a Key:</hi> See what benefit theſe or any of theſe is to a Nation, a Family, or a priuate perſon, the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit is Chriſt, where his ſpeciall preſence remaines, for he is a Sword to defend vs, Water to waſh vs, Milke to nouriſh vs, Wine to reioyce vs, a Treaſure to enrich vs, a Salue to heale vs, a Phyſician to cure vs, a Garment to cloath vs, a Shepherd to feede vs, a Bridegroome to marry vs, a Crowne to honour vs, a Pearle to decke vs, a King to gouerne vs, and a Key to open and vnlocke Heauen gates vnto vs. What ſhall I ſay? but onely as a man rauiſhed, cry from the bottome of my ſoule, O happy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the people that haue the Lord for their God; they ſhall be fed as a Flocke, foſtered as a Family, dreſſed as a Vineyard, decked as a Spouſe, and crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as a Queene. Contrariwiſe, where Chriſts pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is departed, to that people I may ſay, O miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and vnhappy men and women, good had it beene for you you had neuer beene borne, but as the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5137:16"/>
vntimely fruit of the wombe had periſhed and been no more; for better no man, than a man without Chriſt, and no City, than a City deſtitute of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. When <hi>Lot</hi> forſooke <hi>Sodome,</hi> it was ſoone con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed; and if Chriſts preſence forſake our land, it will ſoone be deſtroyed; for that place which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of the preſence of Chriſt, may complaine as ſometimes <hi>Martha</hi> did to our Sauiour,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.21.</note> 
               <hi>Lord if thou hadſt beene here, our brother LaZarus had not beene dead:</hi> So if thy preſence had ſtill remained with vs, our Kingdome had not beene waſted, Magiſtrates not corrupted, Lawes not violated, Lawyers not bribed, Faith and Vertue not baniſhed, Miniſters mouthes not ſtopped, but all goodnes cheriſhed, &amp; all men amended. To conclude, I leaue this branch with a word of exhortation, beſeeching you ſo to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine Chriſt though not in himſelfe (for that is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, ſeeing his body only remaines in Heauen) yet in his members, that hee neuer may finde any iuſt cauſe of departing from vs. I dare boldly ſay, and that with a reioycing heart, that England yet enioyes the ſpeciall preſence of the Lord, to the great comfort of thoſe that ſeeke his face, but how long we ſhall enioy the ſame, the wiſdome of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> is not able to declare: could we keepe from ſin, we ſhould euer enioy a Sauiour, but if ſinne be har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in the ſoule, and rule in the life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, it will proue as a miſt or a darke cloud, to obſcure the ſpeciall preſence of Chriſt from our Kingdome: I feare, nay know, that offence is giuen, &amp; am not much vnſure that offence is taken, for ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity growes ſo faſt, that it hath couered the whole
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5137:17"/>
Land, yet who doth ſeeke to cut it downe? neither is there but few (if any) that ſtands in the gap to intreat the Lord for vs; what ſhall I ſay, <hi>Am I a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 7.14.</note> No, <hi>nor the Sonne of a Prophet,</hi> yet this I dare boldly ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Vnleſſe we ſuddenly repent, we periſh;</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we muſt forſake our ſins, or elſe the preſence of Chriſt will forſake our ſoules. I wonder we haue not loſt him before this day: had it not beene more of his goodneſſe than of our kindneſſe, <hi>London</hi> had long ſince beene left as <hi>Sodome,</hi> and rak't vp in Aſhes like to <hi>Gomorra:</hi> For how is his <hi>Name</hi> blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed, his <hi>Sabbaths</hi> profaned, his <hi>Word</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, his <hi>Sacraments</hi> neglected, his <hi>Miniſters</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, his <hi>Children</hi> derided, his holy <hi>Spirit</hi> grieued by many ſinnes, which I will not ſay are publikely maintained, but am ſure they are openly practiſed, which drawes teares afreſh from the eyes of the Sonne of God, and makes him for want of a <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> to weepe ouer <hi>London,</hi> as though it would proue a ſecond <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to crucifie his body a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: but the Lord in mercy amend it, and giue you hearts that beares the ſword of Iuſtice to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, that Chriſt may not wilfully be baniſhed, but kindly receiued, friendly welcommed, louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertained to vs and our poſterity to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond roome of the firſt Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle is <hi>Praeſentia.</hi>
               </note>The ſecond roome in our Tabernacle or Branch, proceeding from our trees firſt bodie or bole, is <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia;</hi> yet not ſo much in perſon as in affection; not by the people required, but by Chriſt deſired: he longed to be preſent with them,<note place="margin">Chriſt drawes neere either</note> therefore drew neere vnto them. Chriſt may be ſaid to draw neere
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5137:17"/>
a people, either <hi>Corporally</hi> or <hi>Spiritually;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Corporally. 1. in himſelfe. 2. in his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</note> 
               <hi>Corporally in himſelfe,</hi> or <hi>in his members.</hi> In himſelfe, when he rides or goes to any place in his humane body and ſoule, and thus he drew neere at this time to <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> for his body was carried on the backe of a ſilly <hi>Aſſe,</hi> which he ſent his Diſciples to borrow at the hand of a certaine Farmer.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 19.35.</note> And vpon this Aſſe he did take his progreſſe toward <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> now drawing neere to the Citie: but thus he neuer ſhall draw neere to any place againe, his body remaining onely glorified in heauen.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he drawes neere <hi>Spiritually,</hi> and that in <hi>loue or affection.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Or ſpiritually in loue and affection.</note> Thus alſo he may be ſaid to draw neere to <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> for this iourney was not onely <hi>pedibus, ſed affectibus,</hi> not by the motion of the feet, but of the affections; or as <hi>Lira in locum</hi> hath it,<note place="margin">Lira in locum.</note> 
               <hi>Non ſolum corporis greſſu, ſed etiam compaſsionis affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu:</hi> He came not onely with the feet of his body, but alſo with the affection of his compaſſion. When he begins to worke by his holy Spirit, Faith, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and Sanctification in the hearts of a Nation, he may bee ſaid to draw neere that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: For ſaies Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.22.</note> if <hi>I had come and ſpoken vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, they had not had ſinne,</hi> but now they haue no cloake for their ſinne: that is; if I had not come, they neuer would haue knowne themſelues to bee ſinners, whereas by my comming they now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it: ſo that we conclude, if any Nation bee brought to a true ſight and ſenſe of ſinne, it is by Chriſt his drawing neere: but in that he here is ſaid to <hi>draw neere Hieruſalem,</hi> we note,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Lord will not abſent himſelfe for euer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Doctr.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>but
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5137:18"/>
at laſt will draw neere to the people of his paſture:</hi> He is a God which cannot <hi>alwaies be chiding,</hi> neither wil he <hi>forſake his Inheritance for euer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 103.9.</note> His <hi>wrath endures but a moment,</hi> but <hi>in his fauour</hi> is euerlaſting <hi>life: Heauineſſe may endure for a night, but ioy commeth in the morning.</hi> The Clouds of our ſinnes ſhall not alwaies ſhadow the loue of our Sauiour, but as the Sunne, at length ſhall breake forth to our endleſſe comfort. Theſe Iewes, though they were ſtubborne and rebellious, hardning their hearts, increaſing their hatred againſt Chriſt, yet will hee not quite leaue and forſake them, but once more reſolues to draw <hi>neere</hi> vnto them: and herein hath he expreſſed his wonderfull loue, by which hee would faine ouercome our ingratitude, in that he refuſes not to draw neere to miſerable ſinners.<note place="margin">Men willingly draw not neere for good to 1. Strangers, 2. Poore and miſerable, 3. Profeſſed enemies.</note> There bee three ſorts of men in the world, which we would bee loth to draw neere vnto for good: the firſt, are ſtrangers; the ſecond, are poore and miſerable; the third, are profeſſed enemies: As for ſtrangers, we would not come neere vnto them; for poore and miſerable, we ſcorne to come neere vnto them; for profeſſed ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iewes,</hi> all theſe, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Chriſt drawes neere to them.</note> we dare not come neere vnto them. All theſe were the <hi>Iewes</hi> to Ieſus, yet <hi>hee drawes neere</hi> vnto them. Firſt, they were ſtrangers, and that in Grace and Goodneſſe, yet Chriſt will come vnto them: Secondly, they were poore and miſerable, and that in regard of their ſinnes, yet Chriſt could not be kept from them: Thirdly, they were profeſſed, nay proteſted enemies, for ſurely in their hearts they had vowed to kill him, elſe would they not haue ſpread ſo many nets to take him: yet hee
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5137:18"/>
ſtriues to ſaue them in drawing neere vnto them.</p>
            <p>Hath he dealt thus alone with them,<note place="margin">To the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> to vs and our Land, though like in condition to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> though for a while he hid his face.</note> vtterly refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all other people? or was his affection ſo ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> could not taſte the ſweetneſſe of his loue? Oh no! For as he dealt with them, ſo likewiſe with vs and our land. I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, how once hee hid his face from vs, ſhewing himſelfe ſo ſterne and wrathfull, as though he neuer would be intreated by vs. For in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> daies, the bloudy banner of perſecution was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaied, and the fearefull drum of terrible threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (Fire and Fagot) was ſtrucke vp, the ſhrill Trumpet of mournefull lamentation was heard in euery corner, <hi>Rachel weeping for her children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 2.18.</note> 
               <hi>and would not bee comforted.</hi> The pale grim Sergeant <hi>Death,</hi> was met in euery ſtreet, who neither ſpared nor pittied young nor old, man nor woman, rich nor poore, infant nor ſuckling, but arreſted all that would be godly; yet ſoone had that night an end, and the louing countenance of the Lord our God, like vnto the morning Sunne, did moſt comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ariſe vpon our land, in the beginning of Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> reigne, of famous memory, and euer ſince hee hath drawne <hi>neerer</hi> and <hi>neerer</hi> vnto this preſent day. In ſo much as I may truly ſay, and I hope ſay nothing but the truth, that he is now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proched ſo neere in the Chariot of his loue and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as he neuer was neerer to any Nation from the beginning to this day. For he is now arriued at the palace of our ſoules, he is alreadie <hi>come</hi> to the gates of our affections,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3.20.</note> and now <hi>ſtands knocking</hi> at the <hi>doore</hi> of our hearts with the hammer of his ſacred
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5137:19"/>
word: and ſo Lord Ieſus continue ſtill, till thou haſt got a full poſſeſſion of our bodies and ſoules.</p>
            <p>The ſeuerall waies that God drawes neere a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are many: for he comes not to his people al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies after one ſort, though ſtill to one end: he is like a skilfull Muſician, that ſings new ſongs with diuerſitie of Moddes and variety of Notes,<note place="margin">God drawes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Nation by 1. His Word &amp; Sacraments.</note> yet all to one end; namely, for the good of his owne people.</p>
            <p>The firſt way that he drawes neere to any Nation, is moſt commonly by his Word and Sacraments: for he is <hi>that Son of man which walketh in the midſt of the ſeuen golden Candleſticks:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 1.13.</note>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ap.</hi> 22.16. and <hi>Ap.</hi> 1.16.</note> that is, in the <hi>midſt of his ſeuen Churches;</hi> He <hi>is that bright morning ſtar, that holds the ſeuen ſtarres in his right hand,</hi> who although they ſhine, yet receiue they their light from him; his Word is himſelfe, and he is his Word, therefore where his Word is truly preached, his Sacraments conſtantly adminiſtred, both carefully receiued, and conſcionably practiſed, there is Chriſt preſent.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. For his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</note>Secondly, he drawes neere in beſtowing great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, as when he giues vs gracious Princes, zealous Magiſtrates, painfull Miniſters, religious people, &amp; a flouriſhing commonwealth, al which we haue had &amp; do enioy, the Lord continue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for euer amongſt vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. By afflictions</note>Thirdly, he drawes neere when he ſends afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons either inward or outward, vpon body or minde, for affliction is the rod which hee euer holds in his hand, to correct his children withall, needs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt he come very neere when he laies this rod vpon the bodies of his people.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. By deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances.</note>Fourthly, he drawes neere when he deliuers from any imminent danger, as when he ſaues vs from fire,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5137:19"/>
water, ſword, wilde beaſts, or ſtrong enemies; thus he drew neere the <hi>three children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.17.</note> when he ſaued them from the fire;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. vlt.</note> the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> when he ſaued them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the water; <hi>Daniel</hi> when he kept him from the lions; <hi>Dauid</hi> when he hid him from <hi>Saul;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 43.1, 2, 5.</note> &amp; this the Lord confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth by the mouth of his holy Prophet, ſaying, <hi>When thou paſſeſt thorow the waters, I will be with thee, and thorow the flouds that they doe not ouerflow thee; when thou walkeſt thorow the very fire thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle vpon thee.</hi> From whence wee plainly ſee that the Lord drawes neere his Church, when he deliuers them from great dangers.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, the Lord drawes neere by ſignes and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, either in the aire, or in the earth, or in the water;<note place="margin">5. By extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary ſignes in the elements and creatures. <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.29. 6 By the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Spirit.</note> For <hi>when ye ſee theſe things come to paſſe</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>then know that the ſonne of man is at hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, the Lord drawes neere by the motions of his holy Spirit, as when he inflames a land, city, fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or priuate perſon, with godly deſires, with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Meditations, with comforts &amp; conſolations in their ſoules. If the iron riſe of it ſelfe, we may be ſure the Load-ſtone is not far off: ſo if our minds (which are more heauier than lead) be eleuated and lifted vp towards heauen, our hearts which by nature deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in nothing but euil, doe now begin to thirſt after godlineſſe, we may be ſure Chriſt is not far from vs.</p>
            <p>Seuenthly and laſtly,<note place="margin">7. By death.</note> the Lord drawes neere vnto vs by death, and thus he drawes neere vnto all, as well wicked as godly, vnreaſonable as reaſonable, creatures ſenſeleſſe, as ſenſible: For what creature mouing or growing vpon the earth <hi>ſhall not taſte of death,</hi> for the holy Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>It is appointed vnto
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5137:20"/>
all men once to die,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9 27.</note> 
               <hi>and after that comes the iudgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> If the Lord draw neere to vs, then this ſerues to make vs draw neere to him.<note place="margin">As he to vs wee ought to draw neere to him. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.8. <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a.</hi> 1.3, 5.</note> We muſt not with <hi>Adam</hi> runne to hide our ſelues in the buſhes, nor with <hi>Ionas</hi> flie to <hi>Tarſiſh,</hi> couering our ſelues in the keele of a ſhip from the <hi>preſence of the Lord,</hi> nor with <hi>Peter</hi> deſiring him <hi>to depart from vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 5.8.</note> becauſe wee are ſinfull men; nor with the <hi>Gergeſites,</hi> deſire him to part <hi>out of our Coaſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. vlt.</note> when wee ſpie him drawing neere;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.20.</note> but with that <hi>woman which had the bloudy iſſue,</hi> ſtriue to come ſo neere him as that wee <hi>touch,</hi> not only his <hi>garment,</hi> but fleſh and ſpirit alſo, if it be poſſible.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.</note> Yea, with <hi>Zacheus,</hi> let vs preſſe ſo neere, as that we may behold his whole perſon with our owne eyes; for if he draw neere to vs in mercie, we much more ought to draw neere to him becauſe of miſery,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16.</note> &amp; with ſpeed run to the <hi>Throne of grace,</hi> that we may receiue mercy <hi>and finde grace,</hi> not ſo much with the feet of our bodies as of our ſoules;<note place="margin">Generally by the affections of our ſoules which we may doe in what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate ſoeuer we are in.</note> for we may run a pace to Chriſt, euen as we ſit in our hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, feed at our tables, or lie in our beds; the feebleſt cripple may make as good ſpeed as the ſwifteſt foot man: for if the heart be not wounded by ſinne, and the feet of the ſoule foundred by infidelity, we ſhall ſoone draw neere: therefore let vs put but agility into the ſoule, then paſſage will ſoone be made for our approaching into the preſence of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Specially by 1. Prayer.</note>The waies that a Chriſtian may draw neere to God are many: as firſt, when we flie to him by ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and hearty prayer, for true prayer is the wings of the ſoule, by which we mount aloft into the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, ſoaring towards the Heauens,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5137:20"/>
where the ſoules <hi>conuerſation</hi> remaines.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20.</note> True prayer brings vs ſo neere Chriſt, as that it admits vs confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence face to face,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.29.</note> nay it makes vs <hi>wreſtle</hi> with the Lord, &amp; <hi>Iacob</hi> like, to <hi>depart with a bleſsing:</hi> wherfore let vs imbrace that exhortation of <hi>S. Aug. Aſcendat oratio vt deſcendat gratia:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> Let our prayers aſcend vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, that his graces may deſcend downe vpon vs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we draw neere vnto God,<note place="margin">2. By frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Word.</note> when we often frequent his holy word; for he is in his word, and his word in him, his word &amp; he is both one; as by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er we draw neere to ſpeake to him, ſo in frequenting his word we draw neere by harkning what he ſaies to vs; for by his word he confers with our ſoules, as it were face to face (only ſetting the brightnes of his glory aſide, which no mortall eie hath or can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to behold) publiſhing &amp; divulging to the ſons of men, what he would haue done &amp; left vndone in this world: Therefore <hi>Qui habet aure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>audiat quid ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus dicat Eccleſijs;</hi> Whoſoeuer hath an eare to heare, let him heare what the ſpirit ſaith vnto the churches.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. By partaking his Sacraments</note> we draw neere vnto God by often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing his Sacraments, for when wee partake of thoſe heauenly myſteries, wee either lodge in his armes or leane on his boſome. The Sacrament of Baptiſme doth lodge vs in his armes, for he tooke the children into his armes, he laid his hands vpon them and bleſſed them; the Sacrament of his laſt ſupper doth lay vs in his boſome, ſo that neere muſt they needs come that receiue both theſe worthily.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, we draw neere vnto Chriſt,<note place="margin">4 By taking vp his croſſe.</note> in taking vp his Croſſe, for when we take vp his Croſſe with patience we follow him, and if we follow him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5137:21"/>
fainting, we ſoone ſhall draw neere vnto him, he that takes not vp the Croſſe, can neuer come to Chriſt; well he may follow him, but it will bee with <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.58.</note> 
               <hi>a farre off,</hi> for which he was rebuked; but hee that takes vp the Croſſe and followes Chriſt, ſhall with that worthy Cyrenian, at laſt attaine <hi>Golgotha</hi> as ſoone as Chriſt, and Heauen with Chriſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that drawes neere vnto Chriſt this way, muſt not with <hi>Demas</hi> forſake Chriſt for a little affliction, but muſt be like vnto <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14.</note> who was <hi>crucified to the world, and the world to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5. By outward profeſſion.</note>Fifthly, we draw neere vnto Chriſt by an outward profeſſion, which many hypocrites doth the like; therefore the Lord complaineth by the Prophet <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 29.13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.8.</note> ſaying, <hi>Theſe people draw neere vnto mee with their lips, but their hearts are farre from me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6. By conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note>Sixthly and laſtly, we draw neere vnto Chriſt by our conuerſion, for the worke of regeneration brings vs into the houſe of Chriſt, makes vs one of <hi>his Family,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 43.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. vlt. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.14. <hi>Iohn</hi> 21.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.8, 22. <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>his Brethren, his Siſters, his Mothers, his Friends, his Kinsfolke, his Children, his Seruants;</hi> nay, what not? For this makes vs <hi>bone of his bone, fleſh of his fleſh,</hi> yea <hi>his Spouſe,</hi> wee wholly his, hee wholly ours for euermore, and this conuerſion conſiſteth of two parts, Mortification and Viuification. Firſt, Mortification,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13.</note> for hee that <hi>mortifies</hi> not <hi>the deeds of the fleſh by the ſpirit,</hi> can neuer draw neere vnto Chriſt. Secondly, Viuification, for he that beginnes not to lead a holy life as well as to forſake a wicked life, ſhall neuer attaine to the fauour of Chriſt. Thus briefly you ſee how Chriſt may be ſaid to draw neere vnto vs, we neere vnto him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:5137:21"/>Secondly, if Chriſt draw neere vnto vs, it is our <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label>
part and duty to make prouiſion for his entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that when he comes,<note place="margin">Prouide for his entertainment.</note> hee may not finde bare walls; I meane a barren heart. The Prouerbe is, <hi>bare walls driues away a good huſwife,</hi> and a barren heart void of grace and goodneſſe, baniſhes a louing Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. A man cannot offer a Prince a greater iniury then to ſeeme to reioyce at his drawing neere, yet to afford him no entertainment at his arriuall: and wee cannot offer this Prince greater indignity then to ſhew our ſelues ioyfull at his appropin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quation, but to haue nothing for his welcome: this is all one to cry with the Iewes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.9.</note> 
               <hi>Hoſanna in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, bleſſed is hee that commeth in the Name of the Lord:</hi> yet with the ſame Iewes ſoone after, ſtraine our notes to another tune, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.42. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.25.</note> 
               <hi>If thou bee the Sonne of God come downe from the Croſſe, ſaue thy ſelfe and others;</hi> or <hi>crucifie him, crucifie him, his bloud bee vpon vs and our children.</hi> When Chriſt came to <hi>Marthaes</hi> houſe, there he did feaſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.38. <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.36.</note> &amp; now he comes to vs, ſhall we make him faſt? then ſoone ſhall we ſtarue our Sauiour from our ſoules. Publicans and ſinners could, and did make prouiſion for his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, ſhall we be worſe then they? O no, farre be that from vs, that Chriſt ſhould finde ſuch curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies from his enemies, and no welcome amongſt his profeſſed friends; therefore ſince Chriſt drawes neere to vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.6.</note> let vs with courteous <hi>Abraham</hi> runne into our Tents, I meane into our hearts, with the feet of zeale and loue, and there make prouiſion fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for his entertainment, which if he like, we neuer ſhall haue cauſe to repent of our coſt, for liberally
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5137:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:5137:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:5137:23"/>
will the Lord reward all thoſe to whom he comes. <hi>Peters wiues mother</hi> did but once receiue him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.15.</note> and he cured her of her <hi>Feuer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk</hi> 19.9.</note> 
               <hi>Zacheus</hi> did but once enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine him, and <hi>ſaluation</hi> was beſtowed vpon him. The Bridegroome of <hi>Galile</hi> did but once inuite him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.9.</note> and he turned <hi>Water</hi> into <hi>Wine. Abraham</hi> did but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the <hi>Angels</hi> into his houſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.10.</note> and had a ſonne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>Lot</hi> did the like, &amp; was preſerued from <hi>Sodoms</hi> deſtruction. <hi>Obed-edom</hi> did but receiue the Arke into his houſe,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.12.</note> &amp; the Lord <hi>bleſſed him and all his houſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 2.15. &amp; 6.22.</note> 
               <hi>Rahab</hi> receiued but the <hi>ſpies,</hi> and ſhe was preſerued in the downefall of <hi>Iericho;</hi> if ſuch benefit be reaped by entertaining the ſhadow; what do you thinke you ſhall haue for receiuing the ſubſtance? As <hi>Iſaac</hi> therefore kiſſed <hi>Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.27.</note> ſaying, <hi>The ſauour of my ſonne is as the the ſauour of a field which the Lord hath bleſſed.</hi> So let vs kiſſe our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt with the kiſſes of zeale and humilitie, and being refreſhed with the ſweet ſmell of his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe in himſelfe, and his loue towards vs; let vs bleſſe Chriſt, and ſay, the ſmell of our Sauiour is as the ſmell of a field which the Lord hath bleſſed. For ſurely I may ſay, to the comfort of thoſe that finde it; Oh happy and bleſſed people, that hath <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> ſuch a gueſt as Chriſt to come vnto them!</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Chriſts draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neere, a preſeruatiue againſt deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire and feare in Chriſts ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence or affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. <hi>Eſay</hi> 54.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.5.</note> Thirdly, this is a preſeruatiue againſt deſpaire: For why ſhould any ſoule feare when Chriſt abſents himſelfe, ſince it is but for a time? <hi>A little while</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>in mine anger haue I hid my face from thee, but with an euerlaſting loue haue I had compaſsion vpon thee: Heauineſſe may endure for a night, but ioy commeth in the morning;</hi> though he be ſlow, yet he is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5137:23"/>
ſure, therefore wait his leiſure; for <hi>he that ſhall come will come, and will not tarry:</hi> But how? <hi>Tibi ſi credis, contra te ſi non credis;</hi> If incredulous, againſt thee; but if beleeuing, for thee: What can be ſaid leſſe, yet what canſt thou wiſh for more? If Chriſt doth come, he reſpects not his paine; if hee come vnto thee, he regards not his profit, for all his deſire is onely to ſaue thy ſoule. Vpon the Croſſe he thirſted, but <hi>Domine quid ſit is?</hi> Lord, what doeſt thou thirſt for?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 19.28.</note> not ſo much for drinke, as for mans ſaluation, and now comes to effect, what before he thirſted for. I cannot deny, but that ſometimes the Lord will make a man beleeue how that hee will neuer draw neere in mercy to his ſoule: but being once gone, will be euer gone, eſpecially from thee, becauſe thou art a great Sinner; therefore, it may be thou ſhalt be tempted &amp; induced to make away thy ſelfe, either by hanging or drowning, or ſtabbing, or poiſoning, or caſting thy ſelfe downe from ſome high place, by which thou maieſt ſhorten thy daies, and become a murderer vnto thy owne body. But take heed thou yeeld not, for theſe are onely the deluſions of thy enemy, who longeth for thy downefall, and would reioyce at thy ruine, neither ſit thou alone that art in ſuch a conflict, for theſe things are exceeding common amongſt Gods people. The Prophets, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, yea, and the beſt of his Saints haue endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſuch things long before thee. What a caſe was <hi>Iob</hi> in, when he curſed <hi>the daies of his birth?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 3.1.</note> What a caſe was <hi>Dauid</hi> in, when hee ſeemed to feare vtter perdition? therefore praied,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.11.</note> 
               <hi>Caſt me not away from thy preſence, and take not thy holy Spirit from mee:</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:5137:24"/>
What a caſe was <hi>Ieremy</hi> in, when he curſed and fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 20.14.</note> 
               <hi>wiſhing he had neuer beene,</hi> or that <hi>he had beene ſlaine</hi> after his firſt entrance into the world? What a caſe was <hi>Elias</hi> in when he cried;<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.4. <hi>Math.</hi> 26.75.</note> It <hi>is enough Lord, take away my ſoule?</hi> What a caſe was <hi>Peter</hi> in when he went from Chriſt and <hi>wept bitterly,</hi> to come again to Chriſt? What a caſe was <hi>Paul</hi> in, when hee cried out,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14.</note> 
               <hi>Oh wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from this body of death? the good I would do, I doe not; the euill I would not doe, that I doe.</hi> Nay, what a caſe was our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe in, when he praied and wept,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.39.</note> wept and praied: <hi>Oh Father, if it be poſsible let this cup paſſe from me;</hi> and being in an agony,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 22.44.</note> he praied more earneſtly, that <hi>hee ſweat water and bloud,</hi> and vpon the Croſſe cried that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and lamentable cry; <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> Was it thus with theſe ſeruants of God, nay with the Sonne of God himſelfe? Then feare not thou, for as the Sunne at laſt breaketh out from vnder the Clouds, ſo ſhall the preſence of the Lord to thy poore ſoule: Feare not therefore, though hee abſent himſelfe a while, he will ſoone come againe. The experience of his mercies paſt, ſhould encourage and ſtrengthen thee for the time to come; remember how hee hath cheriſhed and kept thee in his boſome, when thou wert in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; yea, how hee hath ſnatched thee out of the clawes of Satan, and ſet thee vp <hi>vpon a rocke of ſtone.</hi> Remember how when thou waſt not, hee made thee; when thou waſt loſt, he redeemed thee; when thou wenteſt aſtray, he reclaimed thee; when thou waſt naked, he clothed thee; when thou waſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5137:24"/>
hungry, hee fed thee; when thou waſt ignorant, he inſtructed thee; and euer ſince thy birth, he hath waited for thee. Furthermore, conſider how bee hath nouriſhed and maintained thee, admitting thee by Baptiſme into the fellowſhip of his Saints, and hath ſealed his affection vnto thee, by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of his body and bloud: O remember, how in great griefes he hath ſtood by thee! when the pit was open, it did not ſwallow thee; when Satan roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he could not touch thee; when men haue threatned, they could not wrong thee in all thy lawfull actions; the Lord hath bleſſed thee, can ſuch a God who hath done all this for thee, now leaue and forſake thee? Oh no! It is impoſſible, for hee will not <hi>abſent himſelfe for euer,</hi> neither will hee vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forſake the people of his owne paſture. Let this comfort therefore euen melt thee with kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards thy God, and cauſe thee to ſay with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.12.</note> 
               <hi>What ſhall I render vnto the Lord for all his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits towards me, I will take the Cup of ſaluation, and call vpon the name of the Lord;</hi> yea, I will loue thee dearely, <hi>O Lord my ſtrength,</hi> I will honour thee, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace thee, kiſſe thee, reioyce in thee, and deuote my ſelfe wholly vnto thee; becauſe thou haſt fauoured my ſoule in her greateſt extremitie, and reioyced my heart in her greateſt heauineſſe.<note place="margin">Auguſt. in <hi>17.</hi> Sermon. <hi>8.</hi> Tom. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>that a mightie man will not loſe that which hee hath bought for his money, and will Chriſt loſe that which he hath bought with his bloud?</hi> Surely no: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when thou findeſt a want of Gods preſence, either in the whole or in part, which before thou haſt felt, be not too much diſmaied, for hee can as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5137:25"/>
ſoone forſake himſelfe as thy ſoule; and though he did forſake thee, hee will not leaue thee: comfort thy ſelfe therefore with theſe words. This matter were worthy of a longer ſpeech, but time inforceth me to make an end: wherefore I beſeech the God of all conſolation, to make this point as profitable, as it is comfortable.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The 3. roome in the firſt Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, is Chriſt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</note>The third roome in this Tabernacle or Branch, proceeding from his <hi>Appropinquation,</hi> is <hi>Diligentia;</hi> or as more properly we may tearme it (labour.) For a iourney cannot be taken in hand without great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and labour, and that becauſe it procures a continuall motion of the body, which conſtant motion will at length breed wearineſſe in all the parts of man. And ſurely thus it was with our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, for as man he was ſubiect to all thoſe paſſions belonging to man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.15.</note> being <hi>like vs in all things, ſinne onely excepted,</hi> yet he continues his iourney, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neere to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> as one regarding no paine, fearing no labour, reſpecting no profit; ſo that his <hi>Appropinquation</hi> might comfort his inheritance. From whence we ſee,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>Doct.</hi> No labour hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Chriſts loue.</note>
               <hi>That no labour could hinder Chriſts loue, no paines with-draw his patience,</hi> but ſtill he is patient in wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and louing in comming to theſe rebellious people. Nothing commends patience more, then with painfulneſſe to ſhew kindneſſe; nor nothing ſets forth loue more, then to ouercome ingratitude with labour: both which doe magnifie themſelues in our Sauiour. His paines doth ſhew his patience, his labour ſetteth forth his loue, in that he drew neere vnto the Citie. Many will loue ſo long, as loue
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5137:25"/>
requires no labour, and all will be patient whileſt they feele no paine: but let labour and paine, paine and labour, once ſeize vpon the body of the moſt, yea, of the beſt, ſoone then ſhall you ſee loue extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, patience baniſhed. The <hi>Iewes</hi> can loue Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, ſo long as he will <hi>cure their diſeaſes, feed heir bodies,</hi> and <hi>reſtore their Kingdome:</hi> but when he prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches againſt the Scribes and Phariſes, calling them Hypocrites, and the <hi>Generation of Vipers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. <hi>Luke</hi> 19.45.</note> 
               <hi>whipping the buyers and ſellers out of the Temple:</hi> declaring how that his Kingdome was not of this world, then farewell loue and patience both; For loue is turned into loathing, patience into raging; in ſtead of <hi>God ſaue thee,</hi> now, The Deuill take thee; in ſtead of <hi>Haile Maſter,</hi> hang Maſter is ſet vp; for <hi>Crucifie him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him,</hi> is their euening and morning ſong: nothing would content them but his death, when once they felt the ſmart. But with our Sauiour it is not ſo: for though his comming was laborious, and his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour painfull to all the parts of his body, yet bee vouchſafes to draw neere this ſinfull Citie. By which hee ſhewes, how farre his loue exceedeth mans, and how great his patience is beyond ours: Our loue may ſparkle very high, and our patience may drinke vp many yeares, but the higheſt ſparkle of our loue, could it mount as high as the loue of <hi>Ionathan</hi> to <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.26.</note> whoſe <hi>Loue ſurpaſſed the loue of women,</hi> yet could it not reach the middle region of Chriſts loue; and were our patience like <hi>Iobs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.11.</note> able to feed vpon all afflictions, and to drinke vp yeares of life, yet not comparable with the patience of Chriſt. For looke <hi>how high the heauen is aboue the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5137:26"/>
earth,</hi> gold beyond droſſe, man beyond beaſt, nay God himſelfe the Creator, beyond miſerable man the creature; ſo farre is the loue and patience of Chriſt beyond ours. <hi>Amor vincit omnia,</hi> is an old phraſe, loue ouercommeth all things: but were it as old as man, and man as aged as the world, yet true in none but onely in Chriſt.<note place="margin">Chriſts loue exceeding large.</note> The loue of man may ouercome many things, as nakedneſſe, famine, ſword, water, fire, ſtones, and many other perils; yet not all things, for hell, death, damnation, and the burning wrath of God was ſomething; yea, and ſuch a thing, that all the loue of all the men in all the world, was neuer able to ouercome one for another, therefore <hi>non omnia, ſed multa,</hi> not all things, but many things; but the loue of our Sauiour ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes <hi>non multa, ſed omnia,</hi> not many things, but all things: for hell, death, damnation, and the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning wrath of God, was by our Sauiour ouercome and ſatisfied, not for him ſelfe, but for vs, and by the loſſe of his life;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.13.</note> therefore <hi>greater loue</hi> then this <hi>could no man ſhew, then to lay downe his life for his friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Vſe.</hi> Thinke no paines too great to come to Chriſt.</note>If our Sauiour take ſuch paines, as by labour to weary his body in comming to vs; we then are to thinke no labour or paines too much in comming to him: one kindneſſe requires another, yet not ſo much for our Sauiours profit as for our benefit. His labouring to come to vs, is for our good, not for his owne: our labouring to come to him, is to profit our ſelues, not him; therefore we ought to be more willing to vndergoe any paines to attaine his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, then he our perſons: But alas, I mourne to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5137:26"/>
ſee, and ſeeing mourne, the backward age wherein we liue; Chriſt may take paines an hundred times to come to vs, before we once to come to him. For who will goe from Eaſt to Weſt; from North to South, to come to him, as he doth to come to vs? If it were to goe to profit or pleaſure neuer ſo farre, we could be well contented to vndergoe all the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and paines ſuch a iourney caſts vpon the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: But to come to Chriſt, who is the pleaſure and profit of our ſoules? we hardly will goe a mile; a mile did I ſay, nay hardly out of our doores, nay ſcarce will take the paines to riſe off our beds to draw nigh Chriſt. For we are like the Church in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> who haue <hi>put off</hi> our <hi>coats,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.3.</note> and cannot <hi>put</hi> them <hi>on, waſhed</hi> our <hi>feet,</hi> and will not <hi>defile them</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: though they are more defiled in keeping from him, then they would be in comming to him. But be it they were defiled after our labour or iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, he that <hi>waſhed</hi> Peters <hi>feet,</hi> would not ſticke to waſh thine: For what he was to him, hee is to vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 13.9.</note> and to all thoſe that draw neere vnto him; yet how long may his houſe ſtand naked, his word vnfre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented, and his table vnfurniſhed, before we will take the paines to draw neere any of them, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally with ſinceritie and vprightneſſe? neither can we of our ſelues, ſo backward and auerſe are we by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to all goodneſſe. Chriſt tels vs, ſaying;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.44.</note> 
               <hi>No man can come vnto me, vnleſſe the Father which hath ſent me draw him:</hi> yet we muſt doe our endeuour, and expreſſe the deſire of our hearts, to come to him. For, <hi>Qui creauit te ſine te, non ſaluabit ſine te,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. tract. <hi>15.</hi> de verbis Apoſt.</note> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> Hee that made thee without thy
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5137:27"/>
ſelfe, will not ſaue thee without thy ſelfe; therefore arraigne thy ſelfe by this Indictment at the barre of Gods Grace, make an humble confeſſion of thy owne backwardneſſe to any goodneſſe, crauing mercy at the hands of him that is rich in mercy, and euermore forwarder to giue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 7.7.</note> then wee to aske; to open, then wee to knocke; to bee found, then we to ſeeke, praying with his onely beloued Spouſe; <hi>Lord draw me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>and we will runne after thee.</hi> And thus much ſhall ſuffice for furniſhing the firſt Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of our Text.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond Tabernacle like a Watch-tower, hath alſo three roomes, or this bole three branches.</note>Our ſecond Tabernacle, as you heard in our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, ſeemeth to bee made in the forme of a Watch-tower, wherein we haue Chriſt viewing <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he beheld the Citie.</hi> This body or bole like vnto the former, ſends forth three bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: or this Tabernacle hath three roomes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, He beheld as</note>The firſt is the Contemplation it ſelfe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is the Obiect, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third more particularly what Citie, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of theſe in order; and firſt of his Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>he beheld:</hi> but how? either with the eies of his bodie, or the eies of his minde; either with the eye naturall, or with the eye ſpirituall; either as God, or elſe as Man, or as both God and Man, and ſo I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinke.<note place="margin">1. Man.</note> Firſt, <hi>he beheld</hi> as man with the eies of his body, or bodily eies; the beautie, the glory, and the magnificence of this Citie. He lookt at this time vpon her Bulwarkes, her Towers, her ſtrong walls and fortifications: He ſaw her curious buildings, rich
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5137:27"/>
pauings, ancient monuments, ſpacious ſtreets; hee beheld the great concourſe of people flocking from all parts in all corners of this Citie. Not any ſexes, yeares or degrees, were hid from him as man: hee <hi>beheld</hi> the old ſitting, the young playing, the maids dauncing, the Merchants trafficking, the greedy ſcraping, the profane ſpending, the prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall waſting; yea, what not? For ſurely, what might be ſeene with the eie of man, was not vnſeene by the eie of our Sauiour as man.</p>
            <p>But if we conſider him in the ſecond place, how hee <hi>beheld</hi> it as God: wee then ſhall finde,<note place="margin">2. As God.</note> hee ſaw much more then man was able to diſcerne. For as God, hee <hi>beheld</hi> their wickedneſſe, hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, contempt of him and his graces; yea, he ſaw, or rather fore-ſaw from this his watch-tower, how there he ſhould ſuffer ſhame, ignominy, and reproach; yea, how he ſhould ſhed his preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bloud amongſt them, yet they neuer a whit the better for it: the future temptations, ruines, &amp; deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, both of Church and people, head and taile, branch and ruſh, were not obſcured from his eyes, for he fore-ſaw all, therefore fore-told all,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.2.</note> 
               <hi>How that a ſtone ſhould not be left vpon a ſtone</hi> vncaſt downe; yet as he fore-ſaw it as God, bewailed and lamented it as man.</p>
            <p>But ſome perhaps may ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſt.</hi> in his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition vpon the tenth book of <hi>Ariſt. Ethiks.</hi>
               </note> that a deepe Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation is part of our felicitie, to which I doe aſſent and agree in ſome ſenſe: for I am not ignorant how that <hi>Euſtratius</hi> affirmeth, that Contemplation is a chiefe perfection of our felicitie, becauſe it doth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate a man from the domeſticall and ciuill cares,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5137:28"/>
making him fly from all company and ſocietie of friends: others take it to be a pleaſure of the minde, which I rather aſſent vnto, therefore in Greeke it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe wee are ſweetly affected with the preſence of ſome good thing agreeing with our nature: But I ſtand not here to diſpute with Schoole-men and Philoſophers, becauſe this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of Chriſt affords vs no ſuch fruit. For it is nei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her the perfection of his felicitie, nor any pleaſure of his minde to behold ſuch miſerie, which now was an obiect to his eies; for had it beene ſo, doubtleſſe it neither would, nor could haue wrung teares from his bright gliſtering eies as it did.</p>
            <p>But in this his Contemplation he offers vs a breaſt of Conſolation, from whence we may ſuck no ſmall comfort for our inſtruction: for if he contemplate our miſeries, how gracious doth he intend to be to our ſoules? Neuer did the beames of his gliſtering eies reflect vpon any obiect, but either it did good, or ſhewed his deſire ſo to doe, might hee be but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. Though theſe wicked <hi>Iewes</hi> had reiected him many a time, both in himſelfe, and thoſe which were ſent vnto him; yet he vouchſafes to view them once againe, ſo vnwilling hee was to leaue them: euen Louer like, who is loth to take any deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, if tongue, eies, hands, workes, or teares, could draw their affections. O happy! nay thrice happy, had it beene for <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> had they made but a right vſe of our Sauiours <hi>beholding</hi> them; then would his eies like a ſalue haue cured their ſores, for as the Sun driues away the miſt from off the earth, ſo would his eies the foggy miſts of ſinne and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5137:28"/>
from their heart, or as the fire doth purge the gold from droſſe, ſo would theſe heauenly lookes their ſoules from errors.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>Peters ſhadow cured the diſeaſed as he paſſed by:</hi> and would not the ſubſtance of Chriſts eies (to whom <hi>Peters</hi> whole body was but a ſhadow) much more haue cured their ſoules? Surely yes; no ſooner did he looke vpon <hi>Matthew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.9.</note> but raiſed him from the table of <hi>Cuſtome.</hi> Hee did but glance his eie vpon <hi>Zaccheus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 19.6.</note> and it brought him downe <hi>haſtily,</hi> cauſing him to <hi>receiue</hi> Chriſt <hi>ioyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.48, 49.</note> In telling <hi>Nathaniel</hi> how he ſaw him vnder <hi>the Fig tree,</hi> made him confeſſe hee was the <hi>Sonne of God:</hi> In but once <hi>looking backe vpon Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 22.60, 61.</note> hee was driuen haſtily from ſinne, to <hi>weepe bitterly for ſinne.</hi> Many more examples might be produced, but this is ſufficient: for certainly the eies of Chriſt were full of vertue, Sunne-like, able to haue thawed the greateſt froſt of ſinne in the ſoule; the fire conſumes the fewell, the heat doth melt the wax, the Sunne doth thaw the ice, yet the eies of Chriſt doth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſume their ſinne, melt their hearts, nor thaw their frozen ſoules. The Load-ſtone by her at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractiue vertue drawes vp the ſolid Iron; ſo would thoſe eies of Chriſt theſe peoples affection, had not their hearts beene more obdurat then Iron. They ceaſe to be Iron (yet are they no Gold) but now are conuerted into the nature of an Adamant. When I call to minde, how pittifully, how mourne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, how ſorrowfully, how carefully, and how lamentably he looked vpon this place and people; it is like <hi>Dauids</hi> ſtone, wounding not onely my head, but my heart; yea, it is like <hi>Longinus</hi> ſpeare,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5137:29"/>
ready to pierce my ſoule with ſorrow and griefe. Neuer did the father ſo tenderly behold his childe, nor the mother ſo compaſſionatly looke vpon the tender infant in her armes, as our Sauiour Chriſt did at this time vpon <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> For ſuch was his affection towards this Nation, that his contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their miſerable faſhion, wrung forth abundant teares of compaſſion from his heauenly eies. But no more of this, leſt griefe and ſorrow ſhould hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our paſſage to the ſecond branch.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond roome of the ſecond Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, is the obiect, Citie.</note>The ſecond roome in this Tabernacle or Branch of this body or bole, is Chriſts Obiect, which in our Text is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Citie,</hi> a faire obiect by name, but foule by nature; for though it was a City, yet a moſt ſinfull Citie, as remained vnder the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, neither are we ſo to vnderſtand our Text, as that he beheld nothing but the Citie. For doubtleſſe, the Suburbs, out-parts and skirts thereof were ſeene by him, as well as the Citie; nay, the villages and priuate houſes neere adioyning to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> were not hid from his all-ſeeing eies. If we conſider him as God, then he ſeeth all things: for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall <hi>Dauid</hi> doth thus acknowledge, ſaying; <hi>Thou knoweſt my downe ſitting,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.2, 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4 <hi>v.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and mine vpriſing: thou vnderſtandeſt my thoughts a farre off; thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeſt my path, and art acquainted with all my waies; there is not a word in my tongue, but loe, O Lord, thou knoweſt it altogether. Sibylla</hi> in her Oracles, could thus ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sibyl.</hi> Or.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The Almightie and inuiſible God, hee onely ſeeth all things; yea, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, God hath an all-ſeeing eie. Alſo the Myſticall and Enigmaticall
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:5137:29"/>
letter, whereby the <hi>Egyptians</hi> would haue God to be vnderſtood, was an eye: and the reaſon is rendred by<note n="*" place="margin">Hieroglyph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lil. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erius,</hi> becauſe (ſaith hee) the great God of heauen is <hi>mundi oculus,</hi> the eie of the world. Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is of the ſame opinion, who ſaith; That God is <hi>totus oculus,</hi> wholly an eie: and his reaſon is, <hi>quia omnia videt,</hi> becauſe hee ſeeth all things, yet more eſpecially at this time <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> for he <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held</hi> the Citie: thereby noting to vs, that hee was more deſirous to view the Citie, then the Countrey, and euer more forward to pry into theſe places, then any other beſides. When he had a controuerſie with <hi>Sodome,</hi> he did not ſo narrowly view <hi>Zoar,</hi> or ſearch the little Villages neere adioyning, as he did thoſe foure great Cities; therefore ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.21.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe the cry of Sodome and Gomorrah is great, I will goe downe and ſee whether they haue done altogether according to the cry that is come vnto me. Whether they,</hi> not leauing out the skirts, nor any parts of the plaine, but <hi>they</hi> more eſpecially. Alſo, in the daies of <hi>Iona,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iona.</hi> 1.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.2.</note> Gods eie was more fixed on <hi>Niniue,</hi> then vpon any part of the Countrey beſides, that he might view and behold that place (being great and populous) more cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectly then any other: from whoſe example, you that are Magiſtrates of this Honourable Citie are to learne,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That though your eies be fixed vpon many obiects,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctr.</hi> The eie eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to be fixed vpon Cities.</note> 
               <hi>yet more eſpecially, you are to ſet them vpon the Citie:</hi> The Citie (I ſay) is to bee your principall obiect, and that for many reaſons: I will onely mention foure.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in Cities there is moſt good to be done,<note place="margin">1. In Cities moſt good may be done.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is moſt people; it is beſt angling where
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:5137:30"/>
there is moſt Fiſh; beſt gathering, where there is moſt fruit; the greateſt gariſon, requires the vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanteſt Captaines; the greateſt Citie, the watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Magiſtrates; where there is moſt treaſure, there is moſt watching and warding; and where there is moſt people, there ſhould be the moſt <hi>beholding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Cities the head of lands.</note>Secondly, Cities are the head of Lands, and all other places are but as members to them. Now na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as well as Phyſicke teacheth this, that if the head be polluted, the body cannot be ſound; if the head be ill, all the members fare the worſe; and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the head affects, the body doth not hate; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he that deſires a ſound and healthy bodie, muſt looke well to his head, that cold pierce it not, blowes wound it not, wine diſturbe it not, heats periſh it not, diſeaſes wrong it not, and cares trouble it not. So you that deſire a good Common-wealth, looke well to the Citie, that Vice infect it not, Sectaries trouble it not, Atheiſme drowne it not, Schiſme rent i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not, Popery powder it not, nor Traitors betray it not. I ſay againe, looke well to the Citie, for as the <hi>Dragon</hi> with <hi>her taile</hi> drew the <hi>third part</hi> of the <hi>ſtars</hi> from <hi>heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 12.4.</note> and <hi>caſt them vpon the earth;</hi> ſo will a Citie the third part (if not more) of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, to delight in what ſhe loues. I ſay againe, looke well to the Citie; for as the poiſoning of the Fountaine is the ſpoile of all the ſtreames, ſo the wickedneſſe of the Cittie is the bane of a whole Kingdome. If the mother bee well tutored, the daughters will ſucke their inſtruction from her breaſts. Win the Lady or Princeſſe, and her hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maids will ſoone be brought to obedience: Looke
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:5137:30"/>
well to the Citie, that ſhe remaine ſound in religion, then the Countrey will ſoone bee brought to any goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Cities are full of windings, turnings,<note place="margin">3. Cities full of ſecret ſinnes.</note> and ſecret corners, in which filth and corruption may lye ſo long feſtring, till it hath bred a contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Leproſie, that like to the Gangren, will endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the ſpreading ouer the whole body; therefore Cities ought moſt narrowly to bee lookt vnto. <hi>Achans</hi> theft may lie in one corner,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh</hi> 7. 2 <hi>King</hi> 9 22. <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> 5. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>Ieſabels</hi> whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome may keepe in another corner; <hi>Belſhazers</hi> drunkenneſſe may lodge in another corner; <hi>Abſolons</hi> conſpiracies may keepe in another corner. Theſe, with a thouſand more wickedneſſes, like ſo many dunghils, may be harboured within, and about the walls of this Citie, yet you ignorant of all, vnleſſe you ſearch more narrowly then we feare you doe concerning all.</p>
            <p>Fouthly, Cities are in greateſt dangers,<note place="margin">4. Cities are in greateſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note> for as the Fowler aimes at the head when hee intends to kill the Bird: ſo our Aduerſaries aime at our Cities, when they intend to conquer our Countries, and that either by ſecret powdering, or cloaked flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, intending neuer more miſchiefe, then when they pretend moſt friendſhip. Awake therefore O you Magiſtrates, and wipe your eies O you Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Lord, that you may behold cleerely the wonderfull deformitie and abuſe of our Citie. <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> ſecond King, and firſt beſt King, hid not his eies from the <hi>violence and ſtrife in the Citie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.9.</note> but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to the Lord, how he ſaw it all whereſoeuer it was committed, and will you maske your faces that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:5137:31"/>
you may ſee none?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 20.8.</note> 
               <hi>Salomon</hi> tells vs, that <hi>a wiſe King ſitteth vpon the Throne, and chaſeth euery one that is euill;</hi> yea, euen <hi>with his eies. Iob,</hi> who was a Magiſtrate, and a great Ruler in the Country where he liued, was ſo vigilant in his place, that the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered young men durſt not indure his ſight, but hid themſelues from his preſence:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 29.8.</note> for he <hi>brake the iaw of the vnrighteous,</hi> (of what ſtate or degree ſoeuer) <hi>and pluck't the prey out of his teeth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 29.17.</note> As for vagabonds and vilde perſons, they were compelled to fly into the Wilderneſſe, and into darke and deſolate places, they were chaſed forth from among men, they ſhouted at them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 30.3.5.6.</note> as <hi>at a Theefe,</hi> therefore they <hi>dwelt in clifts</hi> of <hi>riuers, in holes of the earth, and in rockes.</hi> You, my Lord, and the reſt of the Gouernors of of this honourable and famous Citie, giue me leaue to tell you one thing, and that the truth. I know you haue heard it, and am fully perſwaded you know it, yet I cannot chuſe but once more divulge it; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how that the ſafetie and proſperitie both of Church and Common-wealth, next vnder our good God, and our gracious King <hi>Iames,</hi> whoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous memory ſhall liue when he is dead, lieth in your carefull vigilancy. For as graſſe cannot grow where feet often paſſe, ſo ſinne dares not flow where your eies often glance:<note place="margin">Commonly called the Batt.</note> But as the Night-bird flies without feare, when once the Sunne declineth our Horizon; ſo iniquitie will domineere in our Citie, if your eies ceaſe to looke abroad. When <hi>Sampſon</hi> was aſleepe hee was betraied; and if you ſlumber long, our Cities will be waſted. <hi>Holofernes</hi> in taking his reſt when he ſhould not, ſmarted, both he and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:5137:31"/>
his Army, when they would not; therefore take heede you giue not your eies to much ſleepe, nor your eie-lids to much ſlumber. When you ſhould be about the worke of the Lord, I meane, hewing downe thoſe trees of ſinnes with the ſword of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; that it may be ſaid of you, as the Lord once ſaid of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ap.</hi> 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>I know how thou canſt not beare with them which are euill:</hi> But if you doe contrarily, neglecting the place wherein the Lord hath ſet you, it will not onely bee your owne blot, the poiſon of your family, the bane of your poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; but alſo the vtter diſgrace, ruine, and ouerthrow of our whole Land.</p>
            <p>As I remember you command lights to be hung forth in darke nights, that the feet of Paſſengers may be kept from ſtumbling, and ſtrangers to be guided in the way: ſhall I ſay you doe well in ſo doing? yes, and very well, elſe ſhould I wrong your care. But I could wiſh, that the ſame Lanthornes might bee lights to guide your feet into the ſecret corners of our Citie more oftner then they doe: I need not then ſhew you what there you ſhould finde. For I am perſwaded, you would ſay with the Queene of <hi>Sheba;</hi> The one halfe of what I now ſee,<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 10.7.</note> was neuer told me by the Miniſters of the Lord. For it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that our tongues ſhould vnfold ſo fully the enormities of this great Citie, as your eies may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne them: If I ſhould aske you that queſtion, which once the Lord did aske our daily Watch-man, <hi>Cuſtos quid de nocte? Watch-man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 21.11.</note> 
               <hi>what ſeeſt thou by night?</hi> So my Lord, what ſee you in London by night? it may be nothing: why ſo? becauſe you
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5137:32"/>
are then at reſt, when you ſhould bee at the greateſt labour. Doe you not ſee Adulterers &amp; Adultereſſes together? Doe you not ſee how they ſtriue to make one another drunke, that they may cheat &amp; couzen them of their patrimony? Do you not ſee reuelling, dauncing, and banquetting till midnight? Doe you not ſee carding, dicing, drinking, and ſwearing all night? Doe you not ſee how the <hi>Ieſabellicall</hi> dames bake painting on their faces in the night, that they may allure men vnto vanitie in the day with their deceiueable beauty? Doe you not ſee Maſſe-prieſts as ordinary in the ſtreets as Miniſters? Doe you not ſee the Theefe ſtealing, the Murderer ſtabbing, Couzners cheating, the Prodigall waſting, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane ſpending, and conſpiracy following their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe very cloſely? What ſhall I ſay? me thinkes, if your eies were not too much blinded, you might ſee thoſe euery night in their cups and iollitie, which ſcarce the Sunne ſees in a moneth together, nor they the in-ſide of a Church or good booke in a twelue-moneth together. The Deuill ſees all this, &amp; laughes at it; if you ſee it not to amend it, God one day will ſee to puniſh it, both in you and them: In you, for winking at it; in them, for committing of it. But what auaileth it mee to ſpeake of theſe things? this Pulpit hath ſounded with theſe exclamations many times in your eares; but I feare all in vaine, becauſe I ſee ſo little reformation. You are lulled ſo faſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe in the cradle of ſecuritie, that it is almoſt as eaſie for vs to raiſe <hi>Lazarus</hi> from the graue, who hath beene dead foure daies, as to open your eies to behold the ſinnes of this Citie, with a purpoſe to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5137:32"/>
puniſh them: me thinkes you haue eies, Why doe you not vſe them in the work of the Lord? God and Nature hath made them round like a ball, thereby intimating, that you ſhould looke euery way; not onely before you, but alſo of each ſide, and leſt any thing ſhould be amiſſe behinde, Nature hath giuen your necke motion, ſo that the head may turne to fix the eie vpon any obiect, as well behinde as before. Alſo, the eie ſtands not out, but in the head; for it doth not appeare ſo farre forth, as the noſe or lips of a man: but it is placed in a deepe hole, as water in a Fountaine, and alſo hath a lid to couer it, and a brow to ſhelter it: thereby noting to vs, that the eie muſt be preſerued &amp; not blinded with gifts, or ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter reſpects.<note place="margin">Veiles which hinder the eies of Gouernors, from behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Cities enormities.</note> I am not ignorant of the veiles or coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings that may hinder your eies from beholding the enormities of this Citie: I will not tax you with any, only I will ſhew you them, that when you ſee them, you may examine your ſelues concerning them.</p>
            <p>The firſt is Ignorance (which is the ground of all Errors, and not the mother of Deuotion,<note place="margin">1. Veile, is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the Cities vices.</note> as the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary teacheth) yet not of God, nor of his truth. For that you cannot, nay I dare boldly ſay, bee not ignorant of. Your knowledge is great, yea wonderfull great in this reſpect, farre exceeding all other Nations, the Lord make it as good as great. But the ignorance I ſpeake of, is of the vices and ſinnes of this Citie; for ſurely if you knew them, your eies could not bee reſtrained from beholding them, that your hearts might the more be encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to puniſh them. Yet why doe I ſay you are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of theſe things? Me thinkes it is impoſſible:
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5137:33"/>
you are not <hi>Strangers in Iſrael,</hi> but borne and bred where theſe things haue lodged. Were you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as deafe as an adder, your eares could not chuſe but tingle long agoe with theſe reports; if they haue not now, God grant they may, and not onely now, but euery day till a reformation be made.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Veile, ſtupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie.</note>The ſecond veile or couering is ſtupiditie or blockiſhneſſe, which is ingendred moſt commonly by gluttony and drunkenneſſe: for when a man is ouer-charged with Gods good Creatures, they doe ſo ſtupifie his nature, and dull his ſpirits for the time, that he is not fit for any action, either in his publike or priuate calling; <hi>When the belly is full the bones would be at reſt,</hi> is the ancient Prouerbe; therefore ſo receiue the creatures of God, that by them you may the more cheerefully performe that worke, and execute that place whereunto the Lord hath called you. When the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were full, they forgot that God that made them. When <hi>Belſhazer</hi> was ouer-charged with Wine, his Kingdome might haue run at randome: And when the <hi>Glutton</hi> was cram'd with delicates, <hi>Lazarus</hi> was forgotten; moſt true therefore is this ſaying, That the body being ouer-charged, is not fit for any imployment: for the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God being receiued immoderatly, ſo ſtupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and dull the whole Man, that it makes him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get both God and goodneſſe, himſelfe and others, life and death, heauen and hell, and all things elſe that is needfull for a Chriſtian to ponder. But why doe I reſt here, ſince <hi>venter non habit aures,</hi> the belly hath no eares; and what is ſpoken vnto it, is no more then ſtones caſt againſt the wind, or men figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:5137:33"/>
with the ayre. Paſſe we therefore from this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond veile, and come we to the third.</p>
            <p>The third veile or couering,<note place="margin">3. Veile, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights.</note> is wallowing in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and pleaſures; as hawking, hunting, dicing, carding, bowling, ſhooting, drinking, ſporting, with the like: not that I condemne the lawfull vſe of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things, but the abuſe of them, as in vſing them at vnlawfull times and ſeaſons, and vnlawfully. It was wel ſaid by a good Diuine, that we muſt play no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then we can pray. Can we pray an houre? then in lawfull exerciſes we may ſport an houre; but if a minute wee cannot pray, we haue no libertie to ſpend a day, nor the leaſt part of a day in any exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe whatſoeuer.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.1.2.</note> When <hi>Dina</hi> went from praying to playing, ſhe loſt her virginity. When <hi>Dauid</hi> tooke libertie to ſport with his neighbours Wife, hee brought Gods iudgements vpon his Kingdome. When <hi>Sampſon</hi> lay bathing himſelfe vpon the lap of his delights,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.10. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16.20. <hi>Iudith</hi> 12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13 <hi>Chap.</hi>
               </note> hee was betraied into the hands of the <hi>Philiſtims:</hi> and when <hi>Holofernes</hi> was rauiſht with conceit of pleaſure he ſhould enioy with <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith,</hi> loſt his head by the hand of <hi>Iudith.</hi> For neuer was there any that wallowed long in delights, but ſmarted ſoundly in the end. It is ſo thicke a veile, that no miſery or miſchiefe can be diſcerned (though neuer ſo neere) thorow it. <hi>Dina</hi> ſaw not <hi>Sechem, Dauid</hi> diſcerned not the ſword, <hi>Sampſon</hi> dream't not of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> nor <hi>Holofernes</hi> perceiued not the intent of <hi>Iudith:</hi> he that eates Hony, thinks not of the ſting, becauſe the ſweetneſſe delights his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat: and he that wallowes in delights and pleaſures, thinkes <hi>omnia bene,</hi> all is well, becauſe he enioyes his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:5137:34"/>
hearts deſire: but as he that loiters when he ſhould not, ſhall ſmart when he would not: ſo that Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate that beholds no iniquitie for delights and pleaſure, ſhall one day feele much miſery, and that beyond meaſure vnexpreſſible by the tongue of man.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. Veile, is feare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r cowardli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note>The fourth veile or couer of the eie, is feare and timorouſneſſe, which we commonly call baſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlineſſe, when you would behold to puniſh, but dare not, becauſe they are rich men, or great perſons; therefore if you ſhould prie into their faults, they perhaps would ſit vpon your skirts when you would receiue kindneſſe of them. This veile is iuſt like the plaſtering of hypocriſie, or a ſtrong man with a cowards heart, whoſe voice is euer, One good turne deſerues another, or like the Theefe, Say nothing of me, and I will ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of thee; or like the greedy Cormorant, whoſe onely aime is for his owne gaine, ſaying; I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to paſſe by your offence, and to winke at this your fault, onely doe me ſuch a courteſie when you goe vnto the Court. But know all you that harbour ſuch intents within your breaſts, that if you ſee and feare to ſtrike, God will not feare to ſee you ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, with all thoſe plagues, woes and curſes, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his holy Word. What though they be your friends? it is a happy loſſe to loſe the friendſhip of man, to win the fauour of God. What though they may doe you a kindneſſe? God muſt doe you a greater, or good it had beene you had neuer beene borne. What though they may ſtand you in ſtead in time of extremitie? God muſt ſtand you in more
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:5137:34"/>
when the world forſakes you, or elſe woe bee to your ſoules in death and iudgement. What though they be great, and threaten to remember you? God is farre greater, and will not forget you, when the memoriall of them is rooted out of the earth; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore plucke vp your courage, draw out your ſword, cut downe iniquitie, whereſoeuer, whenſoeuer, or in whomſoeuer you finde it. Stand not like that <hi>Abomination</hi> of <hi>deſolation,</hi> mentioned by <hi>Daniel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.27. <hi>Math.</hi> 24.15.</note> neither paſſe by the enormities of this Citie, with thoſe ſugred words of <hi>Elie, This ought not to bee ſo my ſonnes,</hi> this ought not to be ſo: but <hi>march fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly like Iehu:</hi> threaten terribly with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.22.</note> 
               <hi>God doe ſo,</hi> and <hi>more then ſo to the enemies of Dauid, if ought of Nabals houſe bee left vntill the morning.</hi> Speake ſternely with <hi>Ioſeph,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.15.</note> 
               <hi>By the life of Pharaoh you ſhall not goe hence, vnleſſe your younger brother come.</hi> So, take an holy oath, promiſe betwixt God and your ſoules, that wickedneſſe ſhall not goe vnpuniſhed, vnleſſe it ſpeedily be amended: ſet alwaies before your eies this common, yet ancient verſe:
<q>
                  <l>A Prince can haue no better part</l>
                  <l>Then Foxes wit, and Lions hart.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The fift veile or couering to the eie, is raſhneſſe,<note place="margin">5. Veile, is raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> which is ſeene when you puniſh by ſtriking and giuing ſentence before you heare the defendant. The Prouerbe is, <hi>One cauſe is good till the other be heard;</hi> therefore as God hath giuen you two eares, you muſt heare both ſides; I meane, as well the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant as the plaintiffe, the witneſſe, as the Iury. He that takes vp Iron, but afterwards findes Gold,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:5137:35"/>
flings by the worſe and takes vp the better. Euen ſo, though you finde one cauſe good, but the other better, cleaue to the beſt; yet giue ſentence vpon none, till their caſe be more clearer: for Iudgement raſhly pronounced, many times cauſeth the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent to bee puniſhed, the offender cleared; if you therefore breake forth ſuddenly into any ſuch paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, oh ſpeedily recall that wicked affection, and ſuffer it not to reſt within your breaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6. Veile, is Idleneſſe, and caſting the charge vpon other.</note>The ſixt and laſt veile or couering of the eie, is Idleneſſe, which we commonly call ſloth and lazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Many Magiſtrates it may be, would willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reforme the abuſes of the Citie, but are loth to take the paines: for thus many a drowſie Magiſtrate confers with himſelfe; To walke abroad in the night will breake my ſleepe, diſturbe my reſt, indanger my body; going about the Citie will weary my limbs, trouble my braines, and moue my patience in beholding the wickedneſſe of the people: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that my body may haue his eaſe and reſt, I am willing to ſuffer the people to walke in their owne waies during my time: A yeare is not euer, for ſoone will that time be accompliſhed, and as for the people, they cannot grow much worſe in ſo ſhort a time; therefore hee that comes after ſhall take the paines for me. And thus through ſloth, we poſte our labour off from day to day, caſting the burthen vpon other mens backes: ſo that eaſe and reſt may bee had, let the Citie flow with iniquitie, till it ſinke with <hi>Abiram,</hi> and burne with <hi>Sodome.</hi> Others there are, who thinke their places fully diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, in authoriſing any ſeruant to ſee a reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:5137:35"/>
But I tell you nay: for their labour cannot diſcharge your dutie, nor other mens paines your place. Know you not that ſeruants are idle, and as faine would haue eaſe and reſt as you; but ſuppoſe they be not, yet ſoone eie blaſted, for a viſion of Angels will make them play bo-peepe; ſee, and not ſee; heare, and not heare.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.</note> Will not <hi>Iudas</hi> ſell his Maſter for profit, much more your Honours for gaine? Will not <hi>Geheſi</hi> take a bribe behinde his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters backe, yet ſhameleſly ſay;<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Thy ſeruant hath beene no where?</hi> Truſt not therefore too much to their paines, but to your owne; for that which is done by your owne labour, is euer beſt, and will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford your ſoules in trouble the greateſt reſt. Thus briefly you ſee the veiles that may hinder from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the enormities of this Citie: ſearch there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your ſelues, whether theſe, or any of theſe bee as a couering to your eies, which if you finde, caſt them away ſuddenly, not onely from the face, but from the heart. For if you ſolace your ſelues in theſe things, then ſinne will be the ſickneſſe of our Citie, and your portion after this life euerlaſting miſery.</p>
            <p>The third roome in this Tabernacle or Branch of this body,<note place="margin">
                  <p>The third roome of the ſecond Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle.</p>
                  <p>The Citie <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne into which God powred his bleſſings, yet not anſwerable to his mercies.</p>
               </note> doth liuely paint out to vs what Citie it was our Sauiour thus <hi>beheld.</hi> The Text ſaith, it was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the Citie.</hi> Should I therefore paſſe by this particle <hi>(the)</hi> I ſhould ſuffer <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> to loſe her honour, though now her honour and happineſſe be laid in the duſt: For that Citie which is Chriſts Obiect at this time, was <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> a Citie once that ſhined as the ſtarres in heauen, a Citie that ouer-awed all the Cities in the world, and was the rod
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:5137:36"/>
of Gods anger to ſmite the Nations withall. It was that Citie which God had choſen aboue all the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the earth to dwell in. It was that Citie where the Throne of <hi>Dauid</hi> ſtood:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.13, 14</note> It was that Citie where Gods worſhip was put, for there was the <hi>Temple,</hi> the <hi>Altars,</hi> the <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> the <hi>Arke of the Couenant,</hi> the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum:</hi> yea, what not, for all things that appertained to the worſhip and ſeruice of God, was onely found in her, and none elſe. It was that Citie that was called <hi>holy,</hi> counted glorious by all them that liued when ſhe was in her glory, thoſe that then ſaw her could not chuſe but acknowledge as much, if euer they <hi>numbred</hi> her <hi>Towers, conſidered her walls,</hi> and <hi>marked her bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks.</hi> Should I make report at large of it, you would hardly beleeue me: but I am ſure, when the <hi>Kings of the earth were gathered together and ſaw it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>they maruelled, were aſtoniſhed, and ſuddenly driuen backe.</hi> Beſides all this, it was a Citie of the greateſt Antiquitie one of them in all the world: at firſt, it was called <hi>Salem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.18.</note> where <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> King thereof brought <hi>forth Bread and Wine</hi> to refreſh <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seruants, after <hi>he returned from the ſlaughter of his enemies.</hi> Afterwards it was poſſeſſed by the <hi>Iebuſites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 19.10.</note> and by them named <hi>Iebus.</hi> Now <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> from both theſe names, <hi>Iebus</hi> and <hi>Salem,</hi> ſuppoſeth that by the change of a few letters,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Peter Mar.</hi> in Com. vpon the 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> receiued her name. But whither doe I run, I come not to preach names, but doctrines to you; therefore in that it is ſaid, he <hi>beheld the Citie,</hi> namely <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> aboue all the Cities in the world, this collection doth ariſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:5137:36"/>
               <hi>That where much is beſtowed, much is expected,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctr.</hi> Where much beſtowed, much expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</note> the Lord had beſtowed much vpon this Citie, and now doth expect much from this Citie, therfore it is ſaid, <hi>he beheld (the) Citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This they could not be ignorant of, for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſay</hi> told them (many hundred yeares before this day) in a parable, that after the Lord had digged his vineyard, hedged it round about, and built <hi>a Wine-preſſe</hi> therein, he came to looke for <hi>Grapes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 5.2.</note> that is, for fruit, and that not for a handfull or two, but ſo much as would anſwer his paines and coſt, not of any fruit, but true fruit;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5.</note> for there was <hi>wilde Grapes</hi> good ſtore, yet they could not content the Lord, nor with-hold him from deſtroying this his vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. In the Booke of the <hi>Canticles,</hi> the Lord is ſaid to goe <hi>downe into the garden of Nuts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.11.</note> 
               <hi>to ſee the fruits of the Valley, and to ſee whether the Vine flouriſhed, and the Pomegranats budded.</hi> For moſt certaine it is, that where the Lord hath beſtowed many bleſſings, he expects much fruit and benefit. This Chriſt alſo told theſe <hi>Iewes</hi> in many parables, which are to bee ſeene to this day, &amp; ſhall be in his Church to the end of the world: As firſt in the parable of <hi>a certaine houſholder which planted a vineyard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.33, 34.</note> and built all things neceſſary thereunto, then <hi>let it out to husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and went</hi> (himſelfe) <hi>into a farre Country:</hi> but <hi>when the time of fruit drew neere, he ſent his ſeruants to the husband-men, that they might receiue the fruits of it.</hi> Secondly, by the parable of the <hi>talents,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.14, 15, 16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> for from him that had <hi>fiue talents,</hi> the owner expected ten; from him that had <hi>two,</hi> foure; and from him that had <hi>one,</hi> two; but from all ſome, according to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:5137:37"/>
the meaſure they had receiued; and if any failed, as one did, he was ſure to be puniſhed moſt ſeuerely for it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 13.6.</note> Thirdly, by the parable of the <hi>Fig-tree,</hi> which was <hi>planted by a certaine man,</hi> who afterward came <hi>and ſought for fruit,</hi> and that not any fruit, but doubtleſſe ſuch fruit, as for qualitie and quantitie might be anſwerable to the labour and coſt that he had beſtowed vpon it. And no maruell, for nature teacheth this; to expect much where they beſtow much. The Vſurer lookes for ten from the hundred, and a hundred from the thouſand, if not more; not alike from both; but where is the greateſt ſumme, there hee expects the greateſt vſe. The Merchant lookes for gaine from ventring a little, but for more if he venter much. The Husbandman plowes and ſowes his ground, afterward expects a fruitfull har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt. The Gardiner dungs and prunes his trees, that thereby they may be the fruitfuller, and with plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie requite his paines. In a word, euery one in their ſeuerall labours, lookes that their coſt and paines ſhould bring forth profit, and that anſwerable; for little, ſomething; for much, plentie; but for all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit. This the Lord ſpeakes by the mouth of his holy Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7.</note> ſaying; <hi>Who planteth a Vineyard, and eateth not of the fruit thereof? Or who feedeth a flocke, and eateth not of the milke of the flocke?</hi> This he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds as a queſtion to the <hi>Corinths</hi> by the mouth of his Apoſtle: Who doth theſe and theſe things, ſpending their money, time, and ſtrength of body, but in hope to reape profit, and to taſte of the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their labour? <hi>(q.d.)</hi> Shew me but an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of one man that is ſo void of iudgement, and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:5137:37"/>
deſtitute of vnderſtanding, that can be contented to trauell and take paines; wearying his body, ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his time, waſting his ſubſtance, yet to looke for no gaine in the end, then will I be willing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part with the loſſe: but if you cannot ſhew me one man ſo ignorant or fooliſh, thinke then it is no cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie in me, to expect not onely my owne, but my owne with <hi>aduantage.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.27.</note> The earth was not created for it ſelfe, nor any other vnreaſonable creature for his owne vſe, but all for the good and benefit of man; the Sunne to light him, the Clouds to diſtill her dew vpon him, the Fire to warme him, the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to waſh him; the Fiſh of the Sea, the Fowles of the Aire, and the Beaſts of the field to nouriſh and refreſh him, and all other creatures to be ſeruiceable vnto him. And was he created for no vſe, but like the Hogge to deuoure all the Maſte, and neuer to looke to the tree from whence it came? Surely no; for as all things was created for the vſe and ſeruice of man, ſo man was created for the vſe and ſeruice of God: not to liue as we liſt, like maſterleſſe curres that haue no owner, but to vſe our talent to our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters profit, and to ſpend our time and ſtrength to honour and glorifie our God: Neither is it the end of our creation alone, but alſo of our election. For <hi>yee haue not choſen me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.16.</note> 
               <hi>but I haue choſen you, and ordained you, that you ſhould goe and bring forth fruit, and that your fruit ſhould remaine: for euery branch in me that beareth not fruit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>he taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi> Neither is it the end of our creation and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction alone, but alſo of Gods glory: for our <hi>light</hi> muſt <hi>ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee</hi> our <hi>good
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:5137:38"/>
works, and glorifie</hi> our <hi>Father which is in heauen.</hi> This then ſerues in the firſt place as a rod, to ſcourge two ſorts of men and women withall: firſt, thoſe that receiue much and returne nothing: ſecondly, thoſe that receiue much, but returning nothing worthy of what they haue receiued. Firſt, we haue a world of people that receiue Gods bleſſings, both temporall and ſpirituall, yet returne nothing at all; and they are either ſuch as know not God, or ſuch as know God, but forget both him and his gifts. Firſt, they are ſuch as know not God, and they are all thoſe that aſcribe whatſoeuer they doe enioy to ſate and fortune: For many a man, if he be preſerued from theeues in his iourney, and brought ſafe to his habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation againe; or if he be reſtored from a dangerous ſickneſſe to his former health, preſently aſcribes it vnto deſtiny, concluding with himſelfe thus: It was my fortune to eſcape at this time from the hands of Robbers, or from my cruell ſickneſſe which brought me wonderfull low; for had it not beene my fortune, it had beene impoſſible to haue eſcap't thoſe dangers that I was in; or by good fortune, ſuch a man died and left me all his goods, or I got ſo much by ſuch a venter beyond Seas. Thus we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne all to fate and fortune, but nothing to the Lord, who hath beſtowed all, and lookes for all: and the reaſon is, becauſe we know him not, or at the leaſtwiſe know him not to be ſuch a God as is the giuer of all things;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.1.</note> for <hi>the foole hath ſaid in his heart there is no God.</hi> Secondly, they are ſuch as forget God, and in forgetting him, forget that euer they receiued any thing from him, therefore cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:5137:38"/>
any thing vnto him. If a man haue a friend which beſtowes a great gift, he is thankfull ſo long as he remembers both gift and giuer; but if he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get either, it is impoſſible hee ſhould returne any thing worthy of what he hath receiued. <hi>Iudas</hi> had great fauour ſhewed him, when the Lord paſſed by many, and choſe him to be an Apoſtle; but this he ſoone forgot, which made him turne Traitor to his Lord. So theſe men, though they cannot but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge God the Creator and Giuer of all at ſometimes, yet ſoone doe they forget it againe, which makes them ſo to abuſe what God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed in mercy vpon them. Many a man hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued wealth, and a large eſtate of earthly things, but hath forgotten how he receiued it of the Lord; and that moues him many times to ſpend ſo prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally, to feed ſo gluttonouſly, to drinke ſo vnſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, to goe ſo proudly, and to liue ſo wantonly: whereas if he remembred both the Giuer and the gift, how he enioyes nothing but what bee hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from the Lord, it would inforce him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne the fruit of humilitie and thankfulneſſe vnto him that hath beene ſo gratious vnto him: Others haue receiued honours, fauours, and great authoritie in this world; but it hath ſo puft them vp, with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, ambition, and ſuch aſpiring thoughts, that they ſoone forget what they haue receiued, which makes them to peruert authoritie to iniuſtice, and to ſell equitie and all conſcience for Gold, as ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily as cattle are ſold in Smith-field for gaine. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue receiued gifts and talents of great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and deepe learning, by which they are able to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:5137:39"/>
diue into the cuſtome and practice of all ages paſt, and to doe good ſeruice in Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: but many in forgetting the Giuer of that gift, doe either hide this talent in a Napkin, and doe no good, liuing as drones and vnprofitable mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers amongſt vs, like fruitleſſe trees, who neither will doe good themſelues, nor ſuffer others that would during their life; or elſe they doe much hurt with their learning and knowledge, in oppoſing the truth, goodneſſe, and good men, defending corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, maintaining erronious opinions, making bridges to all Popery and prophaneneſſe, or elſe they draw away others to wickedneſſe by making filthy Poems, and ſuch like. Thus while we know not God, or knowing him, ſoone forget both him and his gifts, it makes vs wee cannot returne any thing to him who hath giuen all things, vnleſſe it be with the barren ground, thornes and thiſtles, or with the wicked <hi>Iewes,</hi> nothing but ſtones to caſt both at him and his Prophets for all his mercies.</p>
            <p>Secondly, thoſe are to be reproued, that returne, but nothing anſwerable to what they haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and they be either ſuch as make ſhew without ſubſtance, or ſuch as haue ſubſtance but of no conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance. Firſt, there are many that like the fruitleſſe <hi>Figge-tree,</hi> are <hi>full of leaues,</hi> that is, glorious in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion, full of good words, but void of good actions: and theſe are thoſe that ſpeake faire with their mouths, but diſſemble in their hearts; that haue <hi>Iacobs</hi> voice, but <hi>Eſaus</hi> hands; gliſter like gold, but being once tried at the touch-ſtone, are found nothing but Copper; they beare the title of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:5137:39"/>
hauing <hi>Belials</hi> heart, though the Saints coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance; glorious to the eye, like the Apples of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> but cruſh't in the hand, fall to aſhes; painted Sepulchers, but full of rottenneſſe and dead mens bones. O theſe are worſe then thoſe that returne nothing, and greater ſhall their condemnation be at laſt. Secondly, there is another ſort which returne ſubſtance, but of no continuance, like the Summers fruit, no ſooner ripe but rotten; or like <hi>Aarons rod,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 17.8.</note> 
               <hi>will bud, bloſſome, beare fruit;</hi> and more then it, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and all in one day. Theſe we commonly call Apoſtataes, becauſe they fall from the grace which they haue receiued; and like <hi>Iulian,</hi> turne their backs vpon heauen, blaſpheming him, whom once they praied vnto; one while with the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.9.</note> 
               <hi>Hoſanna in the higheſt, bleſſed is he that commeth in the name of the Lord;</hi> ſoone after ſtraine their voice to another tune,<note place="margin">Matt. 27.25.</note> 
               <hi>Crucifie him, crucifie him, his bloud be vpon vs and our children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, this ſerues for exhortation, lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and conſolation: Firſt, for exhortation, to ſpur vs forward to all good actions and holy duties; not to be backward in returning, according to what we haue receiued; for if we haue much, God lookes for much; if little, for little; if nothing, for nothing: Hee requires not what hee hath not giuen, neither will hee reape where he hath not ſowne: He ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects not that from the Begger, which hee doth from the King; nor that from the Hand-maid, which he doth from the Miſtris; but from euery man, woman and childe, according to what he hath beſtowed vpon them. Doth any man looke for
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:5137:40"/>
               <hi>Grapes of Thornes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.16.</note> 
               <hi>or Figs of Thiſtles?</hi> Surely no, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did euer any reape Wheat where he ſowed Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley: I meane, one graine in ſowing cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to another in reaping; for euery <hi>Graine beares his owne body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.38.</note> and yeelds fruit according to his owne kinde. So euery Chriſtian muſt be fruitfull, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that meaſure which they haue receiued of the Lord. Hath he giuen thee wiſdome, and that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue others? O labour then, to be more wiſe in thy ſayings, and diſcreet in thy doings then others: Hath he giuen thee riches and wealth, ſo that thou in meanes doſt farre exceed thy neighbours? Then looke thou be more forward in hoſpitalitie and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie then thy neighbours. Hath hee giuen thee ſtrength and courage exceeding many that dwell neere thee? then thou muſt bee more forward to ſtand for the Goſpell, and to defend thy King and Countrey then the weaker. Art thou a Childe or a Seruant? and hath God giuen thee a religious father and mother, or a religious maſter and miſtreſſe? O then ſtriue thou to out-ſtrip many that want thoſe helps which thou enioyeſt. Let not thoſe that haue prophane Parents and wicked Gouernors, be more forwarder in religion, more fuller of knowledge, more zealous for the Lord of Hoſts, then thou that doeſt enioy the meanes and helps to ſpurre thee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. For ſhame, let grace and goodneſſe in thy breaſt aboue theirs appeare; ſuffer not thoſe that haue no meanes, to come to heauen before thou that haſt all meanes, leſt the Saints and Angels ſhout at thee at thy arriuall. If a foot-man and a horſe-man ſhould trauell to a Towne together, the foot-man
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:5137:40"/>
with bolts vpon his legges, the horſe-man free from any: were it not aſhame the foot-man ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his iournies end before the other? Surely yes: and well might all men imagine, that he either hath rid farre out of his way, or elſe ſpent his time very idly, that hauing ſuch helps and meanes to haſten him, yet ſhould be farre behinde him that hath no meanes, but rather pull-backs and hindrances to haue kept him from his iournies end: euen ſo it is a ſhame, nay, a farre greater ſhame for thee, that haſt godly Parents and Gouernors, to ſuffer thoſe to out-ſtrip thee in the way to heauen, that haue wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Parents and Tutors. For they will not onely ceaſe to ſpurre them forward to heare the Word, reade Sermons, receiue Sacraments, and the like, (which thy parents doth daily and hourely animate thee vnto,) but alſo what in them lieth, will keepe, hinder, and draw them from hearing the Word, conferring with Saints, reading, praying, receiuing, and all other good and holy exerciſes: therefore as God hath bleſſed thee in this kinde aboue others, ſo labour to exceed others, that at the laſt day the Lord may finde a plentifull harueſt in thy ſoule. Hath the Lord giuen thee a faithfull Miniſter, that is carefull in watching, diligent in feeding, painfull in teaching and inſtructing thy ſoule in the waies of godlineſſe? Doth hee breake the bread of life early and late, preach in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, pray for thy good when thou art faſt aſleepe, and little thinkes of any good to thy owne ſelfe? Then ſee thou bee found holy in life and conuerſation, gratious in all thy words and deeds, heauenly-minded in euery
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:5137:41"/>
place, full of diuine knowledge and godlineſſe. For if thou (that haſt ſo much good teaching) haue not Faith for thy ſhield, the Word for thy ſword, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe for thy breaſt-plate, Truth for thy girdle, the Goſpell for thy ſhooes, Saluation for thy hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, and Chriſt for thy Sauiour; but ſtill like the Papiſts remaineſt ignorant, then greater ſhall be thy damnation; for to whom much is giuen, much ſhall be required. In a word, looke whatſoeuer it is, that the Lord hath bleſſed thee with all aboue other men, ſee thou be found more fruitfull then other men;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.24.</note> elſe as Ieſus ſaid of <hi>Iudas, It had beene good for that man he had neuer beene borne.</hi> So may I ſay to thee, it had beene good for thy ſoule thou hadſt neuer beene made partaker, or once taſted thoſe things, which thou in abundance haſt enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for thoſe that haue receiued much at the hands of God, muſt not be like vnprofitable ground, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing much ſeed, but reſtoring no profit; much dunging, yet far from fructifying; leſt to our ſoules terror and amazement, we heare that fearefull ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; <hi>Take the vnprofitable ſeruant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.30.</note> 
               <hi>binde him hand and foot, and caſt him into vtter darkneſſe, where ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth for euermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, this ſerues for lamentation; for if God require much where he hath beſtowed much: who can refraine from teares, to ſee our land in generall, and almoſt euery man in particular, ſo fruitleſſe and barren in goodneſſe, notwithſtanding all we haue receiued from the Lord? Hath not God planted vs his <hi>Vineyard as on a fruitfull hill?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſ.</hi> 5.1.</note> hath he not <hi>hedged</hi> vs in on euery ſide with the ſhield of his protection?
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:5137:41"/>
hath hee not <hi>gathered out the ſtones</hi> of Popery a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, &amp; <hi>planted</hi> vs in this fertile ſoile, as his <hi>choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt</hi> plants, ſeaſoning our ſoules with his holy do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and heauenly Sacraments; watring vs with the dew of his holy Spirit, and hath <hi>built a Tower</hi> of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent diſcipline amongſt vs? Hath he not lightned our darkneſſe, heated our coldneſſe, reuiued our drooping ſoules, reioyced our trembling hearts, and freed our languiſhing Spirits from ſorrow? Hath hee not opened his <hi>houſe, prouided his meat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 9.5.</note> 
               <hi>mingled his wine,</hi> ſpread his table, ſent forth his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants in a plentifull manner, to call and inuite all thoſe that <hi>be weary and heauy laden,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28.</note> and thoſe that be <hi>a thirſt, to come to the waters of comfort,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 55.1.</note> to buy and <hi>drinke without money, or monies worth?</hi> What ſhall I ſay? Hath hee dealt thus with any Nation? O no; neither haue the heathen knowledge of his Lawes. So gracious and bountifull, and bountifully graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, hath he beene to vs (and that not for <hi>three yeares,</hi> as to the <hi>Fig-tree;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 13.7.</note> but threeſcore, with many yeares aduantage) that he may ſay, and ſay truly to vs, <hi>What more could I haue done for you</hi> my people, then what I haue not done? yet (for the generall) we are as backward and auerſe to all goodneſſe, as though we neuer had receiued any kindneſſe; as far from godlineſſe in our liues and conuerſations, as though God had neuer beene preached amongſt vs. He requires nothing for all his mercies but thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and that is the returne he demands for all his bleſſings: but we are worſe then the ten Lepers, for one of <hi>them returned with praiſes in his mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 17.17.</note> and thankſgiuing in his heart, for the mercy he had
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:5137:42"/>
receiued of the Lord. But let the Lord beſtow ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo many bleſſings vpon vs, ſcarce one of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred will beſtow thankes vnto him for it. It is a commendation that is giuen of the Dogge, that hee is <hi>Fideliſsimus Domino, &amp; gratiſsimus,</hi> moſt faithfull and gratefull to his maſter that maintaines him; for by night he will watch, ward, and diligently keepe his Maſters houſe, and by day he will attend vpon his Maſter abroad; fight for him, and die for him too if need require.<note place="margin">2 <hi>King</hi> 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>Naaman the Syrian,</hi> when hee was cured, would haue <hi>giuen the Prophet a reward,</hi> but we will not giue the Lord ſo much as thanks for all the fauours hee hath beſtowed vpon vs: Gods mercies by vs are now forgotten, as though they had neuer beene. For who remembers the miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ouerthrow of that inuincible Nauy, in the yeare eightie eight? Who remembers the peaceable gouernment of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> (whoſe famous memory ſhall liue for euer?) Who remembers the peaceable entrance of his Maieſtie into this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, when we had cauſe to feare the daies many hoped for? Who remembers the fift of Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, wherein wee had the greateſt deliuerance that euer any Nation had, from that damned, deuilliſh, and helliſh plot of Powder treaſon, inuented by the Deuils eldeſt ſonne the Pope and his followers? Who remembers our freedome from the plague, which waſted thouſands, and ten thouſands in our ſtreets? Who remembers theſe I ſay, with thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands more of Gods mercies? Surely, ſurely, very few or none: and no maruell though thoſe mercies that are paſt be forgotten, when mercies preſent are
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:5137:42"/>
not remembred. Wee forget how the Lord hath dealt more fauourably with vs, then many; yea, then with all Nations round about vs.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144.14.</note> Wee ſee <hi>no carrying into captiuitie, no complaining in our ſtreets:</hi> Our men are not killed, our Nobles are not woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, our Women are not rauiſhed, our Virgins are not defloured, our Infants are not toſſed, our goods are not waſted, nor our Land nor Cities are ruina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Wee heare not the noiſe of the Gun-ſhot, the clattering of Armour, the ſlaſhing of Swords, the grones of the wounded, nor that vnmercileſſe proclamation, Kill, kill, and ſpare none, rip vp the Women, imbowell the aged, and daſh the Infants vpon the ſtones. This, nor none of theſe doe wee heare, which our poore brethren haue felt a long time; yet we forget all. We haue forgotten how he hath kept vs from diſeaſes, reſtored vs from ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and watcheth ouer vs all the day long. Wee haue forgotten how hee feeds vs, carrieth vs in his armes, ſaueth vs from danger, refreſheth vs with ſleepe, draweth the Curtaine of his loue about vs, watching our houſes from fire, from robbers, and from ruine; nay more, haue we not forgotten that wonderfull redemption, wrought by the bloud of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> when we were vtterly loſt? What ſhall I ſay? Sure we haue forgotten all, that makes vs ſo fruitleſſe as we are; for could wee remember theſe things, and prize them according to their worth, our tongues could not bee kept from praiſing the Lord, nor our hearts bee kept from reioycing in God our Sauiour. O vngratefull <hi>England,</hi> and little deſeruing <hi>London,</hi> that haue fed ſo long vpon all
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:5137:43"/>
kinde of Gods mercies, yet no fruitfuller in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to your God! It makes my heart to bleed within my breaſt, to ſee thy rebellious and wicked practiſes, in ſwearing, lying, dancing, ſinging, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, dicing, drinking, drabbing, as though thou didſt intend to crucifie the Sonne of God againe. Is this the entertainment thou doeſt intend to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford Chriſt? Wilt thou requite his loue with ſuch churliſh actions? Shall this be all the fruit thou wilt afford to requite his paines? Then ſhalt thou ſoone make him plucke vp his hedge, that is, take away his fauour, and lay thee open as a prey for all thy ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to feed vpon thee; for to whom much is giuen, much is required.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this ſerues for comfort and conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to all thoſe that finde themſelues fruitfull, though it be but in a little meaſure: for he that hath inabled thee to bring forth any, will (in his good time) ſo ſtrengthen thee, that thou ſhalt bring forth more, holding fruitfull to the end: For they that <hi>are planted in the Courts of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall bring forth much fruit in their old age:</hi> then ſhall all things proſper thou takeſt in hand;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</note> for <hi>bleſſed ſhalt thou be in the Citie, bleſſed in the field, bleſſed ſhall be the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy ground, and the fruit of thy cattle, the increaſe of thy kine, and the flocks of thy ſheepe: Bleſſed ſhall be thy basket and thy ſtore, bleſſed ſhalt thou be when thou commeſt in, bleſſed ſhalt thou bee when thou goeſt out; and bleſſed from this time forth for euermore.</hi> Thus much ſhall ſuffice for the furniſhing of our ſecond Tabernacle.</p>
            <p>Now we come to the laſt body or boule ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:5137:43"/>
from this root, or the third Tabernacle in our Text, which you heard in our diuiſion,<note place="margin">The third Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, like a ſolitary Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, hath three roomes or things remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</note> was made in the forme of a ſolitary Cloſſet, hung round with mourning, wherein we haue our Sauiour Chriſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and hee wept ouer it: it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uides it ſelfe according to the two former parts into three roomes or branches.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the compaſſion it ſelfe: <hi>fleuit,</hi> wept.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is the perſon ſo paſſionate, Chriſt wept.</p>
            <p>The third is the cauſe of his weeping, which as it may be gathered from the words following, is two-fold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tum propter mala culpae,</hi> the euill of ſinne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tum propter mala poenae,</hi> the euill of puniſhment which muſt be inflicted vpon them.</p>
            <p>Begin we firſt with the compaſſion it ſelfe <hi>(wept.)</hi> Here is nothing but <hi>lacrimae &amp; ſuſpiria,</hi> teares, ſighs,<note place="margin">The 1. roome of the third Tabernacle is Compaſſion, he wept.</note> ſobs, and great ſorrowes, deplorations, lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet all fit meditations for our ſoules at this time: for the life of our Sauiour Chriſt was no other then the <hi>paſſage of Ionathan and his Armour-bearer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.4.</note> 
               <hi>ſharpe rockes on the one ſide, ſharpe rockes on the other,</hi> with a very dangerous and infractious paſſage, flin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſtones vnder him, briers and thornes on each ſide of him, mountaines, crags, and promon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries ouer him: <hi>Sic petitur coelum:</hi> ſo heauen muſt be caught or neuer, or elſe loſt for euer. Hee wept, and in his weeping ſhed teares, which are the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward expreſſion of ſorrow and griefe: A man may couer ſorow a long time by ſecret ſobs and inward
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:5137:44"/>
groanes, but when teares breake from the eies, as water from the fountaine, it plainely demonſtrateth to the view of all beholders, the wonderfull griefe conceiued in the weepers breaſt: for as fire ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering, will at laſt breake into a flame, ſo will a grieued and an oppreſſed ſoule into teares, as heere our Sauiour. But what teares were theſe our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſhed? Diuines doe make teares to be of diuers ſorts, but I will onely follow <hi>Goran,</hi> as liking his di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtinction of teares beſt: for he in his Commentaries on the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> maketh mention of three ſorts of teares.<note place="margin">
                  <p>Lacrimae contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis.</p>
                  <p>Lacrimae com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionis.</p>
                  <p>Lacrimae deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis.</p>
                  <p>Gor. ſuper Pſal. in Pſal. <hi>137.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Firſt, the teares of Contrition; ſecondly, the teares of Compaſſion; thirdly, the teares of Deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: The contrite teares, or teares of contrition, is either for ſinne committed, or good duties omitted; but our Sauiour neither committed euill, nor omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted good, therefore could not ſhed the teares of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition. As for the teares of deuotion, or deuout teares, they are powred forth in holy and religious exerciſes; as praying, hearing, receiuing, conferring, or meditating, or becauſe we are debarred from ſo doing. But theſe were not the teares which our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our powred forth at this time: I cannot deny but that at ſometimes hee ſhed the teares of deuotion, for his praier was heard which he ſent vp to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>with ſtrong cries and teares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7.</note> as the Apoſtle affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, yet at this time there were no ſuch teares: then as for the teares of compaſſion, they are either for the miſeries of others, as thoſe teares which the <hi>Daughters of Hieruſalem ſhed</hi> when Chriſt went to be crucified,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 23.28.</note> or elſe for the wickedneſſe of others: as thoſe teares which <hi>Lot ſhed for Sodome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.</note> 
               <hi>and Dauid
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:5137:44"/>
for his enemies:</hi> ſuch were the teares of Chriſt, which here he ſhed for <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond branch of this body or boule,<note place="margin">The ſecond thing in the third Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, is the perſon wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, Chriſt.</note> or roome in this Tabernacle, is the perſon weeping, which by our Text is found to be Chriſt; and that may make theſe teares of Chriſtians the more to be lamented, of all the more to bee admired. Who doth not ſtand amazed when hee conſiders theſe teares, for they are not the teares of man, but of the Sonne of God: the more worthy the perſon is that weepeth, the more aſtoniſhment it ſtrikes into the beholder. If a mortall King ſhould ſhed teares, would it not cauſe wonder; yea, amazement, trembling, and feare, becauſe wee ſhould imagine that their teares doe proceed either from ſome great anger, or ſome great danger: much more may theſe teares aſtoniſh vs, becauſe they proceed not from the eies of an earthly King, but from him that is <hi>Rex coelorum &amp; terrae,</hi> the King of heauen and earth, euen Ieſus Chriſt the <hi>eternall Sonne of God.</hi> The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> when hee did but conſider how the Sea opened for <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſafetie, was ſo amazed, that out of the aſtoniſhment of his ſoule hee cries out, ſaying; <hi>What ailed thee, O Sea, that thou fleddeſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 114.5.</note> 
               <hi>thou Iordan, that thou waſt driuen backe?</hi> How much more may we out of the amazement of our ſoules cry (now we ſee not onely the Sea to open, but the bleſſed Sonne of God diſtilling abundant of teares from his faire eies vpon his tender cheekes:) What aileth thee, O thou Ieſus, that thou ſo weepeſt? Thou bleſſed Sauiour of mankinde, that teares runs ſo faſt from thy vnſpotted eies? Doeſt thou ſo
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:5137:45"/>
weepe for thoſe that laugh at thee? yea, doſt thou ſhed teares for thoſe that neither will, nor can weepe for themſelues? Are our ſinnes ſo piercing to thy ſoule ſo pleaſant to vs? doth our wickedneſſe wring groanes, ſighes, ſobs, and briniſh teares from thy faire eies; nay, bloud from thy moſt tender heart, and cannot we ſhed one teare for our ſelues? Then hard is our hearts, and miſerable our caſe.</p>
            <p>Oh my deare Brethren and louing Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, know this one thing; how that it was not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other wept for him; that he could not endure, <hi>(O Daughters of Hieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 23.28.</note> 
               <hi>weepe not for mee, but for your ſelues)</hi> but he for others, though he neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to ſhed one teare, yet ceaſeth not to powre forth riuers of teares for this hard-hearted Nation. For my Text tells me, that <hi>He wept,</hi> not an Angell, a Saint, or a Sinner, but <hi>He;</hi> yea, euen <hi>He; He</hi> that was all one with the father;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.35. <hi>Matth.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>He</hi> that was full of glory and might, <hi>He</hi> that was promiſed to our firſt Parents in Paradice; <hi>He</hi> that was <hi>conceiued by the holy Ghoſt,</hi> and <hi>borne of the Virgin Marie; Hee</hi> that at his birth troubled <hi>Herod</hi> and all <hi>Hieruſalem; He</hi> that was exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and there obſcurely kept in the Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a poore foſter-father; <hi>He</hi> that was tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and tempted by Satan; <hi>He</hi> that was derided of his kindred, and blaſphemouſly traduced of the <hi>Iewes; Hee</hi> that by the words of his mouth ſtilled the <hi>raging of the Sea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.26. <hi>&amp; Pſal.</hi> 65.7.</note> the ruffling of the <hi>winds,</hi> and the madneſſe of his <hi>people; He</hi> that cauſed the <hi>Fiſh</hi> to bring him money from the bottome of the Sea;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.27. <hi>Matth.</hi> 14.19.</note> 
               <hi>He</hi> that fed <hi>fiue thouſands with fiue loaues and two ſmall fiſhes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.1.</note> 
               <hi>Hee</hi> that made the <hi>Blinde</hi> to ſee, the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:5137:45"/>
               <hi>deafe</hi> to heare, the <hi>lame</hi> to goe;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 7.34. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.5. <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.44. <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.29. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.5. <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.28, 29.</note> 
               <hi>Hee that cleanſed the Lepers,</hi> cured the <hi>diſeaſed,</hi> and <hi>raiſed the dead</hi> from the graue; <hi>He</hi> that made the <hi>Deuils</hi> to cry, <hi>What haue we to doe with thee, Ieſus thou Sonne of Dauid? Art thou come to torment vs before the time? He</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued this teſtimony three times from God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>This is my beloued Sonne, in whom onely I am well pleaſed; He that did all things well, and neuer any euill,</hi> neither to God nor man. It is <hi>He</hi> that <hi>wept</hi> in this my Text, and none but he: <hi>He,</hi> euen <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> the Sauiour and Redeemer of the world, the Parragon and Prince of Prophets, the true Meſſias, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ioy, the Angels bliſſe, heauens beautie, the <hi>glorie of Iſrael,</hi> the <hi>light of the Gentiles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 2.32.</note> the worlds Sauiour prefigured in the Law, fore-told by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and exhibited in the Goſpell. It was <hi>He</hi> that <hi>wept:</hi> from whence we might draw many concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I will but point at them at this time; yet promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to all thoſe that affects goodneſſe to inlarge them according to their worthineſſe, if ſtrength of body permit hereafter.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in that he wept it ſhewes vs,<note place="margin">Chriſt wept, therefore 1. Man. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.15.</note> how <hi>He was true man, conſiſting of ſoule and body,</hi> as all other men do, yet not ſinfull man: for he was <hi>like to vs in all things, ſinne onely excepted,</hi> neither are we ſo to take our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, as no more but man: for though hee were man, yet he was more then man, hauing the diuine Nature, hypoſtatically vnited to the humane; ſo that hee reſted not God alone, nor man alone, but <hi>God-man,</hi> and <hi>Man-God;</hi> perfect God, begotten of his Father; perfect Man, borne of his Mother.<note place="margin">2. Great his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection towards man.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in that he wept, he ſhewes vs how <hi>that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:5137:46"/>
great is his affection towards mankinde:</hi> the affection of a Father to his childe, or of a Mother to the fruit of her owne wombe, is nothing in reſpect of the Lords affection towards Man: for had he not affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted vs, he would neuer haue died for vs, but he did not onely weepe, but die for our ſinnes, therefore needs muſt we conclude, his affection was great vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. Chriſt not delighted in the deſtruction of his enemies.</note>Thirdly, in that he wept, it ſhewes vs how <hi>that he was no whit delighted in the deſtruction of his enemies.</hi> Though man reioyce at their enemies ruines, either in body, goods, or name, making that day (though a day of faſting) a day of feaſting, when tidings is brought of the ſubuerſion, ruine, and deſolation, of thoſe whom they affect not; yet it is not ſo with our Sauiour, for he fore-ſeeing their deſolation, wrung from his eies abundant teares of compaſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. Greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in the conuerſion of man.</note>Fourthly, in that he wept, it ſhewes vs, <hi>That he is greatly delighted in the conuerſion of others,</hi> that weeps ſo bitterly at the <hi>ſubuerſion</hi> of others; for he is the louing Father that euer is ready to receiue his prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall children, at what time ſoeuer they doe repent them of their ſins from the bottome of their hearts, and that not with grudging,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.17.</note> but with delight; for ſo greatly is he reioyced when wee forſake our ſins, as that he counts nothing too deare for our ſoules. If we be naked, he brings <hi>a robe to couer vs;</hi> if we be hungry,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 15.12, 23.</note> he <hi>killeth the fat Calfe to feed vs;</hi> and if not married to the fleſh, world, nor deuill, <hi>hee brings a Ring</hi> to wed vs; for if hee mourne for man when man was dead and loſt, how greatly will he reioyce at man when man is liuing found.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:5137:46"/>Fiftly, in that <hi>he wept,</hi> and that when the people cut downe the branches of the trees,<note place="margin">5 Worldly pompe would be mixed with teares.</note> ſpreading their garments in the way, euery one crying with a ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full acclamation, <hi>Hoſanna in the higheſt, bleſſed is hee that commeth in the name of the Lord,</hi> We learne that which <hi>Ludolphus</hi> doth obſerue,<note place="margin">Ludolphus de imitat. vitae Chriſti. par. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That worldly pompe and applauſe ſhould be mixed with teares:</hi> For though it were neuer ſo great, it cannot alwaies free from ſorrow, eſpecially if wee belong vnto God. I know the wicked will and can ſhift off their ſorrow, with the Viall, Harpe, Lute, or ſinging to the tune of the Organs. <hi>Pompillius</hi> writes Epiſtles to <hi>Tullie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pompillius <hi>to</hi> Tully. Antimachus.</note> thinking to rid away his ſorrow by reading. <hi>Antima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> makes verſes, thinking to rid away his ſorrowes by riming. <hi>Archilochus</hi> calls for Wine, thinking to to rid away his ſorrow by drinking.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chiſochus.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.22, 23</note> 
               <hi>Saul</hi> calls for Muſicke, thinking to rid away his ſorrow by play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Some call for cards and dice, thinking to rid away their ſorrow by gaming; but alas, all in vaine: for neither the world nor any thing in the world, can free vs alwaies from ſorrow, eſpecially if we belong to the Lord, for <hi>Quid ad nos conſolatio mundi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Martia Epiſe.</note> What doe the pleaſures of the world belong to vs: for the world is but <hi>ſpuma, fumus, ſomnium,</hi> a froth, a ſmoake, a dreame: a froth, becauſe it puffeth vp; a ſmoake, becauſe it maketh blinde; a dreame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it vaniſheth away. Yea, as a good Diuine ſaies, it is Vices Nurſe, Natures ſtep-mother, Vertues murtherer, Thefts refuge, Woredomes pander, <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes</hi> fruit, Crocodils teares, a Syrens ſong; yea, as <hi>Philo</hi> calleth it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a bitter ſweet; pleaſure is a ſpurre, riches a thorne, honor a blaſt, life a flower,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:5137:47"/>
glory a feather, beautie a fancy, ioy a frenzy, and all things in the world but like the Booke in the <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ap.</hi> 10.9.</note> ſweet in the mouth, bitter in the belly; or like the reeds in <hi>Egypt,</hi> which doth not onely breake in peeces when it is <hi>leaned on;</hi> but in breaking, flieth in ſplinters,<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 18.21.</note> to the <hi>piercing of the hands</hi> of him that truſted to it; or like a draught of cold water, drunke vp by him that is heated with the violence of a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Feauer, which allaieth the heat, during the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of drinking; but ſcarcely is the Cup gone from his mouth, before he feeleth an increaſe of his boiling drought; or like money taken vp from the cheſt of the Vſurer, which will ſtop a gap for the preſent, but afterwards make the wound the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6. Cities are chiefly to be lamented.</note>Sixthly &amp; laſtly, in that <hi>He wept,</hi> and <hi>ouer Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> the ſame Citie that he drew neere vnto, and euen now beheld, We learne, <hi>That Cities ought chiefly to be lamented:</hi> Theſe things we might handle at large, but leſt your patience ſhould be vrged, my weak body too much ſtrained, and all our memories ouer charged, I ceaſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution till ſome other occaſion: in the meane while I referre theſe heads to your godly meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and for a concluſion, will onely ſpeake a word or two of the cauſe of theſe teares,<note place="margin">Cauſes of Chriſt wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ouer <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi>
               </note> which is two-fold. Firſt, <hi>Propter mala culpae,</hi> the euill of ſinne committed by them. Secondly, <hi>Propter mala poenae,</hi> the euill of puniſhment that was to be inflicted vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Cauſe was <hi>propter mala culpae,</hi> their ſinnes.</note>Firſt, <hi>Propter mala culpae,</hi> the euill of ſinne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by them: This was the greateſt cauſe that
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:5137:47"/>
produceth our Sauiours teares;<note place="margin">Roy. Poſt.</note> for <hi>non ruinam lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, ſed hominum vanitatem,</hi> ſaies <hi>Royard</hi> in his <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtils:</hi> He wept not ſo much for the ruine of the City, as the vanitie of the people. Neuer did the nailes ſo wound him, nor the ſpeares ſo gore him, as their ſinnes did pierce him. Neuer was the gall ſo bitter to his taſte, nor the thornes ſo pricking to his touch, as their ſinnes was offenſiue to his ſoule: Neuer was their fiſts ſo ſmarting to his cheekes, nor their ſpittle ſo loathſome to his face, as their ſinnes were hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to his heart: Neuer was their flouts ſo hurtfull to his name, nor the Croſſe ſo tormenting to his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rure, as their ſinnes were burdenſome to his body and ſoule: for ſo heauy a weight was their ſinnes to him, that it did not onely make him pray once,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.44. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.44.</note> twice, and thrice, nor to ſweat, and that in a cold winters night, water and bloud, nor to complaine, <hi>I thirſt,</hi> but to cry,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 19.</note> and that with ſuch a lamentable cry, as made both heauen and earth to ſtand ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, the Sunne to hide his face, as not daring to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Sonne of God in ſuch a caſe as he was in, when he cried, <hi>Eli Eli lamaſabachthani, My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me.</hi> Blame not therefore our Sauiour to weepe, ſince ſinne is ſo tormenting to his ſoule. Of old the Lord complaineth by the mouth of his holy Prophet;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 2.13.</note> That <hi>he was preſſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their ſinnes as a Cart is preſſed with ſheaues,</hi> which Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> thus gloſſeth, <hi>As a Cart laden with hay or ſtubble, maketh a noiſe, ſoundeth out, and howleth, ſo I howle and cry vnder your ſinnes,</hi> ſaith the Lord; euen <hi>ſhriking</hi> as ſometimes a cart doth: and no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, for their ſinnes were not few, but many; yea,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:5137:48"/>
more then can bee numbred by any Arithmetician, and greater then can be meaſured by any Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trician.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 1.4. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 1.5. <hi>&amp; Ier.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 17.21. <hi>Ier.</hi> 6.14. <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Amos</hi> 6.6. <hi>Eſay</hi> 3.16, <hi>&amp;c. Ier.</hi> 9 5. <hi>Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k.</hi> 6.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5. <hi>Iere.</hi> 17.25.</note> I will not now ſtand to tell you of their <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi> not of their <hi>ſwearing and forſwearing,</hi> nor of their profaning the Lords <hi>Saboath,</hi> nor of their <hi>falſe teachers,</hi> nor of their <hi>contempt of Gods word,</hi> nor of their <hi>Couetouſneſſe,</hi> nor of their <hi>ſloth and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> nor of their <hi>pride,</hi> nor of their <hi>deceit,</hi> nor of their <hi>whoredome,</hi> nor of their <hi>vnthankfulneſſe,</hi> nor of their <hi>waxing worſe and worſe,</hi> with many moe. All which I will not ſpend time about, becauſe I know you haue heard them, and hope by frequent rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Bible you know them, but needs it muſt be granted, that ſince their ſinnes did ſo abound, it was the cauſe that our Sauiours teares did much more abound.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Our ſinnes as well a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalems, draw teares from Chriſts eies.</note>And was it their ſinnes alone, that wrung theſe teares from our bleſſed Sauiours eies; alas no, ſweet Ieſus, thou knoweſt it was ours as well as theirs: for all thy labours, thy troubles, thy miſeries, thy griefes, thy ſweatings, thy bleedings, and thy tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which in the daies of thy fleſh, from the firſt houre of thy Natiuitie, to the laſt moment of thy ſufferings vpon the Croſſe, was for our ſinnes, and for our ſakes: our ſinnes, I ſay, was the cauſe of all. <hi>Eſay</hi> confeſſed it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſ.</hi> 53.4, 5.</note> ſaying; <hi>Hee hath borne our griefes, and carried our ſorrowes; hee was wounded for our tranſgreſsion; he was bruized for our iniquities: the chaſtiſement of our peace was vpon him and with his ſtripes we are healed.</hi> If there be euer an vnbeleeuing <hi>Iew</hi> amongſt vs, that ſhould demand this vnſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable queſtion: Why doth our Sauiour weepe for
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:5137:48"/>
my ſinnes? Hee hath his anſwer from theſe ſhort Arguments following.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe it grieues the Father, offends his Maieſtie, vexeth his holy Spirit of grace:<note place="margin">Chriſt weeps for ſinnes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 1. they grieue God and his bleſſed Spirit. 2. Procure pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23.</note> Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one that loues the Father, cannot chuſe but weepe at that which grieues and offends the Father.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe it procureth puniſhment from the Father, either temporall or eternall; for <hi>the reward of ſinne is death;</hi> Death in this life, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a great repentance, eternall death in the life to come.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, becauſe it ſeparates grace from the ſoule,<note place="margin">3. Separate grace and God from man. <hi>Eſay</hi> 59.2.</note> and the ſoule from grace, <hi>&amp; God from the whole man,</hi> for it is a high brazen wall, hindring our praiers from aſcending to God, his graces from deſcending to vs.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, becauſe it reioyceth the Deuill,<note place="margin">4. Reioyce Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan.</note> who is Chriſts greateſt enemy, for ſinne is meat and drinke to Satan. When any dances after his pipe, he is as greatly reioyced, as a man that hath taken many ſpoiles: if all this then bee true, as the Lord hee knowes it is too true, needs muſt it make Ieſus to weepe, if either he reſpect God or loue man.</p>
            <p>If this then be ſo, it may teach vs in the firſt place to take heed of ſinne. O delight not in it,<note place="margin">1. Delight not in ſinne.</note> ſince it is an offence both to God and godly men: therefore deteſt it, and flie from it as from the Deuill, who is the Author of it; it is a fire and will burne thee; water, and will drowne thee; a nettle, and will ſting thee; a ſword, and will wound thee; poiſon, and will kill thee; and a Serpent, which will deuoure thee; kill it, or elſe it will kill thee; be a ſtranger to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:5137:49"/>
it, it will be a ſtranger to thee; harbour it not to gain the world, to grieue Chriſt: but beat out the braines of theſe Babiloniſh children;<note place="margin">Sinne to be nipped in the bud. <hi>Iud</hi> 7.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.30 <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.5. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 11.1. 2. <hi>Par.</hi> 22.10.</note> for if they die thou maieſt liue, but if they liue thou ſhalt die. As the reigne of <hi>Abimelech</hi> was the ſlaughter of <hi>Gedeons</hi> Sonnes; and the reigne of <hi>Athaliah was the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the Kings ſeed:</hi> ſo the reigne of our ſinnes will be our deſtruction. Let vs therefore beat them downe betimes before they grow too head-ſtrong, like an vnruly Maſtiue Dogge tearing out their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters throat; the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> at firſt ſpared the <hi>Canaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> afterwards when they would haue deſtroied them they could not; but they became <hi>prickes in their eies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.55. <hi>Iud.</hi> 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>and goads in their ſides:</hi> Euen ſo will it bee with our ſinnes, for if at firſt we ſpare them, in the end they will be vnreſiſtable. Oh that wee could once liue to ſay of our ſinnes, as Chriſt ſaid of the Temple,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.2.</note> 
               <hi>One ſtone ſhall not be left vpon another vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt downe:</hi> ſo one ſinne ſhall not be left vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vncaſt out of the heart. Then would they ſoone die in our liues and conuerſations, but ſo long as we harbour them in the hidden man, ſo long will our liues bee corrupted, and our conuerſations dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted: let vs therefore bury our ſinnes that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be remembred; kill our ſinnes, that their power againſt vs, neuer be lamented; caſt out our ſinnes as dung out of the Citie, that they neuer be reſpected: for as carrion cauſeth wormes, ſtinkes, and feedeth Fowles; ſo our ſinnes cauſeth woes, and ſorrowes, and feedeth the Deuill.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.24, 27.</note> O therefore <hi>breake off your ſinnes by repentance,</hi> breake off your iniquitie by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to the Lord your God. Nothing can ſtench
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:5137:49"/>
Chriſts teares, vnleſſe we ſtop our ſinnes; nothing can dry his cheekes, vnleſſe wee waſh our hearts;<note place="margin">The beſt acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if ſinne be not ſtopped, dry not Chriſts cheekes.</note> nothing can cleare his eies, vnleſſe wee purge our ſoules; our ſinging Pſalmes, hearing Sermons, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing Sacraments, reading Homilies, feeding the hungry, clothing the naked, viſiting the ſicke, buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hoſpitals, repairing Churches, catechiſing fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, nor all the gliſtring profeſſion in the world can ſtop Chriſts teares, vnleſſe wee make conſcience of ſinning. We muſt not be of <hi>Abrahams</hi> heart and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lials</hi> life, we may not beare the ſoule of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and the ſhewes of <hi>Phariſes:</hi> Good King <hi>Ioſaphat</hi> in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturing to <hi>goe like Ahab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.32.</note> had like to haue beene ſlaine for <hi>Ahab;</hi> ſo all thoſe are in danger of deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that make a ſhew outwardly, but like <hi>Sodoms</hi> Apples are corrupted inwardly; for if thoſe be in danger which are vpright in heart, &amp; faile in act, how much more are they in danger that gliſter like Gold, but being toucht, are found Copper? I pray God our ſinnes haue not wrung more teares from the eies of our Sauiour then euer the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſinnes did; I feare they haue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1.</note> becauſe I ſee the <hi>more his grace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds,</hi> the more our <hi>ſinnes abound;</hi> by how much the more mercifull God hath beene to vs, the more miſcreants haue we beene towards him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In agro Narnien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi ſiceitate lutum fieri (ex Plinio) imbre pulurem.</hi> That aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of grace ſhould produce abundance of iniquitie is Chriſts greater griefe.</note> 
               <hi>Tully</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth amongſt all his wonders in Nature, that in one Country drought cauſeth dirt, and raine ſtirreth vp duſt. Whether this be ſo or no, I ſtand not heare to proue; but this I know, that the abundance of Gods graces hath brought forth nothing, but abundance of ſinnes: Iniquitie was neuer ſo rife, as ſince fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent preaching of the Goſpell; yet the fault is not
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:5137:50"/>
in the world, but in the Deuill and our corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: God may call a Conuocation of heauen and earth together againſt vs, as ſometimes hee did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his owne people the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 1.2.</note> ſaying; <hi>Hearken, heauens, giue eare O earth, I haue nouriſhed and brought vp children, but they haue rebelled againſt me: Had they beene my enemies that had done mee this diſhonour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.12, 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>I could haue borne it;</hi> or had they beene my ſeruants, or the ſonnes of <hi>Hagar</hi> that had magnified them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt me, I could haue endured it, but it was Children, yea, euen my Children, Children of my owne education and bringing vp; thoſe that were nurtured and inſtructed in my owne family, and that by my owne hand; it was they that rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me; therefore <hi>hearken O heauens, and giue eare O earth.</hi> Nay the Lord may take vp his owne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt this Citie, which you lately had ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in your eares by a thundring Trumpet of the Lord:<note place="margin">I meane Maſter <hi>Wood</hi> in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at the Spittle on Wedneſday in Eaſter weeke laſt, 1624. <hi>Hoſea.</hi> 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>There is no truth, nor mercy, nor knowledge of God in the Land: For by ſwearing, and lying, and killing, and ſtealing, and whoring, they breake out, and bloud toucheth bloud.</hi> Are theſe things ſo, and doe they cauſe no teares? O yes! and ſhall bring iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment too, if they be not amended. Our ſweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours patience ſhewes his deſire of our amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if tongue or teares can procure it; beſides, ſo great is his deſire of our repentance, that hee vſeth a very patheticall perſwaſion to induce vs thereunto by the tongue of his bleſſed Spirit, recorded by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> in the Booke of the <hi>Canticles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.13.</note> ſaying; <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, returne, O Shulamite, returne, returne:</hi> but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, we cannot returne of our ſelues: being by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:5137:50"/>
dead and lumpiſh;<note place="margin">Man like a Coachwheele moues not to any grace if not drawne. <hi>Iere.</hi> 31.18.</note> euen like to a Coach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wheele, able to run no further then wee be drawne; therefore let vs reply with the holy Prophet <hi>Ieremy, Turne vs, O Lord, and we ſhall be turned; conuert vs, and we ſhall be conuerted indeed.</hi> Yea, let vs pray with Saint <hi>Auguſtine, Domine da quod iubes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; iube quod vis, id eſt,</hi> Lord giue vs abilitie to returne vnto thee, and then command vs to returne, or inable vs to doe what thou commandeſt, then command what thou wilt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if Chriſt weepe for our ſinnes,<note place="margin">Seeing Chriſt weeps for ours, wee ſhould weepe for our owne.</note> we are taught to weepe for our owne. Wee muſt not be like ſtockes and ſtones that haue no ſenſe nor feeling of our owne miſerie; neither muſt wee be like men dead, ſince wee make a ſhew of life: for if Chriſt weepe for vs, wee haue much more cauſe to weepe for our ſelues. It may be the worldling thinkes hee need not weepe, becauſe Chriſt wept not for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but for vs: For ſaith the careleſſe Carnaliſt, If his bloud be ſufficient for my ſoule without mine, why not his teares for my ſinnes without mine? Thus to a deſolute liuer, the teares of Chriſt are like <hi>Mercuries</hi> ſtill-pipe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mercuries</hi> ſtill-pipe.</note> which plaied <hi>Argus</hi> his hundred eies aſleepe at once. But let me tell thee, O thou traytour to thy owne ſoule, though Chriſts bloud be ſufficient without thine, yet not his teares with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thine. For when he ſhed his bloud, it was to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme thee from ſinne, but when he ſheds his teares,<note place="margin">Our ſins coſt Chriſt both teares &amp; bloud, therefore we muſt at leaſt ſhed teares for them.</note> it is in ſeeing thee runne ſo faſt to ſinne; therefore as it coſt him both bloud and teares to come to thee, ſo it muſt coſt thee at the leaſt many a ſhower of teares before thou canſt come to him. Hee ſailed
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:5137:51"/>
thorow the Sea of bloud to ſaue thy ſoule; thou muſt ſaile thorow the Sea of teares to win his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour. If thou refuſe to lanch forth into the Sea of Contrition in this world, thou ſhalt be drowned in the Ocean of perdition in the world to come; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to purge thy heart, to free thy ſoule, to winne Chriſts fauour, be not backward to weepe, but po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer forth teares with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. <hi>Ion.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>Eſay</hi> 38.14. <hi>Iob</hi> 3.24. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.75. <hi>Luke</hi> 7.38. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16 30.</note> apparell thy ſelfe in ſackcloth with <hi>Niniuy,</hi> humble thy ſelfe to the ground with <hi>Abraham, mourne like a Doue with Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia, rore out thy griefe with Iob, powre forth thy ſoule with Hanna, rent thy heart with the penitent, lament thy ſinnes with Peter, let ſorrow bee thy feaſt with Mary, and cry out with the Iewes and Iaylor, Men and brethren, what ſhall we doe to be ſaued?</hi> It may be thou thinkes thou doeſt ſorrow, but delude not thy ſoule; for euery groane, and ſigh, and crying, Lord haue mercy vpon me, is no true ſorrow: but grant it be, yet where are the teares? Chriſt did not ſigh,<note place="margin">Chriſt did not ſtay in ſighing, groning, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but alſo ſhed both teares &amp; bloud.</note> groane, and pray for thee, then reſting himſelfe contented as if he had done ſufficient, but as a man neuer ſatisfied in affection, was not contented till he had ſhed teares from his eies; nay, bloud from his heart for the ſinnes of thy body and ſoule: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if thou thus truly ſorrow,<note place="margin">Teares, griefes chiefe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.</note> ſhew mee thy teares, for teares are griefes chiefe teſtimonies, the ſorrow of the minde will ſoone bewray it ſelfe by the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the man:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seneca.</hi> Neither plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure nor profit, nor any thing in the world ſhould hinder teares.</note> if thou canſt not weepe, then thou haſt moſt reaſon to weepe, for there is no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cauſe of ſorrow miniſtred, then where teares are aboliſhed. Doth the worlds pleaſure or profit ſtop or hinder thee from penitentiall teares? Then call
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:5137:51"/>
to minde <hi>Salomon</hi> and <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>Salomon</hi> who enioyed many things, yet ſaid of all things in this world, <hi>Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas vanitatum, &amp; omnia vanitas,</hi> Vanity of vanity, &amp; all is but vanity. Chriſt who enioyed no thing of this worlds good, yet ſaid;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.26.</note> 
               <hi>What ſhal it profit a man to win the whole world, and loſe his owne ſoule.</hi> Let not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world, nor any thing in the world withdraw thee from weeping for ſinne, but rather lament the more: for the more thou weepeſt here, the more thou ſhalt reioyce hereafter. <hi>Peter</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he came to Chriſt, leapt into a Sea of waters; but when he went from Chriſt, leapt into a Sea of teares: our ſins deſerue as much; for a whole ocean of teares, will hardly rince our ſoules. <hi>Dauid,</hi> though <hi>a man after Gods own heart,</hi> yet complaineth that he was like <hi>a Pellican in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe,</hi> whoſe nature is euer to haue teares trickling downe her bill. For teares were <hi>his meat day and night,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>yea, he waſhed his bed, and watred his couch;</hi> nay, <hi>made it to ſwim with the teares of his complaint Ioſiah</hi> though he were a powerfull Prince ouer a great people, yet his <hi>heart melted like wax, and his eies weept bitterly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 22.19.</note> when he heard the words of the Law. Looke vpon <hi>Iob,</hi> that was the Mirror of patience, yet vpon the dunghil he ſits weeping night &amp; day, crying out moſt pittiouſly: <hi>My ſighings come before I eat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh</hi> 3.24.</note> 
               <hi>and my rorings are powred out like water.</hi> Looke vpon holy <hi>Ieremy,</hi> you ſhall finde his eies <hi>caſting forth riuers of teares.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.48.</note> Looke vpon <hi>Iona,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iona.</hi> 2.2.</note> you ſhall finde him <hi>weeping at the bottome of the ſea, and in the belly of hell.</hi> Looke vpon <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> you ſhall finde her weeping,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 7.38.</note> and that in ſuch exceſſiue manner, that ſhee is able with teares to bathe the <hi>feet of Chriſt.</hi> In a word,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:5137:52"/>
view but any one of the Children of God, and tell me whether you finde them backward in weeping for ſinne,<note place="margin">None come to heauen with dry eies, at leaſt not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a ſorrow for not wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. <hi>Reu.</hi> 21.4.</note> yea or no? Can we finde none that euer came to heauen with dry eies, and ſhall wee thinke to come to heauen with a merry countenance? Surely no; for Chriſt is ſaid in the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> to <hi>wipe away all teares from his childrens eies.</hi> But how can he wipe them away from thoſe that neuer either did, or ſorrowed that they could not ſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny? Awake therefore, O thou ſinner, weepe and howle for the ſinnes thou haſt committed againſt God, againſt man, and againſt thine owne ſoules conſcience, leſt judgement <hi>ouertake thee, and there be none to helpe thee;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.22.</note> but away thou muſt to the graue, before thou haſt repented.</p>
            <p>Once there was a certaine King that neuer was ſeene to laugh or ſmile; In all places, amongſt all perſons, at all times, hee was very penſiue and ſad. His Queene being much grieued thereat, came to his Brother, requeſting him to aske of the King, what was the cauſe of his continuall ſadneſſe. No ſooner had this Noble man fulfilled this Princeſſe deſire; but the King his Brother replied, I will tell thee next day; ſo he departed for that time. When the King perceiued he was gone, he went preſently and cauſed a great deepe pit to be made, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his ſeruants to fill it halfe full with firie-coles; hauing ſo done, hee cauſeth an old rotten boord to be laid vpon it, and ouer the boord to hang a two-edged ſword by a ſmall threed, with the point downewards, and cloſe by the pit to ſet a table full of all manner of dainty meats and delicious wines.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:5137:52"/>
This being thus done, he commanded his Brother to be placed vpon that rotten boord, and foure men to ſtand round about him with drawne ſwords; one before, another behinde, a third on his left hand, a fourth on his right; alſo, he ſent for Drums, Trumpets, and all other kinde of Muſicke, which his Country afforded, to play, ſing, and dance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Brother. Then the King called vnto him, ſaying, Reioyce and be merry, O my Brother, eat, drinke, and laugh, for here is pleaſant being: but he replied and ſaid; O my Lord and King, how can I be merry, ſince I am in ſuch danger on euery ſide; looking vnder me, I ſee coles of fire, and if I ſtirre, this rotten boord will breake, then ſhall I fall into the pit and be conſumed to aſhes. In looking vp, I ſee a ſword right ouer me, which if it be but touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, fals downe and ſlaies me: In looking on either hand, behinde and before me, I ſee men ſtand with naked ſwords to take away my life. Since therefore I am in the midſt of ſo many dangers, how can I eat drinke, or be merry? for theſe ſame ſights doe turne my ioy into ſorrow, and my laughing into lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Then the King ſaid, Looke how it is now with thee, ſo it is alwaies with me: for if I looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mee, I ſee the great and dreadfull Iudge, to whom I muſt giue an account of all my thoughts, words and deeds, good or euill. If I looke vnder me, I ſee the endleſſe torments of hell, wherein I ſhall be caſt if I die in my ſinnes. If I looke behinde me, I ſee all the ſinnes that euer I haue committed, and the time which vnprofitably I haue ſpent. If I looke before me, I ſee my death euery day approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:5137:53"/>
neerer and neerer vnto my body. If I looke on my right hand, I ſee my conſcience accuſing me of all that I haue done, and left vndone in this world. And if I looke on my left hand, I ſee the creatures crying vengeance againſt me, becauſe they <hi>groaned vnder my iniquities.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 21.</note> Now therefore won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not, hence-forward, why I cannot reioyce, but ſtill mourne and weepe. O that all men could thus conſider their eſtate, then ſhould they finde ſmall cauſe to reioyce at the world, or any thing in the world, but imploiment for <hi>Argus</hi> his eies, yet all lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle enough to weepe and ſhed teares for the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eſtate wherein wee ſtand by ſinne: for theſe things are hidden from the worlds eie; they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count their eſtate to be happy, bleſſing themſelues in the abundance of their riches, and becauſe they are not <hi>afflicted like vnto other men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.5.</note> they thinke of no better heauen then that which they enioy vpon earth. For <hi>the Prince of this world</hi> hath ſo blinded their minds, that they cannot diſcerne what is good for their ſoules.</p>
            <p>Many times I mourne, as one who cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe chuſe, to ſee the folly of this world, and what excuſes the ſonnes of men will make to free their eies from weeping, and that not onely of the profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſort, but alſo of ſuch as make great ſhew of Religion, in ſo much that now a daies true peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall teares is as rare to finde or ſee, (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe is) a blacke Swan. Euery true teare in this age wherein wee liue, is a pearle in price, and a few of them is worth a Kings ranſome. But where ſhall we finde them? In the Court? Alas no; there is
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:5137:53"/>
pride and vanitie,<note place="margin">Teares for ſin in this age, ſcarce any where to be ſeene in any eſtate gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally. <hi>Hoſea.</hi> 4.2. Not in the Citie, Inns of Court.</note> and hardly any roome for true penitentiall teares. Are they in the Citie? No; for there is ſwearing, lying, ſtealing, whoring, and brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out, till bloud touch bloud; therefore there is hardly any roome for theſe true teares. Are they in the Innes of Court or Weſtminſter Hall? Alas no; vnleſſe it bee the poore Clients teares, who weeps more for the loſſe of his money amongſt Lawyers, then for his ſoule by ſinne: for there is delaying of Iudgement, demurring of Cauſes, and ſelling of Iuſtice, but no place for true teares. Are they in the Countrey? Surely no;<note place="margin">Country.</note> for there is nothing but labouring day by day, weeke by weeke, and yeare by yeare, for the maintenance of the body, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer once dreaming of the good of the ſoule. Are they among the Gentry? No neither;<note place="margin">Gentry.</note> vnleſſe true teares conſiſt in hawking, hunting, gaming, or ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, which if they doe, God ſhall haue enough of that: but alas, theſe cannot waſh the ſoule from ſinne, or free the conſcience of his burden, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beſpot their ſoule more with ſin, heaping few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell to the fire for their greater torments. Where then ſhall I finde true teares? Surely amongſt the Clergie; for they bee the Prieſts of the Lord,<note place="margin">Clergy.</note> and euer ſhould be offering ſacrifices, not onely of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but alſo of teares, and that both for their owne ſinnes, and the ſinnes of the people; but with griefe I ſpeake it, that few, if any, is there to be found; for they are growne ſo fat, that they can neither weepe for themſelues, nor ſpeake to inſtruct the people. What ſhall I now doe? Or whither ſhall I trauell, to finde one cloth bedued with true teares? For
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:5137:54"/>
ſince I finde them not in the Court, nor in the Citie, nor in Weſtminſter Hall, nor in the Countrey, nor in the Gentry, nor in the Clergie, (I meane the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralitie of all theſe) whither will you then ſend me to finde this rare fountaine? I will command my Muſes once more to goe abroad, to ſee if they can finde this cleanſing riuer of <hi>Iordan,</hi> or bring me any tidings of the true Fullers earth: But whither? I haue ſearched all places, one onely excepted, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if they remaine not there, I boldly dare ſay, they haue no being in this land: and that place is <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Onely among the afflicted.</note> where the captiuated Iſraelites remaine, I meane, the afflicted, oppreſſed, and grieued ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of the Lord; whether it be in Court, or Citie, Weſtminſter Hall, or Countrey, Gentry or Clergie, or any place elſe; there, and onely there is this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious water to bee found, and not elſe-where: for theſe <hi>people weepe ſore in the night when they ſhould take their reſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>and their teares ceaſe not trickling downe their cheekes,</hi> till the Lord returne with comfort to their ſoules.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.1.</note> Theſe weepe at the <hi>remembrance of Sion,</hi> and are waſted with ſorrow, when they call to minde the dew of <hi>Hermon</hi> diſtilling vpon the Watch-tower of the Lord; therefore you that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to drinke of theſe teares, reſort with ſpeed to theſe people, leſt the Lord doe free them from the <hi>Egypt</hi> of this world, before wee haue learned to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Excuſe for not weeping.</note>Some there are that could finde in their hearts to weepe, yet dare not, and onely for feare of hurting the eye: But alas; this bucket will draw no water, nor this excuſe free the ſinner from ſorrow. Chriſt
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:5137:54"/>
had more walls to ſtop his paſſage to vs, and ſhall ſuch a ſlender hedge keepe vs from drawing neere to him by repentance? Be it granted, that the teares hurt the eie; yet who will not hurt one member for the good of all, rather then to cheriſh that and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the whole body? <hi>If thy ere offend thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.29, 30</note> Chriſts counſell is, <hi>to plucke it out, for better it is to enter into heauen with one member loſt, then into hell fire with all:</hi> Be it therefore that it hurt the eie,<note place="margin">Houle and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> yet if it hurt the eie naturall, it cures the eie ſpirituall, healeth the ſoule finally, and pleaſeth God perpetually. Teares,<note place="margin">The effects and nature of teares compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiuely.</note> as one Diuine ſaith, are hot and moiſt; hot, to warme the cold conſcience; moiſt, to mollifie the hard heart. They are ſalt and wet; ſalt, to ſeaſon the ſoule; wet, to cleanſe the conſcience. They are bitter and ſweet; bitter, to waine vs from the world, as Wormewood the Infant from the dug; ſweet, to ſeaſon all our ſorrowes, and to turne them into ioyes. In a word, they are a ſword, and a ſalue; a ſword, to cut the ſoule from ſinne; a ſalue, to cure and heale the ſoule againe: Feare not therefore to ſhed teares ſince they are of ſuch qualitie; for if the world were truly perſwaded of the benefit true teares doe bring, they would not bee hindred from weeping. <hi>Royard</hi> obſerueth ſix properties of true teares.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they doe <hi>Purgare,</hi> purge the ſoule:<note place="margin">Plainly they are ſix. <hi>Roy. in Peſt.</hi>
               </note> for as raine diſtilling from the clouds clarifies the aire; ſo the teares of the penitent purifies the heart; it makes the tongue to pray, the tongue makes the heart to relent, the heart makes the man to repent, &amp; repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance can neuer be begun, continued, and ended,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:5137:55"/>
without many teares, which cannot ceaſe till the heart be purged. I remember a certaine King had an Oxe-ſtall, which had not beene emptied of many yeares, at laſt was growne ſo ſoule, that it was thought men could hardly make it cleane in a life time: The King perceiuing that, preſently conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that if he could bring the Riuer which ran hard by his houſe to runne thorow it, that then it would quickly be cleanſed. No ſooner was this thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in his minde, but hee preſently put it in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, and at laſt with much labour and coſt, brought the riuer to runne thorow the oxe-ſtall with a very ſwift current, which riuer in three daies cleanſed that houſe, and carried all that filth away, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe could hardly euer haue beene cleanſed: euen ſo that heart of ours, which would aske a like time to cleanſe, by hearing, reading, praying, and receiuing, will in a ſhort time be purged, if teares be but ioyned with theſe: for true teares runne with ſuch a forceable current, that they will ſuffer no pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifaction to reſt long in the heart vncarried away; as <hi>Peter, Dauid, Marie Magdalen,</hi> with many more, can witneſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they doe <hi>illuminare,</hi> open the eies; for true penitentiall teares are as a ſoueraigne ſalue, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſtiffe lid pliable, and will eat out the web that hinders the ſight of Mercy: for Mercy is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured where the eie is vailed, and the eie is vailed where ſinne raigneth: but as the raine powring from the Clouds, clarifies the aire, and alaies the duſt, by which a man may ſee farre, both forward and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; euen ſo true teares alaies the duſt of ſinne,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:5137:55"/>
and that miſt of deſpaire inabling a man to ſee farre into Gods wonderfull mercies promiſed in Chriſt to his ſoule.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they do <hi>Corroborare,</hi> ſtrengthen the man: for theſe teares doe inable a Chriſtian to incounter with Satan, and to wreſtle with Chriſt; nay, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer Satan, and to ouercome Chriſt. Firſt, they doe conquer Satan: witneſſe our Sauiour; who by ſtrong cries and teares, receiued ſtrength from God his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to vanquiſh Satan, Death and Hell; for hee triumphed ouer them all vpon the Chariot of his Croſſe. Secondly, they ouercome Chriſt: witneſſe <hi>Iacob;</hi> who by weeping and praying had power ouer the Angell,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.6.</note> for as the dew of the Lord maketh <hi>Iſrael</hi> to grow as the Lilly, and to faſten his roots as the trees of <hi>Lebanon:</hi> ſo will true teares make a man ſtrong in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, they do <hi>Laetificare,</hi> reioyce the ſoule, and that both by making it fruitfull &amp; acceptable to the Lord. Firſt, by making it fruitfull; for as the water which falls from heauen, nouriſhes the earth, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth the dry ground, making it able to ſend forth fruit which reioyceth the heart of the ſower; euen ſo, true teares cauſeth the heart to ſend forth much good, which will reioyce the man in the Winter of aduerſitie and temptation. Secondly, it maketh a man acceptable in the ſight of the Lord: witneſſe <hi>Maries</hi> teares, which preferred her to Chriſt before all <hi>Marthaes</hi> dainties could her ſelfe: beſides, they bring a bleſſing, and a ioyfull harueſt; a bleſſing,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.5.</note> 
               <hi>For bleſſed are thoſe that weepe, they ſhall be comforted;</hi> a ioyfull harueſt, <hi>For they that ſow in teares, ſhall reape in ioy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:5137:56"/>Fiftly, they doe <hi>Eleuare,</hi> vp, for as <hi>Noes</hi> Arke, the more the water increaſed, the more it was eleuated: euen ſo, the more that teares abound, the more is the heart raiſed, and the affection ſet vpon God.</p>
            <p>Sixthly and laſtly, they doe <hi>Impetrare quicquid vult,</hi> obtaine whatſoeuer good a man would at the hands of God: witneſſe <hi>Hezekia,</hi> vpon whoſe teares the Lord delaies not to ſend vnto him the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> to remoue his feare,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 38.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.7, 8.</note> and aſſure him of his deſired wiſhes. And <hi>Dauid</hi> in danger of death and in doubt of falling, comming to the Lord with teares in his eies, was freed from the one, and ſtood vpright vpon the other; ſo that his ſoule returned to that reſt for which it longed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctr.</hi> Chriſt weeping for our ſinnes, not his owne, we ſhould weep for others ſins.</note>Thirdly, if Chriſt weepe for our ſinnes, wee are taught to weepe one for another. It is a dutie of loue that Chriſtians owe, to weepe one for another: If they were to loue none but themſelues, then were they to ſhed teares for none but themſelues. But we are commanded to loue our neighbours as our ſelues, therefore muſt weepe for other as for our ſelues. It hath beene the practiſe of Gods Church from the beginning, and ought not to be left in the declining age. The ancient cuſtome of the <hi>Iewes</hi> (which ſtill they doe retaine) was to rent their clothes at any blaſphemy ſpoken by others. <hi>Ieremy</hi> when he ſaw the wickedneſſe of his people, was vexed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 8.21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.1.</note> therefore wiſhed, <hi>O that my head were a Well of water, and my eies a fountaine of teares, that I might weepe night and day for the ſlaine of the Daughter of my people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7, 8.</note> This did <hi>Lot</hi> for <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> was
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:5137:56"/>
no whit behinde any, when his eies <hi>powred out riuers of teares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 130.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe men would not keepe the law of his God:</hi> Shall ſuch affection be found in Gods ancient people, and we to ſauour neuer a whit thereof? If our friends depart from vs, or die with vs, we can weep and mourne as faſt as any; but if we ſee a neighbour or a brother wedded to wickedneſſe, and ſunk almoſt paſt recouery into ſinne, we neuer mourne, nor ſhew any diſlike, but ſalue it vp with <hi>humanum eſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Others ſins not to be ſalued, but ſorrowed for.</note> ſo that for a young man to ſinne, is but a tricke of youth; for an old man, but an infirmitie of age; and in none at any time as it ſhould be lamented. Children are ſuffered to be wanton, becauſe their yeares are ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; youth is permitted to bee licentious, becauſe their age is luſtie; rich men are moued with vanitie, becauſe it is their portion; poore men are cuſtomed with folly, becauſe they liue in want; old men are drowned in ſuperſtition, becauſe they are neere their graues; women are wanton, becauſe they be beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, and all are ſinfull, yet by few or none lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: nay, are they not reioyced at,<note place="margin">Sinnes now moue not mourning, but mirch or mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, eſpecially the failings of Gods children.</note> and in theſe times made the principall cauſe to moue laughter? for if any man fall dangerouſly into ſinne, eſpecially the childe of God, either by infirmitie, blindneſſe, or being ouertaken on a ſudden by Satan, the world then flings away jeering, as hauing caught what of long time they watcht for: then with a ioyfull countenance they vaunt abroad, the whole, nay, more then the whole fall or ſailing of this poore childe of God, divulging to as many as they ſee, or at leaſtwiſe know, the time, the place, and the manner of that ſinne which was committed by ſuch
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:5137:57"/>
a perſon:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.52.</note> for as the <hi>Iſraelites reioyced at the fall of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah,</hi> ſo doth the world at the failings of the Saints of God.<note place="margin">Cato.</note> 
               <hi>Cato,</hi> that graue Senator of <hi>Rome,</hi> was neuer ſeene to laugh but once, and that was, when he eſpied out of his window an Aſſe eating of Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; wondring why that beaſt ſhould take pleaſure in pricks, that ſhould haue beene ſpurres to haue made him to take paines: So wee when wee ſee our brethren eating vp ſinnes like bread, and <hi>drinking vp iniquitie like water,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 15.16.</note> rather laugh with <hi>Democritus</hi> at their folly, then with <hi>Heraclitus</hi> lament their faults. I tell you brethren, there is no greater ſigne of a reprobate, then to laugh at ſinne and Sinners: for hee that can make wickedneſſe his chiefeſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime, and the faults of others his greateſt ioy, is iuſt like to Satan our greateſt enemy,<note place="margin">Satans greateſt ſolace is to ſee men ſinning.</note> who reioyceth at nothing more then when men commit ſinne. Therefore when thou ſeeſt ſinne in any, be it in thy wife, children, friends, ſeruants, or enemies, take heed thou reioyce not at it, but weepe and mourne for it: preſent not <hi>Omnia bene,</hi> all is well: For any man being fallen into ſinne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Our hearts ſhould ſmite vs when wee ſee another ſinne.</hi> Pia eſt illa tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlitia alienis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>js ingemiſcere, non adhaerere: Contriſtari, non implicari: dolore contrahi, non at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trahi. Auguſt. Ber. homil. de reſurrectione Dom.</note> is in a very miſerable caſe till hee returne vnto the Lord by true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; wherefore let thy heart ſmite thee when thou ſeeſt thy brother ſleeping in the bed of ſinne. For, <hi>This is a godly ſorrow to pitie mens ſinnes, and not to be polluted by them; to ſorrow for them, and not ſinke into them, to be drawne away in dolour, and not drawne away with delight.</hi> Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> makes mention in one of his Homilies, of an old man, who when hee ſaw any man ſinne, wept and lamented for him; being asked why he ſo grieued for others, anſwered:
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:5137:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Hodie ille, cras ego;</hi> hee fell to day, I may fall to morrow. If we could but remember this, it would rather draw bloud from the heart then ioy, when we ſee a man fallen into ſinne; therefore when thou ſeeſt a murdering <hi>Caine,</hi> a theeuiſh <hi>Achan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 7. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 5. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Exod.</hi> 9. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21. <hi>Eſay</hi> 37. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. <hi>Luke</hi> 15. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. <hi>Acts</hi> 12. <hi>Luke</hi> 16. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.48. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.25. <hi>Luke</hi> 7.37.</note> a lying <hi>Gehezie,</hi> an inceſtuous <hi>Amnon,</hi> a churliſh <hi>Nabal;</hi> a reſiſting <hi>Cora,</hi> a filthy <hi>Sodomite,</hi> a murmuring <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite,</hi> a rebellious <hi>Abſolom,</hi> an idolatrous <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> and an oppreſſing <hi>Pharao:</hi> a painted <hi>Ieſabel,</hi> a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming <hi>Sennacherib,</hi> a railing <hi>Rabſachath,</hi> a ſcoffing <hi>Michal,</hi> a ſpending <hi>Prodigall,</hi> a curſing <hi>Shemei,</hi> a proud <hi>Herod,</hi> a gluttonous <hi>Diues,</hi> a traiterous <hi>Iudas,</hi> an hypocriticall <hi>Phariſie,</hi> a wanton <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> an tyrannicall <hi>Nero,</hi> a bloudy <hi>Bonner,</hi> and an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate <hi>Iulian,</hi> or any other ſinner whatſoeuer, Oh weepe and lament for them, knowing not how ſoone God may with-draw his grace from thee, and ſuffer thee to fall as foule as any of them into the like ſinnes! I conclude this point with that place of <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> where the Lord commands a marke to be ſet vpon the <hi>foreheads of all thoſe that mourne and cry for all the abominations done in the midſt of Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem for their preſeruation:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.4, 5.</note> But to take notice of all thoſe which did not onely laugh at ſinne, but would not lament for ſinne for their deſtruction: O therefore let vs with our louing Sauiour, ſorrow and grieue for our ſinfull brethren, vſing all meanes to turne them from their wicked courſe of life; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing the man, but hating his manners, rebuking him ſharply for his great offence;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 27.5.</note> for an <hi>open rebuke is better then a ſecret loue:</hi> then it may be, thou ſhalt pull his ſoule from Satan, which if thou canſt but
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:5137:58"/>
ſo doe, thou maieſt ſit downe with ioyfull <hi>Iacob</hi> when he heard of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> life;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.25.</note> 
               <hi>I haue enough, my ſonne is liuing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Cauſe of Chriſts teares, was <hi>Propter ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la poenae,</hi> the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to which they were ſubiect.</note>Our laſt point is the ſecond cauſe of Chriſts teares, which is <hi>Propter mala poenae,</hi> the euill of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment that was to be inflicted vpon them; for as God he ſaw, nay rather fore-ſaw from the Watch-tower of this Mount, the future temptations and vtter deſolations both of Church and people, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Citizens, which whileſt he beheld as God, he lamented as Man. Should I enter into their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I ſhould diue into an Ocean without bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, and loſe my ſelfe in a wilderneſſe of diſcourſe: therfore I refuſe to tel you how the ſword deſtroied <hi>twentie thouſand in one day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſephus.</note> 
               <hi>and how the Edomites let in by Iehochanan, ſlew eight thouſand and fiue hundred of the wealthieſt Citizens in one night.</hi> I will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late how the peſtilence went thorow ſtitch, deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more then an <hi>hundred thouſand</hi> during the ſiege, neither wil I ſtand to ſhew you how the famine ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red none, but made the Nobles to eat the leather of their Coaches as they rid, Ladies to ſcrape in dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hils for their food,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lament.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Iere.</hi> 31.15.</note> and many <hi>women to eat the fruit of their owne wombe, and children which were but a ſpan long:</hi> as for Rats, Mice, Frogges, Snailes, and ſuch like, they were no ordinary food in <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> at this time, for vengeance did ſo ſtirre her within and without, that there was nothing but weeping, howling, and great lamentation. Not onely <hi>Rachel weeping for her children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 2.</note> but the children weeping for their parents, ſeruants for their Maſters, and the poore for their maintainers. If a man at this time
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:5137:58"/>
had beene in <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> his heart could not but haue melted, to haue ſeene the deaths of ſome, the cryings of others, and the miſeries of all. For if he looke of one hand, hee might ſee men and women halfe dead, and halfe liuing, bathing themſelues in one anothers wounds, crying out for ſome relen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hearted man to kill them out-right, and to rid them out of their lingring tormenting paine. If he looke on the other-ſide, hee ſhould ſee the ſonnes, daughters, and ſeruants of the Elders thus ſlaine, crying vp and downe the Citie like mad men, with their eies and hands extended towards heauen, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Iuſtice Lord, Iuſtice Lord, Iuſtice vpon the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt depriuers of our friends and maintainers. If he looke before him, hee ſhould ſee the gray haires of the ancient lying vpon the pauements of the Citie, as if they had bin ſtrewed with ruſhes. If he lookt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him, there he ſhould ſee virgins lamenting the vntimely death of their Louers: which way ſoeuer he had lookt at this time in <hi>Hieruſalems</hi> miſery, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, death, and deſtruction, muſt needs be his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect. But I ceaſe to proſecute it largely, becauſe it would be too tedious both to me that ſpeake, and to you that heare; neither will I tell you of the ancient buildings, glorious Temples, and ſtately Palaces of <hi>Dauid, Solomons,</hi> and the reſt of the ancient Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> how they were all deſtroied, and pulled downe to the ground, not hauing <hi>a ſtone left vpon a ſtone,</hi> according as our Sauiour fore-told them; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo much as now we may ſay of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> as one ſpake of <hi>Priams</hi> Towne; <hi>Iam ſeges eſt, vbi Troia fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it;</hi> Now is that a Corne-field, which was c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſt
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:5137:59"/>
called <hi>Troy;</hi> ſo now is that a barren ground, and a mount of ſtones, which was earſt called beautifull <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> All this, with a thouſand times more our Sauiour fore-ſaw, which whilſt hee beheld it as God,<note place="margin">Magiſtrates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to puniſh ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the malefactors caſe, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per mercy with Iuſtice. <hi>Grego.</hi>
               </note> lamented it as man. To draw towards an end, though there be no end in the matter it ſelfe, and to temper my ſpeech according to the time: The reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due belongs to all Magiſtrates and Iudges, but more eſpecially to you that are Magiſtrates and Iudges of, and in this honourable Citie of <hi>London. Omnis Chriſti actio eſt noſtra inſtructio,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory, id eſt,</hi> Euery action of Chriſt is our inſtruction; if all ours, then this more particularly yours; namely, to temper Mercy and Iuſtice together, that is, If at any time in Iuſtice you are compelled to puniſh a malefactor, yet in the midſt of Iuſtice, let Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſhine forth; be not vnlike our compaſſionate Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, who powres forth teares when he pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth Iudgement: for if this be wanting, all your Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice will be conuerted into tyranny; a mans eſtate, name, or life, is not to be plaid or ieſted withall, <hi>Noli me tangere:</hi> for theſe three, or at the leaſt two of them can neuer be reſtored againe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sulpitius.</note>Memorable is that fact of <hi>Sulpitius,</hi> an ancient <hi>Romane,</hi> who neuer paſſed the ſentence of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to execution vpon any man, but his teares were ſeene to trickle from his eies, as if water had beene powred on his face.<note place="margin">Bias.</note> And <hi>Bias</hi> that was a Iudge of <hi>Greece,</hi> neuer gaue ſentence of death vpon any, but he wept for them.<note place="margin">Theodoſius.</note> 
               <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperor was euer ſo mercifull, that hee alwaies gaue one daies libertie to the enemy for meditation, before he would vſe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:5137:59"/>
any violence. Alſo I haue read of a certaine Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, who when he beſieged any Citie, the firſt day would diſplay a white Enſigne in token of Mercy;<note place="margin">By no meanes to inſult ouer or deride the guilty in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencing or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing.</note> the next day a blacke Banner, in token of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the third day red colours, in token of bloud, fire and ſword, without any Mercy; they therefore are monſters in Nature, which will ſhew no mercy to their Brethren, but in ſuperſtition, malice, or vaine-glory, wrong thoſe whom they ought to iudge with equity. There ought to be a ſympathy, and a fellow-feeling in mens minds, eſpecially in a Ruler great compaſſion, wiſhing from the bottome of their hearts there were no ſuch cauſe of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo to be ſuffered: for a Magiſtrate ought not to be like the proud <hi>Phariſes,</hi> and inſolent <hi>Prieſts,</hi> who when they had taken our Sauiour, delighted not in any thing ſo much, as in <hi>mocking, ſpitting, buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feting,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>railing, reuiling, ſcourging, ſcorning, crowning</hi> him with <hi>thornes,</hi> and <hi>crucifying him betweene two Theeues.</hi> They were not content to take his life, and to ſhed his bloud, but loaded his body with moſt ſhamefull calumniations; nay, when they had him where they would haue him, namely vpon the Croſſe, then did they reioyce and ſhout out of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, <hi>nodding</hi> their heads, <hi>ſhaking</hi> their hands,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.</note> and cried with their voice; <hi>If thou bee the Sonne of God, come downe from the Croſſe, and we will beleeue thee: he ſaued others, but himſelfe he cannot ſaue.</hi> Neither would I haue you like to <hi>Voleſus,</hi> who was a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſull of <hi>Aſia,</hi> liuing vnder the Emperor <hi>Auguſtus:</hi> for he is recorded for a very famous Tyrant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that when he had beheaded three hundred in
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:5137:60"/>
one day, with a proud and loftie countenance hee walked amongſt the dead carkaſes, as if he had done ſome great exploit, and at laſt cried out, <hi>O rem regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, id eſt,</hi> Oh an act fit for a King! But ſurely wee may anſwer him thus: <hi>O rem Diabolicam,</hi> O an act fit for a Deuill! For this doing beſeemeth not a King or Magiſtrate, they ſhould rather with Chriſt here, grieue that any ſhould grow to that extremity, as to deſerue ſuch judgement. Courteſie ſhould be the Crowne of a King, Compaſſion the handle, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice the edge, Anger the backe, and Mercy the point of a Magiſtrates ſword; therefore you that are Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, call to the Lord early and late, morning and euening, that hee may drop downe kindneſſe and mercy into your hearts, that vncourteous and churliſh actions may alwaies bee farre from your hands: For it is not in our time as it was in the daies of <hi>Ieremy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 48.10.</note> that <hi>curſed is he that keepeth backe his ſword from bloud:</hi> but bleſſed is he that ſpareth, and bleſſed is he that ſaueth: For thoſe whom you judge, are they not your Brethren? Yea, and that from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wombe;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.10.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hauing one <hi>Father,</hi> which is the Lord in heauen; and one Mother, which is the Church on earth:<note place="margin">A Magiſtrate in doing ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice may be guiltie of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice, and ſubiect to Gods iudgement, failing in the end and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9.25, 26. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.4.</note> therefore when you pronounce judgement vpon any, looke it bee done with an vpright heart, and to the glory of God: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe whilſt you giue ſentence againſt man, the Lord giueth ſentence againſt you. <hi>Iehu King of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el executed the judgements of the Lord vpon the houſe of Ahab, according to all the word of the Lord: yet himſelfe is threatned to be puniſhed becauſe he did it with a cruell and bloudy affection.</hi> The worke was
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:5137:60"/>
good, but his heart was euill: the deed done was righteous, but the manner of doing it was corrupt, for he reſpected not the glory of God, but his owne reuenge, which made the Lord to viſit him and his houſe, and all <hi>Iſrael</hi> for it. See therefore not onely what you doe, but alſo to what end and purpoſe you doe it. Bee not vnlike the Lord your God, who is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Father of mercies:<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3.</note> But when you iudge, let clemency ſhine forth, knowing that one day you ſhall bee iudged your ſelues; and what meaſure you giue vnto others, ſhall bee ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at the laſt by the Lord vnto you againe.</p>
            <p>It is time to gather vp all my broken fragments into one basket, and to winde vp all my ends vpon one clue, therefore let my laſt concluſion be your exhortation; <hi>Hieruſalems</hi> deſtruction our inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a fearefull <hi>Felix quem faciunt,</hi> to all thoſe that feare not judgements threatned: as God hath made you Magiſtrates, ſo execute your places, and ſhew your ſelues worthy of your calling: Let <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> be ſtill a patterne for your practiſe, that as he was carefull to come to view, to weepe, ſo doe you; let not your paines be burdenſome to your bodies, wicked obiects pleaſing to your minds, nor true teares offenſiue to your cheekes: It was not ſo with our Sauiour, I hope it will not be ſo with you.</p>
            <p>I remember a certaine <hi>Roman</hi> Generall, after the beſieging ſuch a Towne, was demanded by one of his friends of his proceedings, who anſwered; <hi>Veni, vidi, vici:</hi> I came, I ſaw, I conquered, But if you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand what ſucceſſe Chriſt had againſt <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> he may thus anſwer, <hi>Veni, vidi, fleui;</hi> I came, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:5137:61"/>
I wept, not ouercame; for his teares was not able to breake into the ſtony hearts of thoſe wicked <hi>Iewes;</hi> if not theirs, let it be ours, &amp; teach you to do the like;<note place="margin">Magiſtrates where they cannot draw by compulſion, ſhould win by compaſsion: howſoeuer be ſtrong, vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, and looke neere home.</note> namely, where you cannot draw by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, win by compaſſion; you are the armes of our Citie, therefore ought to be ſtrong; you are the pillars of a Common-wealth, therefore muſt haue a good foundation; you are our Watchmen, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought not to be drowſie; you are our Keepers, looke therefore you be not found gadders too farre from home, when we haue moſt need of your helps. When <hi>Moſes was in the Mountaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.19.</note> 
               <hi>Iſrael plaied the wanton:</hi> and if you be not carefull, our Citie will be extreme ſinfull; it is ſo already, yet it will be worſe if you be not wary; for we haue ſo many back-win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and obſcure corners, that vnleſſe you ſearch narrowly, you will neuer finde out thoſe Cages of vncleane birds that harbour within them: but I leaue the labour to you, the bleſſing to God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">London in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things to be praiſed.</note>Many things (Right Honorable) we may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you for, as building of Hoſpitals, repairing of Churches, maintaining of Schooles, rewarding of learning, feeding the hungry, clothing the naked, prouiding for widowes, caring for Orphans, guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding your Citie:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.8.</note> but aboue all, for <hi>your faith which is ſpoken of thorowout the whole world;</hi> yet as the Lord ſaid to the Church of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> ſo may I ſay to you,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ap.</hi> 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>Neuertheleſſe, I haue a few things againſt you,</hi> which are theſe: Why doe you ſuffer pride to iet vp and downe by your faces, and to liue in your houſes without correction? Why doe you ſuffer the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerns and Ale-houſes (which for multitude is the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:5137:61"/>
ſhame of our Citie, and for order the baine of our Citie) to be more frequented then the Church, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times roome being to be had in the one, none in the other, and that vpon the Lords day? Why doe you ſuffer Stewes and Brothell-houſes to liue at your elbowes; nay, vnder your noſes, as though you had afforded them a toleration?<note place="margin">This made <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes</hi> to laugh, when he ſaw how the great theeues hung vp the leſſer.</note> Why doe you ſuffer little theeues to goe to the gallowes, and great theeues to eſcape without any puniſhment (I meane thoſe that rob and ſteale by falſe wares, falſe weights, falſe meaſures, and falſe tongues?) I will not mention what elſe I publikely ſpake (and that not without a credible Author, though then I na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him not) becauſe the aduerſarie ſhall haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by me to detect your vnſpotted Charitie withall, becauſe you might be ignorant of it: but I hope the ſound of this Trumpet hath ſo rowſed you from the bed of reſt, that that little which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, ſhall ſoone bee reformed without any more threatnings from the Lord. If you doe not, God will not long ſee our want, and this wickedneſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed: for though he came in mildneſſe here to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> he ſhall come in terror hereafter to vs, and pay vs what wee haue deſerued. I cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelfe that <hi>Sodom</hi> lieth in aſhes for greater offences, then haue beene found in vs within theſe few daies. For I haue ſeene drunkenneſſe, drunke till it thirſted, and gluttony vomit till it hungred againe; I haue ſeene Gods word contemned; his Saboaths profaned, his Sacraments neglected, his Miniſters abuſed, his children moſt ſhamefully derided. What ſhall I ſay, if I ſhould reckon vp all the wickedneſſe
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:5137:62"/>
that I haue ſeene in this ſhort time of my life, it would aske a large time to name them, and drinke vp a great volume to vnfold them; therefore I will ſay no more but onely this: beſeeching you, that as God hath placed you aboue others, ſo to looke to others, haue a care of their ſoules that are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to your gouernment as to your owne. Goe forth into the high way with <hi>thoſe ſeruants of the King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.10.</note> walke the ſtreets, ranſacke the irreligious and idle corners of this Citie;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 14.23.</note> 
               <hi>Compell them to come to the houſe of the Lord</hi> for feare, which will not come for loue, that their roomes which now are emptie may be filled: If you refuſe this, you refuſe to wage war with ſinne, and to waken your Brother out of his wicked ſleepe: and if you refuſe to wage warre with ſinne, you deny the colours of Chriſt your Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and reiect the Enſignes of God your Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. If therefore you will haue God to bleſſe you, Chriſt to ſaue you, and the holy Trinitie to defend you, keepe your oath with your Soueraigne, bee faithfull to your Captaine, and fight againſt ſinne that you may win many ſoules to Chriſt. If ſleepe would kill your friend, would you ſuffer him ſtill to ſlumber and not awake him?<note place="margin">What care and reſpect Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors ſhould haue ouer and towards thoſe who are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their charge, in the Teſtimony of the Heathens. <hi>Xenophon in Cyro.</hi>
               </note> Surely no; why then doe you ſuffer your Brethren and Siſters to ſleepe in ſinne, and to ſnore and ſnort in the bed of wickedneſſe, and neuer once awake them with a laſh of Iuſtice? The old Heathens to note vnto vs the great care that Magiſtrates ſhould haue of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ouer whom they were placed, intituled them Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the people, becauſe they muſt eſteeme and imagine <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to be
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:5137:62"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; his Countrey to be his houſe, his Citizens his fellowes, his friends, his children, and his children his ſoule.<note place="margin">Hom. Illiad. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Homer</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>Agamemnon</hi> to his great praiſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Shepherd of the people; becauſe his ſleepe was ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or neuer <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſweet, pleaſant, or quiet.<note place="margin">Plutarchus.</note> Such was <hi>Epaminondas,</hi> of whom it is reported, that when others feaſted and ſlept, hee did faſt, watch, vſe ſobrietie, view the Tents, and walke the wals; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the ancient <hi>Perſian</hi> Kings, when they ſhould take their reſt, had a Chamberlaine who vſually came vnto them, ſaying; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>id eſt,</hi> Ariſe, ariſe, O King, and looke about thy bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe. Had the heathens this care ouer their charge and people who knew not Chriſt, and will not you that know Chriſt and his will, haue much more care? then ſhall theſe people riſe vp in iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you: Awake, awake, therefore you Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, I ſay awake, both early and late, and walke about the ſtreets of this Citie, that you may finde the Crimſon coloured ſinnes without any varniſh: then thruſt them out of the gates, and bring Chriſt into the Citie, who hath ſtood this threeſcore and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ten yeares, waiting for an entrance, for feare left he depart, &amp; you neuer more enioy his preſence: God hath giuen you both gifts and places not for your ſelues alone, but alſo, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for the common good of Church and Citie, Towne and Country, which if you carefully and truly performe, aiming more at the glory of God, then your owne praiſe; the peoples good, then your owne eaſe: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will the Country be leſſe miſerable, the citie leſſe
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:5137:63"/>
a louer of pleaſure,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.4.</note> and both more louers of God; the Country more plentifull, the Citie more beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the Country flowing with goodneſſe, the Citie ouerflowing with happineſſe. In a word, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try ſhall flouriſh and reioyce, the Citie with a loud ſounding voice ſhall ſend forth your praiſe to the vttermoſt parts of the earth; yea, it ſhall be a crowne to your heads, a recompence to our labours, a ſweet ſmelling ſacrifice vnto the Lord, the ioy of Angels, the triumph of Saints, a bleſſing to the Citie, a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of ſoules, and an euerlaſting happineſſe to your poſteritie; nay, more then all this, if you thus doe, it will ſo pleaſe our Sauiour, as that it will ſtop his teares, reioyce his heart, confound his foes, win his fauour, vnfold his mercy, vnlocke his kingdome, that our ſoules may haue free paſſage to enter; firſt into grace in this life, and hereafter into glory in the life to come: Where God the Father ſhall take you by the right hand, and lead you to the fountaines of water, waſhing all your garments white in the bloud of the Lambe; Chriſt Ieſus ſhall imbrace you in the armes of his mercy, crowne you with crownes of glory: at whoſe Coronation all the Angels in heauen ſhall applaud your praiſe, and God himſelfe ſhall ſay Amen to your felicities.</p>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:5137:63"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
